[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
大卫·马兰：好的。
This is CS50.
这是 CS50。
This is week 2 wherein we will ultimately learn how to use memory,
这是第二周，我们将最终学习如何使用内存，
but we thought we'd first begin with a bit of story time.
但我们想先从讲故事开始。
And in fact, allow me to walk over to our brave volunteers who
事实上，请允许我走到我们勇敢的志愿者身边，他们
have joined us already.
已经加入了我们。
First here on my left, we have who?
首先，在我左边，我们有谁？
AKSHAYA: Hi, I'm Akshaya.
阿克沙雅：你好，我是阿克沙雅。
I'm a first year in Mathews, and I'm planning
我是一年级学生，在马修斯学习，我正在计划
on concentrating in chemical and physical biology and CS.
专注于化学和物理生物学以及计算机科学。
DAVID MALAN: Wonderful, welcome.
大卫·马兰：太棒了，欢迎。
And let me have you hang on to the microphone
请你拿着麦克风
first because we've asked Akshaya to tell us a short story.
先，因为我们请阿克沙雅给我们讲个短故事。
So in your envelope, you have the beginnings of a story.
所以，你的信封里，有故事的开头。
If you wouldn't mind reading it aloud.
如果你不介意大声朗读。
And as she reads this, allow us to give some thought as to what
当她读的时候，让我们思考一下阿克沙雅的阅读水平，怎么说呢。
level Akshaya reads at, so to speak.
就好像她的阅读水平一样。
AKSHAYA: All right, it's a long one, get ready.
阿克沙雅：好的，它很长，准备好。
One fish, two fish, red fish, blue fish.
一条鱼，两条鱼，红鱼，蓝鱼。
DAVID MALAN: All right, very well done.
大卫·马兰：好的，做得很好。
What grade level would you say she reads at if you think back
你认为她的阅读水平是几年级，如果你回忆一下
to your middle school, grade school, when
你的中学，小学，当
maybe teacher said you read at this level or maybe this level or this one
老师也许说你的阅读水平是这个级别，或者也许是这个级别，或者那个级别
here?
在这里？
So OK, no offense taken yet.
所以，好的，还没人冒犯。
AUDIENCE: 1st grade.
观众：一年级。
DAVID MALAN: I'm sorry?
大卫·马兰：你说什么？
AUDIENCE: 1st grade.
观众：一年级。
DAVID MALAN: 1st grade.
大卫·马兰：一年级。
OK, so first grade is just about right.
好的，所以一年级正好合适。
And in fact, according to one algorithm, this text here,
事实上，根据一种算法，这里这段文字，
one fish, two fish, red fish, blue fish, would indeed
一条鱼，两条鱼，红鱼，蓝鱼，确实
be considered to actually be 1st grade or just before first grade.
被认为是实际的一年级水平，或者刚过一年级。
So let's-- and why is that, though?
所以，让我们，为什么这样呢？
Why did you say 1st grade?
为什么你说是一年级？
AUDIENCE: It's very basic.
观众：它非常基础。
DAVID MALAN: It's very basic.
大卫·马兰：它非常基础。
But what is it about these words that are very basic?
但是这些单词中什么很基础呢？
Do you want to identify yourself?
你想自我介绍吗？
AKSHAYA: Sure.
阿克沙雅：当然。
They're all one syllable and they're very simple like colors and stuff
它们都是一个音节的，而且很简单，就像颜色和那些东西
like that.
就像那样。
DAVID MALAN: Spot-on.
大卫·马兰：完全正确。
So like they're very short words they're very short sentences.
所以，就像它们是很短的单词，很短的句子。
And you would expect that of a younger person.
而且你会期望一个更年轻的人会这样。
All right, let's go ahead and hand the mic to your next volunteer
好的，让我们把麦克风递给下一个志愿者
here if you'd like to introduce yourself.
如果你想自我介绍。
ETHAN: Yes.
伊森：好的。
Hi, I'm Ethan.
你好，我是伊森。
I'm a first year in Canada, and I'll be concentrating in economics.
我是一年级学生，在加拿大学习，我将专注于经济学。
DAVID MALAN: Wonderful.
大卫·马兰：太棒了。
And in your folder, we have another story to share.
你的文件夹里，我们还有另一个故事要分享。
ETHAN: Congratulations.
伊森：恭喜你。
Today is your day.
今天是你的日子。
You're off to great places.
你要去很棒的地方。
You're off and away.
你出发了。
DAVID MALAN: So this text might sound familiar, particularly
大卫·马兰：所以这段文字可能听起来很熟悉，尤其是在
on the heels of high school, perhaps.
高中毕业之后。
What grade level might he be reading at?
他的阅读水平可能是几年级？
So maybe 5th grade.
所以也许是五年级。
And why 5th grade?
为什么是五年级？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: OK.
大卫·马兰：好的。
Yeah.
是的。
So a little more complicated.
所以稍微复杂一点。
Like the words-- we've got some more punctuation, we have an apostrophe,
比如这些单词，我们有一些标点符号，我们有一个撇号，
we have longer sentences.
我们有更长的句子。
And indeed, according to one algorithm, not quite 5th grade,
事实上，根据一种算法，还没有到五年级，
but we would adjudicate your reading level to be 3rd.
但我们会判断你的阅读水平是三年级。
But let's see if we can't do one final flourish here
但是，让我们看看是否可以在这里做最后的润色
if you'd like to introduce yourself and your story.
如果你想自我介绍和你的故事。
MIKE: Hi, I'm Mike.
迈克：你好，我是迈克。
I'm also a first year.
我也是一年级。
I'm in Weld, and I'm planning on concentrating
我在韦尔德，我正在计划专注于
in biomedical engineering.
生物医学工程。
DAVID MALAN: Welcome.
大卫·马兰：欢迎。
And your tale?
你的故事呢？
MIKE: It was a bright, cold day in April and the clocks were striking 13.
迈克：那是四月里一个晴朗寒冷的日子，钟敲了13下。
Winston Smith, his chin nuzzled into his breast in an effort
温斯顿·史密斯，下巴紧贴着胸膛，努力地
to escape the vile wind, slipped quickly through the glass doors
躲避恶风，迅速穿过玻璃门
of victory mansions, though not quickly enough
胜利大厦，尽管不够快
to prevent a swirl of gritty dust from entering along with him.
阻止一股沙尘随他一起进入。
DAVID MALAN: All right, so escalated quickly.
大卫·马兰：好的，所以迅速升级了。
And someone's guess at this reading level?
有人猜一下他的阅读水平？
AUDIENCE: 1984.
观众：1984。
DAVID MALAN: What's that?
大卫·马兰：你说什么？
Oh, OK, 1984 is indeed the text in question, and in what
哦，好的，1984确实是讨论的文本，你是在几年级读的这本书？
grade did you perhaps read that book?
你也许是在几年级读的这本书？
So I'm hearing 8th, I'm hearing 10th.
所以，我听到的是八年级，我听到的是十年级。
So indeed, 10th grade is what a certain algorithm would actually
所以，事实上，十年级是某种算法实际上
adjudicate that reading level to be at.
判断的阅读水平。
And consider now the heuristics.
现在考虑一下启发式方法。
So we started with very small words, very small sentences, very easy words,
所以我们从非常小的单词，非常小的句子，非常简单的单词开始，
and then things sort of escalated into more interesting, more
然后事情逐渐升级，变得更有意思，更多
sophisticated English, more interesting sentence construction and the like.
复杂的英语，更有趣的句子结构等等。
So I bet if we could somehow capture those characteristics of text,
所以，我打赌，如果我们能以某种方式捕捉到文本的那些特征，
the length of the words and the lengths of the sentences
单词的长度和句子的长度
and the position of the punctuation, I daresay,
以及标点符号的位置，我敢说，
even using week 1 material and, today, week 2 material,
即使使用第一周的材料和，今天，第二周的材料，
we'll be able to actually write code and implement an algorithm like that
我们实际上能够编写代码，并实现像这样的算法。
can take these spoken words, put them to paper,
可以把这些口语文字写到纸上，
and actually analyze roughly what that reading level might be.
并实际分析一下这个阅读水平大约是多少。
So that's just a teaser of what lies ahead.
所以这只是对未来内容的预告。
For now, allow us to thank our volunteers, each of whom
现在，让我们感谢我们的志愿者，每一位志愿者
gets a wonderful parting gift here to read at home.
都会收到一份很棒的告别礼物，可以带回家阅读。
[APPLAUSE]
[鼓掌]
All right.
好的。
And Thank you all so much.
非常感谢大家。
So with that said, there's another domain that we'll explore this week,
话虽如此，本周我们将探索另一个领域，
and indeed, what you'll find in the coming weeks
而且，你会发现，在接下来的几周里，
is that beyond just focusing on some of the fundamentals and the basics
除了关注一些基础知识和基本概念之外，
like we've really done in the past couple of weeks talking about loops
就像我们在过去几周谈论循环时所做的那样，
and conditionals and Boolean expressions,
还有条件语句和布尔表达式，
really building blocks or puzzle pieces that we can assemble together,
这些都是我们能够组装在一起的真正意义上的构建块或拼图碎片，
we're going to increasingly start talking about applications
我们将越来越多地开始讨论这些概念的应用，
of these ideas which, after all, is why any field is perhaps
毕竟，这正是任何领域可能
important and applicable.
重要且可应用的原因。
So here, for instance, we'll consider not only reading levels today,
因此，例如，我们今天不仅要考虑阅读水平，
and in turn, in problem set 2 this week, but also the world of cryptography,
而且，在本周的习题集 2 中，还要考虑密码学的世界，
which is the art, the science of scrambling, encrypting
密码学是混淆、加密信息的艺术，是科学。
information, and ciphering it in such a way
它以这样的方式对信息进行加密，
that you can send a message securely through the internet, through the air,
以便你可以安全地通过互联网、通过无线电发送信息，
through any medium even though someone might intercept it.
通过任何媒介，即使有人可能拦截它。
Ideally, thanks to cryptography, they shouldn't
理想情况下，由于密码学的存在，他们不应该
be able to decrypt it or actually determine what it there says.
能够解密它，或者真正确定它上面写了什么。
So for instance, if you were to receive a message like this, at first glance,
例如，如果你收到像这样的消息，乍一看，
it's indeed a bit cryptic.
它确实有点神秘。
Three words maybe, but by day's end, we'll
可能三个词，但到今天结束时，我们将
have decrypted even this message for you.
为你解密这条消息。
So up until now, though, we've had some sort of conceptual training wheels on.
不过，到目前为止，我们一直都在使用概念上的辅助轮。
And I gave us this picture last week when we introduced the tool make via
上周我们介绍工具 make 时，我就画了这个图，
which you can make programs out of your source code because you need to turn
你就可以用源代码制作程序，因为你需要将
that source code into machine code, the 0's and 1's.
源代码转换成机器代码，也就是 0 和 1。
And in the middle here was this thing called a compiler.
中间这个东西就叫做编译器。
But it really has been kind of an abstraction for us,
但对我们来说，它实际上一直都是一个抽象的概念，
and we've sort of had these metaphorical and physical training
我们一直在使用这种隐喻性的和实际上的辅助轮，
wheels here in the sense that we haven't really
从某种意义上来说，我们并没有真正
needed to care like what the compiler is doing, how it works and so forth.
需要关心编译器在做什么，它是如何工作的等等。
But today, what we thought we'd do is peel back a bit of that layer so
但是今天，我们想做的是剥开那一层的部分内容，这样
that even though after today you'll continue
即使在今天之后，你仍然会继续
to be able to use commands like make and sort of return
使用像 make 这样的命令，并回归到
to the beautiful abstraction that is not caring about some
这种美丽抽象的状态，这种状态是不关心一些
of these lower-level details, we'll offer you
底层细节的，我们会为你提供
a glimpse of how some of these things work.
对这些东西是如何工作的有一个简单的了解。
Because so that inevitably when something goes wrong,
因为这样，当不可避免地出现错误时，
you've got some bug, you're having some problem,
你遇到了一个错误，你遇到了一个问题，
you'll have a bottom-up understanding of what it could actually be.
你将会从底层向上地理解它究竟是什么。
And indeed, these basics, you'll find, will very often
而且，你会发现，这些基本概念往往会
help you troubleshoot problems and really solve problems more generally.
帮助你排查问题，更普遍地解决问题。
So here, for instance, is the code that we keep coming back to.
所以，例如，这就是我们一直在使用的代码。
And this code here is the simplest of C programs that just says "hello, world."
这段代码是 C 语言中最简单的程序，它只输出“hello, world”。
This is the source code.
这是源代码。
This, we claimed, was the corresponding machine code.
我们声称，这是相应的机器代码。
And it was that program called a compiler that
而那个叫做编译器的程序
converted one into the other.
将一个转换成另一个。
But let's dive a little more deeply this week
但本周，让我们更深入地了解一下
into what we mean by compiling code.
我们所说的编译代码是什么意思。
Like what is happening so that by day's end,
比如，到今天结束的时候，
nothing really feels like magic anymore.
一切都变得不再像魔法一样。
It's not just that it goes from source code to machine code
它不仅仅是从源代码到机器代码
and that's that, you understand what's actually being done for you,
就是这样，你明白为你做了什么，
and frankly, what other humans have done over the decades to make
坦白地说，还有几十年来，其他人做了些什么，才让
make as beautifully abstract and as simple as it now might seem to be.
make 变得如此抽象，如此简单，就像现在看起来那样。
So here are a couple of commands that you've
所以，这里有一些你一直以来习惯使用的命令，当你想
been in the habit of running when you want to first compile your code
编译你的代码，然后执行你的代码时，就会使用这些命令。
and then execute your code.
然后执行你的代码。
But it turns out that make is actually running another command for you.
但事实证明，make 实际上是在为你运行另一个命令。
The first of several white lies we'll tell in the course
这是我们这门课程中要讲的第一个善意的谎言，
is that make itself is not a compiler, per se.
就是 make 本身并非严格意义上的编译器。
It's actually a program that automatically runs a compiler for you.
它实际上是一个为你自动运行编译器的程序。
And by that, I mean this.
我的意思是这个。
Let me go over to VS Code here and let me create our familiar hello.c program.
让我到 VS Code 中创建一个我们熟悉的 hello.c 程序。
And I'm going to go ahead and do include stdio.h, int main void, and inside
我将继续执行包含 stdio.h、int main void，以及里面
of the curly braces, printf "hello," comma, "world," backslash n semicolon.
花括号的内容，printf "hello," 逗号，"world," 反斜杠 n 分号。
So that's the code that we keep writing again and again.
这就是我们一直重复编写的代码。
And up until now, if I wanted to compile that, I would do make hello
到目前为止，如果我想编译它，我会执行 make hello
dot slash hello, and voila, now my program is made
点斜杠 hello，瞧，现在我的程序已经制作完成了，
and it actually executes.
它实际上可以执行了。
But what's actually going on underneath the hood
但是，实际上在幕后发生了什么
there is that make is running an actual compiler for you,
就是 make 正在为你运行一个真正的编译器，
and the reveal today is that the compiler we have been using
而今天要揭示的是，我们一直在使用的编译器
is something called Clang for C language.
是一个叫做 Clang 的编译器，用于 C 语言。
And this is just another program whose purpose in life
它只是另一个程序，它的生命目的
is actually to do the conversion of source code to machine code.
实际上是将源代码转换成机器代码。
But it turns out that Clang by itself can
但事实证明，Clang 本身就可以
be used very simply like you see here, clang hello.c,
像这里看到的一样，非常简单地使用，clang hello.c，
but it doesn't behave nearly as user-friendly as you might like.
但它的行为不像你期望的那样友好。
So in particular, let me go ahead and do this.
因此，具体来说，让我继续执行这个操作。
I'm going to go ahead and remove my compiled program
我将继续删除我的编译程序
by running rm for remove, which I alluded to briefly last time.
通过运行 rm 来删除，我上次简要提到了它。
And then I'm going to say y for yes, remove that regular file.
然后我会输入 y 代表是，删除那个普通文件。
And if I go ahead now and run just clang of hello.c and hit Enter,
如果我现在继续运行 clang hello.c 并按回车，
it seems to be successful, at least insofar as there's no error messages.
它似乎是成功的，至少没有错误消息。
But if I try to do dot slash hello, Enter,
但是如果我尝试输入点斜杠 hello，回车，
there is no such file or directory called hello.
没有名为 hello 的文件或目录。
That is because by default, Clang somewhat goofily like just
这是因为默认情况下，Clang 有点笨拙，就像
outputs a file name called a dot out.
输出一个名为点 out 的文件名。
Like why a?
为什么是 a 呢？
Well, it's sort of a simple name. a dot out, technically for assembler output,
好吧，它算是一个简单的名字。a 点 out，从技术上讲是用于汇编输出，
but this just means this is the default file
但这只是意味着这是 Clang 将要给我们的默认文件
name that Clang is going to give us.
名称。
So OK, it turns out I can do dot slash a dot out Enter, and voila,
所以，我发现我可以用点斜杠 a 点 out 回车，瞧，
that now is my program, but that's just a stupid name for a program.
现在这就是我的程序，但这只是程序的一个愚蠢的名字。
It's not very user-friendly.
它不是非常人性化。
It's certainly not an icon you would want
它肯定不是你想放在人们的桌面或手机上的图标。
to put on people's desktops or phones.
So how can we do better?
我们如何才能做得更好？
Well, it turns out, with Clang, we can configure it using
事实证明，对于 Clang，我们可以使用它来配置它
what we'll call command line arguments.
我们称之为命令行参数。
And command line arguments are actually something we've been using thus far,
命令行参数实际上是我们一直在使用的，
we just didn't slap this word on it, but command line arguments
我们只是没有用这个词来描述它，但命令行参数
are additional words or shorthand notation
是你在命令提示符处键入的附加词语或简写符号，
that you typed at your command prompt that somehow
它们以某种方式
modify the behavior of a program.
修改程序的行为。
And you can perhaps guess where this is going.
也许你已经猜到我们要做什么了。
It turns out that if I actually want to create a program called hello--
事实证明，如果我实际上想创建一个名为 hello 的程序——
not a.out, which is the default, I can actually
不是 a.out，它是默认的，我实际上可以
do this-- clang, space, dash lowercase o, space, hello,
这样做—— clang，空格，短横线小写 o，空格，hello，
or whatever I want to call the thing, space, hello.c.
或者我想要叫它什么名字，空格，hello.c。
And now if I hit Enter, nothing seems to happen,
现在如果我按回车，似乎什么也没发生，
but now if I do ./hello and Enter, now I've actually got that program.
但现在如果我输入 ./hello 并按回车，现在我实际上得到了那个程序。
So why is make useful?
那么，为什么 make 有用呢？
Well, it just saves us the trouble of having
好吧，它只是省去了我们每次都必须
to type out this longer line of command any time
键入这长长的命令行的麻烦。
we actually want to compile the code.
我们实际上想要编译代码。
But in fact, it gets even worse than that
但实际上，它比这更糟糕
with commands like clang or compilers in general
像 clang 这样的命令或者一般意义上的编译器
because consider this code here.
因为考虑一下这里代码。
Not just the version of "hello, world," but maybe the second version wherein
不仅仅是 "hello, world" 的版本，也许是第二个版本，其中
last week, I started to get user input by adding the CS50 Library using
上周，我开始通过添加 CS50 库来获取用户输入，使用
get_string and then saying, "hello," comma, "David."
get_string 然后说 "hello"，逗号，"David"。
Well, if I go back to VS Code and I modify this program
好吧，如果我回到 VS Code 并修改这个程序
to be that same one--
变成和之前一样的——
so let me go ahead and include cs50.h at the top.
所以，让我在顶部添加 cs50.h。
Let me get rid of this simple print line and instead give myself
让我去掉这简单的打印行，取而代之的是给自己
a string called name equals get_string, "What's your name?"
一个名为 name 的字符串，等于 get_string，"你的名字是什么？"
Question mark, just like we did in Scratch.
问号，就像我们在 Scratch 中做的那样。
Then I can do printf, quote-unquote, "hello," comma.
然后我可以执行 printf，引号，"hello"，逗号。
And previously I typed "world."
之前我输入的是 "world"。
I obviously don't want to type "David" because I want it to be dynamic.
我显然不想输入 "David"，因为我希望它是动态的。
What did I type last week for as a placeholder?
上周我输入了什么作为占位符？
So yeah, just-- not Command-S, but %S. So %S in this case,
所以，是的，不是 Command-S，而是 %S。在这种情况下，%S，
which is a placeholder for any such string.
它是一个占位符，用于任何这样的字符串。
Then I can still do my new line, close, quote, comma, and then
然后我仍然可以执行我的换行，关闭，引号，逗号，然后
I can substitute in something like the value of the name variable.
我可以代入类似于 name 变量的值。
All right, so if I go ahead now and compile this,
好的，所以如果我现在继续编译它，
now last week, I could just do make hello and I'm on my way,
上周，我可以直接执行 make hello，然后我就完成了，
it worked just fine.
它运行得很好。
But if I instead do clang manually, it turns out
但是如果我手动执行 clang，结果发现
that this is not going to be sufficient now. clang -o hello, space, hello.c.
现在这将不再足够了。clang -o hello，空格，hello.c。
Exact same thing I typed a moment ago, but I
和刚才我输入的完全一样，但是我
think I'm going to see some errors.
我认为我将看到一些错误。
So what's this error hinting at here?
那么，这里错误提示的是什么？
Well, at the very bottom, it's a bit arcane with its output,
好吧，在最底部，它的输出有点深奥，
and much of this you can ignore, but there are some certain key words.
而且其中大部分你可以忽略，但有一些特定的关键词。
What's the first maybe keyword you recognize in these three
在这三行错误输出中，你认识的第一个关键词可能是哪一个？
lines of erroneous output?
So it mentions main.
所以它提到了 main。
That's not that much of a clue because that's the only thing I wrote so far.
这不太是一个线索，因为到目前为止，这是我唯一写的东西。
Second line, though, get_string.
第二行，get_string。
There's some issue with an undefined reference to get_string.
关于 get_string 的未定义引用存在一些问题。
Now why might that be?
为什么会出现这种情况呢？
I did include cs50.h, but that's apparently not
我已经包含了 cs50.h，但这显然
enough to teach the compiler about get_string.
不足以教编译器关于 get_string 的知识。
Well, it turns out that if you're using a third-party library, one
事实证明，如果你使用的是第三方库，一个
that doesn't necessarily come with C the language, something like CS50's, it
并非 C 语言自带的库，例如 CS50 库，它
turns out that you additionally have to tell the compiler that you
原来你还要额外地告诉编译器你
want to use that library.
想使用那个库。
And not just by including the header file,
不仅仅是包含头文件，
but by an additional command as well.
还要通过一个额外的命令。
So when you run Clang, you want to provide an additional
所以当你运行 Clang 时，你想要提供一个额外的
rather command line argument.
命令行参数。
Literally -l for library, which is a term I used last week, cs50.
实际上是 -l 代表 library（库），这是我上周用过的术语，cs50。
A library is just code that someone else wrote
库只是其他人写的代码
that you want to use in your project.
你想在你的项目中使用它。
So if I really want to compile this version that uses the CS50 Library,
所以如果我真的想编译这个使用 CS50 库的版本，
I can still do clang o hello hello.c, but before I finish my thought,
我仍然可以执行 clang o hello hello.c，但在我想完之前，
I need to tell the compiler to link, so to speak, in the library CS50.
我需要告诉编译器连接，也可以说是链接，CS50 库。
And now I hit Enter, the error message goes away, I can do ./hello,
现在我按回车，错误消息消失了，我可以执行 ./hello，
I can type in my name, and voila, we're back to week 1.
我可以输入我的名字，瞧，我们回到了第一周。
And this is why, suffice it to say, we introduce make,
这就是我们引入 make 的原因，不难理解，
which is not a CS50 thing.
这不是CS50的东西。
This is a popular tool that real people in the real world
这是一个现实世界中真实的人们使用的流行工具
use to automate these kinds of processes.
用来自动化这类流程。
So unbeknownst to you, make has been using
所以在你不知情的情况下，make一直在使用
the -o for you. make, unbeknownst to you, has been using -l cs50 for you
-o 命令。在你不知情的情况下，make一直在为你使用-l cs50命令
just because it makes our lives easier.
仅仅是因为它使我们的生活更轻松。
But today, we thought we would deliberately
但今天，我们想故意
peel back this layer so we at least understand
剥开这一层，以便我们至少了解
what's going on behind this abstraction that is make itself
make本身这一抽象背后的情况
and compiling more generally.
以及更一般的编译过程。
So let me propose that compiling itself is not quite what
所以我想说，编译本身并不完全是
we've described it to be.
我们所描述的那样。
Compiling is like this catch-all phrase that apparently I claim
编译就像是一个万能词语，我似乎声称
goes from source code to machine code.
它将源代码转换为机器码。
But if we really want to get pedantic, which we'll do briefly,
但如果我们真的想要吹毛求疵，我们会简单地进行一下，
but this is not a sign of things to come because this, too,
但这并不意味着未来会一直这样，因为这也会
will be abstract away, compiling is just one of four steps that are involved
被抽象化，编译只是涉及到的四个步骤中的一个
in turning source code that you and I write into those 0's and 1's.
将你和我的源代码转换为0和1。
But through an understanding of these four steps
但是，通过理解这四个步骤
today, you'll hopefully better understand
今天，你应该会更好地理解
how to troubleshoot issues like that and just know
如何解决类似的问题，并且知道
what's happening because it's not, in fact, magic.
发生了什么，因为实际上这不是魔法。
It's just the result of years of humans developing these four steps here.
这只是人类多年来开发这四个步骤的结果。
So when you run make, what's happening?
所以当你运行make时，发生了什么？
Or in turn, when you run clang, four different things are happening.
或者换句话说，当你运行clang时，会发生四件事。
And the first one is called pre-processing.
第一个叫做预处理。
So what is this all about?
所以，这到底是怎么回事呢？
Well, let's consider this code here.
好吧，让我们看看这里这段代码。
And this code is a little bit interesting
这段代码有点意思
insofar as it's one of the more complicated examples from last week.
因为它算是上周比较复杂的例子之一。
And you'll notice, for instance, that I had include stdio at the top
你会注意到，例如，我在顶部包含了stdio
so I could use printf.
这样我就可以使用printf函数了。
I had main down here, whose purpose in life was just to meow three times.
我在下面写了main函数，它的唯一作用就是叫三声喵。
And then recall we made our own meow function just like we did in week 0
然后记得我们自己制作了一个喵函数，就像我们在第0周用Scratch做的那样
with Scratch that just printed out, quote-unquote, "meow."
只是输出“喵”这个词。
But I also included this line here, which we called what?
但我还在此处包含了这行代码，我们称它为？
This was a prototype.
这是一个原型。
And why did I have to include it there?
为什么我必须把它包含在里面？
Or equivalently, what would happen if I didn't include a prototype up
或者等效地，如果我不包含一个原型在
at the top there?
顶部呢？
Yeah?
对吧？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
听众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
大卫·马兰：没错。
If I didn't include it up here, the program, when trying to compile main,
如果我不把它包含在这里，程序在尝试编译main函数时
would not know what meow is because it's not defined until later.
将不知道meow是什么，因为它直到之后才会定义。
So this is kind of like a little hint of what is to come.
所以这有点像未来即将发生的事情的一个小提示。
Alternatively, we could just move this whole thing up at the top of the file,
或者，我们可以直接将整个东西移动到文件顶部，
but I claim that just devolves into a big mess
但我认为，这最终会变成一团糟
eventually once you have many different functions.
最终你会拥有许多不同的函数。
Like you can't realistically put them all at the top to solve this problem.
就像你不能现实地将它们都放在顶部来解决这个问题。
So these prototypes solve that problem.
所以这些原型解决了这个问题。
So nothing new here.
所以这里没有新东西。
Just a reminder of what motivated this one line of prototype.
只是一个提醒，说明是什么促使了这行原型代码。
Now let's consider this simpler program, which
现在让我们考虑这个更简单的程序，它
is just the one we wrote most recently in VS Code.
是我们最近在VS Code中编写的程序。
This program prompts the human for their name
这个程序提示用户输入他们的姓名
and then says hello to that person.
然后向那个人问好。
But it has two includes at the top of the file.
但是它在文件顶部包含了两个头文件。
And in fact, any line of C that starts with this hash symbol
实际上，任何以这个井号开头的C语言代码行
is what we'll call now a preprocessor directive.
我们现在称之为预处理指令。
It's not really a word you need to remember in your vocabulary,
这不是你必须记住的一个词，
but it is a little bit different from most every other line
但它与大多数其他代码行略有不同
because it starts with that hash.
因为它以井号开头。
That's a special symbol in C.
这是C语言中的一个特殊符号。
And what this means is the following.
这意味着以下几点。
This very first line, cs50.h, is indeed a file that I and CS50 staff
这第一行，cs50.h，实际上是一个文件，由我和CS50的工作人员
wrote and we installed somewhere in VS Code for you, somewhere in the cloud.
编写并安装在你的VS Code中的某个地方，云端中的某个地方。
And I've claimed you need to use this header file in order to use get_string.
我声称你需要使用这个头文件才能使用get_string函数。
So just logically, what is probably inside of cs50.h?
所以，从逻辑上讲，cs50.h里可能有什么？
Yeah?
对吧？
AUDIENCE: Function [INAUDIBLE].
听众：函数[听不清]。
DAVID MALAN: Super close.
大卫·马兰：非常接近。
So the function called get_string that does the getting of a string,
所以这个叫做get_string的函数，它负责获取字符串，
but it's not quite as much as the function itself.
但它并不完全是函数本身。
It's actually a little bit less than that, but you're on the right track.
实际上比这少一点，但你是在正确的轨道上。
What is inside of cs50.h, presumably?
cs50.h里面应该是什么？
Just a what?
只是一个什么？
Just a prototype for?
只是一个原型，用于？
Which function?
哪个函数？
get_string.
get_string函数。
So admittedly, there's some other stuff in there, too,
所以不可否认，里面也有一些其他的东西，
but the important line for today's discussion is that inside of cs50.h
但是对于今天的讨论，重要的是，在cs50.h里面
is indeed one line of code that defines what the return value, what
的确有一行代码，定义了返回值、
the name is, and what the arguments, if any, are to get_string,
函数名，以及get_string函数的参数，如果有的话，
and some other stuff.
以及一些其他的东西。
And so what happens effectively when you compile your code,
所以当你编译你的代码时，实际上发生了什么，
step 1 is this pre-processing line.
第一步就是这条预处理指令。
And essentially, there is some code that someone else wrote inside
本质上，clang编译器内部有一些其他人编写的代码，
of the clang compiler that looks for a line that starts with hash include,
它会寻找以井号include开头的代码行，
and when it sees that, it goes and finds this file and effectively copies
当它看到这个时，它就会去找到这个文件，并且实际上会复制
and pastes the contents of that file right there into your code
并将该文件的内容粘贴到你的代码中
so that you don't have to go find the file,
这样你就不用去查找文件，
copy and paste it, and make a mess of your own code.
复制粘贴它，并弄乱你自己的代码。
So in particular, it's effectively as though you're copying and pasting
所以，特别地，它实际上就像你在复制粘贴
the prototype of get_string to the very top of your file,
get_string函数的原型到你的文件顶部，
thereby teaching the compiler that it exists.
由此告诉编译器它的存在。
By that same logic, what is probably in stdio.h?
用同样的逻辑，stdio.h 中可能包含什么？
The prototype for?
对于什么？
For printf.
对于 printf。
And indeed, exactly that.
的确如此，就是它。
So this line effectively gets replaced with the equivalent
因此，这行代码实际上被替换成了等效的代码
of the prototype for printf, which, for today's purposes,
printf 函数的原型，就今天而言，
is a bit more complicated, so let me wave my hand at the dot-dot-dot
稍微复杂一点，所以我在省略号部分挥挥手
just because it takes a variable number of arguments
因为它接收可变数量的参数
depending on how many placeholders or format codes you have.
取决于你用了多少占位符或格式代码。
But effectively, that, too, is what's happening.
但实际上，就是这样。
So the preprocessor step, step 1 of 4, just
因此，预处理步骤，4 个步骤中的第 1 步，仅仅
does that find and replace, if you will.
进行查找和替换，如果你愿意。
Now there's some-- again, some other stuff in that file,
现在这个文件中有一些其他的内容，
and this, too, is kind of a white lie. printf
这也算是一个善意的谎言。printf
probably has its own file because that's a really big library,
可能拥有自己的文件，因为这是一个非常大的库，
but the essence of it is exactly this.
但它的本质正是如此。
So preprocessing converts all of those hash
所以预处理将所有这些哈希
include lines to whatever the underlying prototypes are
include 行转换为底层的原型
within the file plus some other stuff.
在文件中，以及一些其他内容。
Now compiling we use it as this catch-all phrase, but it turns out,
现在我们用编译这个万能短语，但事实证明，
it has a very specific meaning that's worth
它有非常具体的含义，值得
knowing about even though after today, you
了解，即使在今天之后，你
can go back to using compiling as the sort of catch-all phrase.
可以继续使用编译作为万能短语。
So when you've got this same code here after the pre-processing step
所以当你拥有这段代码，在预处理步骤之后
has happened.
已经完成。
So this is essentially happening in the computer's memory.
所以这本质上是在计算机内存中发生的。
It's not changing your hello.c file permanently or anything like that.
它不会永久地改变你的 hello.c 文件，或进行任何类似的操作。
This code gets, quote-unquote, "compiled" into something
这段代码被“编译”成了
that looks more like this.
更像这样的东西。
And this is a scarier language that we won't spend time
这是一门更可怕的语言，我们不会在这门课上花时间
on in this particular class.
学习它。
This is what's known as assembly language.
这就是所谓的汇编语言。
And back in the day, before there was C, humans
在 C 语言出现之前，人们
wrote this to program their computers.
用它来为他们的计算机编写程序。
Similarly, before there was assembly code back in the day,
同样，在汇编代码出现之前，
humans very initially used what instead?
人们最初使用什么？
AUDIENCE: 0's and 1's.
观众：0 和 1。
DAVID MALAN: So 0's and 1's-- like they actually wrote the machine code
大卫·马兰：所以 0 和 1 - 就像他们实际上编写了机器代码
painfully, be it in code or be it in punch cards like physical objects
非常痛苦，无论是代码还是像物理对象一样的穿孔卡片
or the like.
等等。
So again, these are sort of abstractions,
所以，这些都是抽象的东西，
but we're rewinding for today in time.
但我们今天要回到过去。
But what this compiler for C is doing is converting C
但 C 语言的编译器所做的就是将 C 语言
into this other language called assembly language.
转换为另一种语言，叫做汇编语言。
And even though this looks very esoteric,
虽然它看起来非常深奥，
there's at least some juicy things in here.
但这里至少有一些有趣的东西。
If I highlight get_string, it's mentioned in this code.
如果我高亮显示 get_string，它在这段代码中被提及。
printf is mentioned in this code.
printf 在这段代码中被提及。
And even some of these keywords here that
甚至这里的一些关键字
are spelled a bit weirdly, this relates to subtracting and moving
拼写有点奇怪，这与减法和移动相关
something in memory and calling a function, calling a function.
内存中的某些内容，以及调用函数、调用函数。
So there's some semantics that are probably
所以有一些语义可能
somewhat familiar even though this is not code we ourselves will write.
有些熟悉，即使这不是我们自己会写的代码。
But unfortunately, this is not yet machine code,
但不幸的是，这还不是机器代码，
and that's where step 3 comes in.
这就是第 3 步的用武之地。
So step 3 of this four-step process is technically called assembling.
因此，这个四步过程中的第 3 步在技术上被称为汇编。
And assembling just takes that assembly code and converts it, thankfully,
汇编只是将汇编代码转换成，谢天谢地，
to the thing we do care about, the 0's and 1's.
我们真正关心的东西，0 和 1。
So assembling takes assembly code converts it to 0's and 1's.
所以汇编将汇编代码转换为 0 和 1。
As an aside, and I alluded to this earlier,
顺便说一下，我之前提过，
the reason that Clang names its files a.out by default, assembler output,
Clang 将其文件默认命名为 a.out 的原因是，汇编器输出，
is a side effect of that being one of the steps in this process,
是这个过程中的一个步骤的副作用，
dealing with assembly language and its subsequent output.
处理汇编语言及其后续输出。
All right, so here are some 0's and 1's, but unfortunately, there's
好的，所以这里有一些 0 和 1，但不幸的是，还有
still that fourth and final step, which is a word that I also used earlier,
第四步也是最后一步，我之前也用过这个词，
namely linking.
就是链接。
So let me take a step back and look at this code here.
所以让我退一步，看看这里的代码。
And even though this code is exactly as I wrote in VS Code in hello.c--
即使这段代码与我在 VS Code 中 hello.c 中编写的完全一样 -
so no copying and pasting, no prototypes have
所以没有复制粘贴，没有原型
been plugged in here, this is my code, technically, there's
被插入到这里，这是我的代码，从技术上来说，有
three different files involved in compiling even something relatively
三个不同的文件参与编译，即使是像这样相对简单的东西
simple like this.
简单的东西。
There's obviously this thing itself, hello.c, which I wrote.
很明显，这个东西本身，hello.c，是我写的。
There's apparently cs50.h, and there's apparently stdio.h.
很明显，cs50.h 和 stdio.h 也存在。
But technically-- and you don't have to know this file name, per se, somewhere
但从技术上来说——你不需要知道这个文件名，在某处
else on the computer's hard drive, so to speak,
在计算机的硬盘驱动器上，可以这么说，
is a cs50.c file, which actually contains
有一个 cs50.c 文件，它实际上包含
the staff's implementation of get_string and get_int and get_float
工作人员对 get_string、get_int 和 get_float 的实现
and all of those other functions.
以及所有其他函数。
Somewhere on the server's hard drive is stdio.c
服务器的硬盘驱动器上还有 stdio.c
that implements printf and all of these other functions as well.
它实现了 printf 和所有其他函数。
So the dot c is just inferred from the dot h here.
所以 .c 文件名是从这里的 .h 文件名推断出来的。
You don't ever mention the dot c file, but someone else wrote those files,
你永远不会提到 .c 文件，但其他人写了这些文件，
someone else stored them in the server for you--
其他人将它们存储在服务器上，供你使用 -
CS50 staff in this case.
在这种情况下，是 CS50 工作人员。
So technically, even when compiling a relatively short program like this,
所以从技术上来说，即使编译像这样的短程序，
you're really combining three files at least at the end of the day.
实际上你至少组合了三个文件。
And I'll write them from left to right. hello.c,
我会从左到右写它们。hello.c，
which I wrote, cs50.c, which the staff wrote, and then stdio.c as well.
是我写的，cs50.c 是工作人员写的，还有 stdio.c。
So somewhere there's these three files.
所以这些三个文件存在于某个地方。
And Clang, our compiler, needs to compile each of these
而 Clang，我们的编译器，需要将这些文件中的每一个
into the corresponding 0's and 1's.
编译成相应的 0 和 1。
Lastly, this is not yet sufficient because these 0's and 1's haven't
最后，这还不够，因为这些0和1还没有
been linked together.
被链接在一起。
I mean, I deliberately left a gap here to imply that these
我的意思是，我故意在这里留了一个空隙，暗示这些
are three separately-compiled files.
是三个独立编译的文件。
So that fourth and final step called linking
所以第四步也是最后一步，叫做链接，
takes all of these 0's and 1's and an intelligent way
它会以一种智能的方式将所有这些0和1
combines them into just one final file named hello, named a.out,
组合成一个名为hello的最终文件，或者名为a.out，
whatever the file name is of choice.
无论你选择什么文件名。
So what you and I for the past week have just been calling compiling--
所以，过去一周你我一直在称之为编译——
and that's what a normal person will use henceforth
而这也是普通人从今以后会用来
to describe this whole process, technically, there's
描述整个过程的术语，从技术上讲，
these four different steps underneath the hood, each of which
这四个不同的步骤隐藏在幕后，每一个步骤
is sort of a representative of an evolution of technology over the years.
在某种程度上代表着多年来技术的演变。
And nowadays, if we fast forward a few weeks
而如今，如果我们快进几周
in class, when we start talking about Python, which
在课堂上，当我们开始谈论Python，它
is another more modern language, that, too, is going to be conceptually even
是另一种更现代的语言，它在概念上也将更加
higher level, even though underneath the hood,
高级，即使在幕后，
there's going to be some lower-level principles at work.
将会有一些底层原理在起作用。
So any questions on just terminology or these processes known as compiling?
那么，关于术语或这些被称为编译的过程，有什么问题吗？
Yeah?
有吗？
AUDIENCE: I didn't really understand what compiling means.
观众：我不太理解编译是什么意思。
[INAUDIBLE]
[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
大卫·马兰：当然。
Compiling, if I rewind, is the process of taking your source code, which
编译，如果我倒带一下，就是将你的源代码（它
looks like this, recall-- whoops, this, and converting it into assembly code.
看起来像这样，你还记得吗？——哎呦，这个，然后将其转换为汇编代码。）
So preprocessing just converts all of those hash
所以预处理只是将所有这些hash
include lines and a few others to their equivalents.
include行和其他一些行转换为它们的等价物。
So that's step 1.
所以这是第一步。
Compiling converts the C code into the underlying assembly code.
编译将C代码转换为底层的汇编代码。
The assembling step, step 3, converts the assembly code to 0's and 1's.
汇编步骤，第三步，将汇编代码转换为0和1。
And then the fourth step, linking, combines
然后第四步，链接，将
all of the 0's and 1's from the one, the two, the three or more files
来自一个、两个、三个或更多文件的所有0和1
that are involved in your project and links them
参与到你的项目中，并将它们
all together for you magically.
全部神奇地连接起来。
But at the end of the day, all of this is happening automatically for you.
但归根结底，所有这些都是自动为你完成的。
If I jump now to the end here, whereby just by running
如果我现在跳到最后，只需要运行
make, which, in turn, runs clang for you, like all of this
make，它反过来会为你运行clang，就像所有这一切
is abstracted away.
都被抽象掉了。
But the key here is that even with these commands that we've been running,
但关键是，即使我们一直在运行这些命令，
be it the make command or the clang command,
无论是make命令还是clang命令，
everything should be explainable what you are typing at the prompt
你输入到提示符上的内容都应该是可以解释的
ultimately.
最终。
Each of those things has a purpose.
每一件事都有它的目的。
So any questions, then, on what we've just
那么，关于我们刚刚
now called compiling even though it's only when you take another CS
现在称为编译的东西，即使只有当你学习另一门计算机科学课程的时候，
course that you might spend more time on assembly
你才会花更多时间在汇编
language or these lower-level details?
语言或这些底层细节上？
Yeah?
有吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: A good question.
大卫·马兰：问得好。
Are there other types of compilers?
还有其他类型的编译器吗？
Yes.
是的。
Back when I took CS50, I used a popular compiler called GCC, the GNU Compiler
当我学习CS50的时候，我用过一个流行的编译器叫做GCC，即GNU编译器
Collection, which still exists actually in the code space
集合，它实际上仍然存在于你用来学习CS50的代码空间中。
that you're using for CS50.
你用来学习CS50的代码空间中。
Clang is somewhat more recent.
Clang稍微晚一些。
It's gaining popularity.
它正在越来越受欢迎。
And frankly, we use it in large part because it's error messages
坦白地说，我们使用它的很大一部分原因是它的错误消息
are slightly more user-friendly.
稍微更人性化一些。
You might not believe us because if you encountered some errors with your code
你可能不信，因为如果你在过去一周遇到了代码错误，
this past week, they were probably just as arcane as the error messages I saw,
它们可能和我在过去看到过的错误消息一样难懂，
but it's better than it was some years ago.
但比几年前好多了。
And there's alternatives to compiling, too,
还有编译的替代方案，
but more on that when we get to Python as well.
但我们会在学习Python的时候详细介绍。
Other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
No?
没有吗？
All right.
好的。
Well, what are the implications of the fact that we're going from source code
那么，我们从源代码转换到机器码，这有什么影响呢？
to machine code?
转换到机器码？
Well, it stands to reason that if you can compile code,
那么，如果你可以编译代码，
maybe you can decompile it-- that is, go in the reverse direction.
也许你可以反编译它——也就是说，反向操作。
Go from 0's and 1's to actual source code.
从0和1转换为实际的源代码。
Now that would be handy if you want to go in as a programmer and change
如果你想作为一名程序员进入程序内部并修改
something in a program that you or someone else already wrote.
你或其他人已经写好的程序中的某些东西，这会很方便。
It's maybe not ideal for your intellectual property,
但如果你最初是编写该程序的人，这对你自己的知识产权来说可能不太理想。
though, if you are the person who wrote that program in the first place.
If you are Microsoft and you wrote Microsoft Word or Excel
如果你就是微软，是你编写了Microsoft Word或Excel，
that people with Macs and PCs and phones have installed on their devices,
这些程序被安装在使用Mac、PC和手机的人们的设备上，
it doesn't actually sound very appealing if any old customer
如果任何一个老顾客
can take those 0's and 1's and reverse them, reverse engineer them,
可以获取这些0和1并反转它们，对其进行逆向工程，
so to speak, into the original source code
也可以说，反编译成最初的源代码，
because then they can have their own version of Microsoft Word
因为那样他们就可以拥有自己版本的Microsoft Word，
and make changes to it without really having put in all of the R&D
并且可以对其进行修改，而无需投入所有用于构建最初版本的研发
that it might have taken to build the first version thereof.
投入所有用于构建最初版本的研发工作。
But it turns out that reverse engineering--
但事实证明逆向工程——
so doing things in the opposite direction-- is easier
也就是反向操作——说起来容易做起来难，因为正如你所见，
said than done because there are multiple ways, as you've seen already,
说起来容易做起来难，因为正如你所见，
to implement programs.
有很多方法可以实现程序。
Like loops alone, you can use for loops, while loops, even do-while loops.
比如循环，你可以使用for循环、while循环，甚至do-while循环。
And so there's other ways-- there's multiple ways
所以还有其他方法——有很多方法
to solve the same problem.
来解决同一个问题。
So even if you try to reverse engineer a program
所以即使你试图反编译一个程序
and convert machine code back to source code,
并将机器码转换回源代码，
there's not necessarily going to be an obvious way to do so.
也不一定会有明显的方法可以做到。
And the reality is, that it ends up being such a mess
而现实是，它最终会变得非常混乱，
because you lose the variable names typically,
因为你通常会丢失变量名，
you lose the function names typically, that what you end up looking at
你通常会丢失函数名，最终你会看到的东西
might very well be C code, but it's completely difficult for you,
很可能就是 C 代码，但对你来说，
even a good programmer, to read.
即使是优秀的程序员，也很难阅读。
And generally, the mindset is, if you're really good enough
通常情况下，心态是，如果你足够优秀
to decompile code in that way and read it subsequently
以这种方式反编译代码并随后阅读它
even without good variable names, good function
即使没有好的变量名，好的函数
names, good documentation and the like, could probably have just implemented
名，好的文档等等，可能你一开始就能够自己实现
the program in the first place yourself without jumping through those hoops.
程序，而无需经历这些麻烦。
So there's some practicality pushing back
所以有一些实用性在回击
on what are otherwise potential threats to, say, your intellectual property.
对其他潜在的威胁，比如你的知识产权。
But that's not going to be the case later on in the term when
但本学期后期情况并非如此，当
we do get to languages like Python to some extent, other languages
我们确实接触到像 Python 这样的语言，在某种程度上，其他语言
like JavaScript.
像 JavaScript 那样。
Some of those are actually going to be readable by anyone.
其中一些实际上可以被任何人阅读。
Any of your customers, any of your friends,
你的任何客户，你的任何朋友，
and your family that actually use your programs.
以及使用你的程序的家人。
So with that said, let's introduce now another tool to our toolkit
因此，现在让我们向工具包中引入另一个工具
that will hopefully make some of the pain
希望这能够减轻一些痛苦
from this past week when you did encounter
来自上周，当你遇到
bugs a little more manageable.
bug 时，会更容易管理一些。
And indeed, part of the process of writing code to this day
事实上，编写代码的过程的一部分直到今天
is debugging it.
就是调试它。
And it is a rare thing to write a program,
编写一个程序是件很罕见的事情，
be it in C or any other language, and get it 100% right the first time.
无论是用 C 语言还是其他任何语言，第一次就能做到 100% 正确。
I mean, to this day, I still, 20-plus years later, still write buggy code.
我的意思是，直到今天，我仍然，二十多年后，仍然会写出有 bug 的代码。
Hopefully a little bit less of it, but any time you're adding a new feature,
希望 bug 少一些，但是无论什么时候你添加一个新功能，
any time you're doing something for the first time,
无论什么时候你第一次做某件事，
you're not necessarily going to see all of the possible mistakes.
你并不一定会看到所有可能的错误。
So even in industry, bugs are omnipresent, which is really to say,
因此，即使在工业界，bug 无处不在，也就是说，
having techniques to debug code-- that is, eliminate bugs,
拥有调试代码的技术，也就是说，消除 bug，
is super compelling.
非常有说服力。
Now just for a bit of history, here is Admiral Grace Hopper,
现在，让我们了解一点历史，这位是 Grace Hopper 海军上将，
who was actually in not only the military,
她不仅在军队服役，
but also on the faculty of Harvard years ago
而且很多年前也在哈佛大学任教
and worked on a Harvard computer called the Harvard Mark
并参与开发了名为哈佛 Mark 的哈佛大学计算机
I, which is actually on display at the School of Engineering and Applied
I，它现在实际上在工程与应用学院展出
Sciences if you take a tour over there sometime.
科学学院，如果你有时间去参观一下。
But also when working on the Harvard Mark II,
但她在开发哈佛 Mark II 的过程中，
she is known for having at least popularized the phrase "bug" to mean
她以至少推广了“bug”一词来表示而闻名
a mistake in a computer's program--
计算机程序中的错误——
a mistake in a computer's code.
计算机代码中的错误。
And the etymology of this supposedly is this here logbook
而这个词的词源据说是这份航海日志
wherein she and her colleagues were documenting processes being computed
她和她同事记录了正在计算机上计算的过程
on computers, that a moth actually got stuck
在计算机上，一只飞蛾卡住了
in one of the relays, one of the mechanical-- the electric relays inside
在一个继电器中，一个机械——电继电器在
of the very old now computer, and someone very cleverly
现在非常古老的计算机中，然后某人非常聪明地
wrote, "First actual case of bug being found."
写下了：“第一个发现 bug 的真实案例”。
So it wasn't she who actually discovered it,
所以发现它的人不是她，
but this was a story she was thereafter fond of telling as a famed computer
但她后来很喜欢讲述这个故事，作为著名的计算机
scientist thereafter.
科学家。
We now know bugs to be all too familiar when it comes to writing our own code,
我们现在知道，当编写自己的代码时，bug 实在是太熟悉了，
and I thought I would deliberately write some buggy code based
我想我会故意写一些有 bug 的代码，这些代码基于
on some of the programs with which we experimented last week.
我们上周实验的一些程序。
So let me go back over to VS Code here and let
所以，让我回到 VS Code，并让
me propose that I do something somewhat simplistic just like this to print out
我提议我做一些简单的事情，就像这样，打印出
a column of bricks of height 3.
一列高度为 3 的砖块。
So I'm going into VS Code and I'm going to deliberately call this program
所以我要进入 VS Code，并且故意将这个程序命名为
buggy.c because I intend to do this poorly.
buggy.c，因为我打算把它写得不好。
I'm going to include stdio.h as before, int main void as before.
我将像以前一样包含 stdio.h，像以前一样包含 int main void。
And in here, if I want to print a pyramid of height 3,
这里，如果我想打印一个高度为 3 的金字塔，
I'm going to do 4 int i gets--
我要做 4 个 int i 获取——
all right, I'm still new to programming in my mind
好吧，我仍然是一个新手，在我的脑海中
here, so I know I'm supposed to start counting at 0, OK.
这里，我知道我应该从 0 开始计数，好的。
And I want to do this until I count up to 3, so I'm going to do that.
我想一直这样做，直到我计数到 3，所以我将这样做。
And then i++ I remember from class in this way.
然后是 i++，我从课堂上记得是这样的。
And now I might go ahead and print out just a hash mark, backslash n,
现在我可以继续打印一个井号，一个反斜杠 n，
which I do want because I want to move this cursor to the next line
因为我想要这样做，因为我想要将光标移动到下一行
to make this vertical.
让它变成垂直的。
But of course, if you've noticed with your eye already, when I do make buggy,
但是当然，如果你已经用眼睛注意到，当我执行 buggy 时，
it compiles OK.
它编译正常。
So no typos, no syntactical errors.
所以没有错别字，没有语法错误。
But when I run this, I'm going to see how many bricks.
但是当我运行它时，我会看到有多少块砖。
So four in this case.
在这种情况下是四块。
Now this is meant to be a simplistic example
现在，这是一个简化的例子
so that we don't spend time trying to figure out what the bug is, but rather,
这样我们就不必花费时间来弄清楚 bug 是什么，而是，
focus on techniques for actually identifying the bug.
专注于识别 bug 的技术。
So-- finding, rather, the bug.
所以—— 找到，而是 bug。
So what's one of the first tools in your toolkit?
那么，工具包中的第一个工具是什么？
Literally one you have already. printf is your friend.
实际上你已经有了。printf 是你的朋友。
And it is a very quick and dirty tool for just seeing
它是一个非常快速而粗糙的工具，用来查看
what's going on inside of the computer when
当你在计算机内部发生了什么，
you don't have more sophisticated tools or even the time to use them.
你没有更复杂的工具，甚至没有时间使用它们。
And so in this case, for instance, what I'd propose is that--
因此，在这种情况下，例如，我建议——
all right, I'm obviously seeing four hashes.
好吧，我显然看到四个井号。
And let me play a little slow here.
让我在这里慢一点。
It'd be helpful for me to understand why logically I'm ending up with four, even
对我来说，了解为什么在逻辑上我最终得到四个会很有帮助，即使
though I'm starting at 0 like I remember from class and I'm going up to 3
虽然我从 0 开始，就像我从课堂上记得的那样，我正在向上计数到 3
as we did in class, like I'm just not seeing it in this particular story.
就像我们在课堂上做的那样，我在这里并没有看到这个故事。
So what I would commonly do is go into my code and just help me see
因此，我通常会进入我的代码，并帮助我看到
what's going on, and I might literally write a printf line like, i is %i,
发生了什么，我可能会直接写一行 printf 代码，比如， i 是 %i，
backslash n, comma, and then just print out the value of i.
反斜杠 n，逗号，然后直接打印 i 的值。
I just want to see on every iteration, what
我只想看看每次迭代，
is i, what is i, what is i just to help me see what the computer already knows.
i 是什么，i 是什么，i 是什么，只是为了让我看看计算机已经知道什么。
So let me go ahead and recompile buggy, let me rerun buggy,
所以让我继续重新编译 buggy，让我重新运行 buggy，
and then let me make my terminal window bigger
然后让我把我的终端窗口放大
just to make clear what's going on.
只是为了让大家清楚发生了什么。
And now it's a little more pedantic.
现在有点过分了。
Now i is 0, I get a hash. i is 1, I get a hash. i is 2, I get a hash.
现在 i 是 0，我得到一个井号。i 是 1，我得到一个井号。i 是 2，我得到一个井号。
Wait a minute. i is 3, I get a hash.
等一下。i 是 3，我得到一个井号。
So clearly now, it should be maybe more obvious to you,
所以现在很明显，也许对你来说更明显，
especially if the syntax itself is unfamiliar,
尤其是如果语法本身不熟悉，
I certainly don't want this last one printing,
我当然不想打印最后一个，
or maybe equivalently, I don't want the first one printing.
或者等价地说，我不想打印第一个。
So I can fix this in a couple of ways, but the solution,
我可以通过几种方法来解决这个问题，但是解决方案，
the most canonical solution is probably to do what with my code?
最规范的解决方案可能是用我的代码做什么？
To change to what to what?
改变什么？
Yeah?
是吧？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
大卫·马兰：是。
So change the less than or equal sign to just a less than sign.
所以把小于等于号改成小于号。
So even though this is like counting from 0 to 3 instead of 1 through 3,
所以尽管这看起来像是从 0 到 3 而不是从 1 到 3 计数，
it's the more typical programmatic way to write code like this.
但这是更典型的程序化编写这种代码的方式。
And now, of course, if I do make buggy--
现在，当然，如果我做了 buggy--
and I'll increase my terminal window again, ./buggy,
而且我会再次放大我的终端窗口，./buggy，
now I see what's going on inside of the code.
现在我看到了代码内部发生了什么。
Now it matches my expectations, and so now the bug is gone.
现在它符合我的预期，所以现在 bug 消失了。
Now of course, if I'm submitting this or shipping it,
现在当然，如果我提交它或发布它，
I should delete the temporary printf.
我应该删除临时 printf。
And let me disclaim that using printf in this way just to help you
我必须声明，用这种方式使用 printf 只是为了帮助你
see what's going on is generally a good thing,
看到发生了什么事通常是件好事，
but generally adding a printf and a printf and a printf and a printf--
但是通常添加一个 printf 和一个 printf 和一个 printf 和一个 printf--
like it starts to devolve into just trial and error and you
就像它开始演变成反复试错，然后你
have no idea what's going on, so you're just printing out everything.
不知道发生了什么事，所以你就把所有东西都打印出来。
Let me propose that if you ever find yourself slipping down
我想说的是，如果你发现自己滑下了
that hill into just trying this, trying this, trying this,
那座山，只是尝试这个，尝试那个，尝试这个，
you need a better tool, not just doing printf.
你需要更好的工具，而不仅仅是使用 printf。
And frankly, it's annoying to use printf because every time you add a printf,
坦白说，使用 printf 很烦人，因为每次添加一个 printf，
you have to recompile the code, rerun the code.
你必须重新编译代码，重新运行代码。
It's just adding to the number of steps.
这只是增加了步骤的数量。
So let me propose instead that we do this.
所以，我建议我们这样做。
I'm going to go back into VS Code here and I'm
我要回到这里的 VS Code 中，我
going to write a different program that actually
要写一个不同的程序，它实际上
has a helper function, so to speak.
拥有一个辅助函数，可以这么说。
A second function whose purpose in life is maybe just
第二个函数，它的生命意义也许只是
to print that column for me.
为我打印那一列。
So I'm going to say this-- void print_column,
所以我要这样写：void print_column，
though I could call it anything I want, and this function
虽然我可以随意命名它，而这个函数
is going to take a argument or a parameter called
将接收一个参数，叫做
height which will tell it how many bricks to print,
height，它将告诉函数打印多少个砖块，
how many vertical bricks.
多少个竖砖。
I'm going to do the same kind of logic. for int i equals 0.
我要用同样的逻辑。for int i 等于 0。
i is less than--
i 小于--
I'm going to make the same mistake again-- less than or equal to height,
我将再次犯同样的错误：小于等于 height，
i++.
i++。
And then inside of this for loop, let me go ahead and print out the hash mark.
然后在这个 for 循环中，让我继续打印井号。
So I've made the same mistake, but I've made it
所以，我犯了同样的错误，但我在
in the context now of a helper function only because in main,
现在辅助函数的上下文中犯了这个错误，因为在 main 中，
what I'd like to do now, just to be a little more sophisticated is get int
我现在想做的事情，为了更精致一点，就是获取 int
from the user for the height.
从用户那里获取高度。
And when I do get that int, I want to store it in a variable called n,
当我获取到那个 int 时，我想把它存储到一个叫做 n 的变量中，
but I do need to give that variable a type like last week.
但是我需要给那个变量一个类型，就像上周一样。
So I'll say that it's an integer.
所以我把它定义为整数。
And now, lastly, I can print_column, passing in-- actually, I'll
现在，最后，我可以调用 print_column，传入参数--实际上，我将
call it h just because height is h.
把它叫做 h，因为 height 就是 h。
Print column h, semicolon.
打印列 h，分号。
OK, so it's the exact same program except I'm getting user input now.
好的，所以它和之前的程序完全一样，除了我现在获取用户输入。
So it's not just going to be 3, it's going to be a variable height,
所以它不再是固定的 3，而是一个可变的高度，
but I've done something stupid.
但我做了一些愚蠢的事情。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: I've done two stupid things.
大卫·马兰：我犯了两个愚蠢的错误。
So this, of course, is not supposed to be there, so I'll fix that.
所以，当然，这里不应该出现这个，所以我会把它改掉。
And someone else.
还有其他人。
What else have I done?
我还做了什么？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
大卫·马兰：是。
I'm missing the prototype.
我漏掉了原型。
And this is, let me reiterate, probably the only time where copy-paste is OK.
而且我要重申一遍，这可能是唯一可以复制粘贴的时候。
Once you've implemented the function, you
一旦你实现了函数，你
can copy paste its first line at a semicolon
可以复制粘贴它的第一行，加上分号
so that it teaches the compiler that this function will exist.
这样它就可以告诉编译器这个函数将会存在。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Three stupid things.
大卫·马兰：三件蠢事。
OK.
好的。
Thank you.
谢谢。
So, good.
所以，很好。
Include cs50.h.
包含 cs50.h。
And now, anyone want to go for four?
现在，有人想要去尝试第四个吗？
No?
没有？
All right.
好的。
Slightly unintended here.
这里有点意外。
So let's see. make buggy.
我们来看看。make buggy。
OK, no syntax errors thanks to you all.
好的，没有语法错误，感谢大家。
So the code compiles, but of course, when I run buggy
所以代码可以编译，但当然，当我运行 buggy 时
and I type in something like 3 manually, I'm still going to get 1, 2, 3 4 out.
我手动输入 3，我仍然会得到 1，2，3，4。
So let me now introduce a more powerful tool
所以，现在我将介绍一个更强大的工具
that's generally known as a debugger.
通常称为调试器。
And within the VS Code environment that you're using,
在您正在使用的 VS Code 环境中，
we actually have a command that makes it a little easier to use this tool,
我们实际上有一个命令，可以让你更轻松地使用这个工具，
but we didn't write the tool itself.
但是我们并没有编写这个工具本身。
You are about to see a very graphical, a very popular industry standard
您将看到一个非常图形化的、非常流行的行业标准
tool called a debugger, but we'll start the debugger using a CS50-specific
称为调试器的工具，但我们将使用一个CS50特定的工具
command called debug50, which just makes it easier with a single command
名为debug50的命令，它只需要一个命令就能简化操作
to start the debugger without having to configure a text
启动调试器，而无需配置文本
file with all of your preferred settings and all of that.
文件，里面包含您所有偏好的设置等等。
It's just an annoying hoop otherwise to jump through.
否则就是一个需要跳过的令人讨厌的障碍。
So what I'm going to do is go back to my code here.
所以我要回到我的代码这里。
I have already compiled it, but just for good measure,
我已经编译了它，但为了保险起见，
I'll make buggy again because the debugger needs your code
我会让它再次出现错误，因为调试器需要您的代码
to be compiled.
被编译。
It's not going to help with syntax errors
它不会帮助解决语法错误
like the stupid mistakes I just made unintentionally,
就像我无意中犯的一些愚蠢错误，
it will help you though with programmatic errors, logical errors
但它可以帮助您解决程序错误，逻辑错误
in your code once your code is running.
在您的代码运行时。
So to run debug50, I'm going to do this. debug50, space, and then
所以要运行debug50，我会这样做。debug50，空格，然后
the exact same command I would normally run to just run the program itself.
与我通常运行程序时使用的命令完全相同。
So ./buggy.
所以是./buggy。
So exact same thing, ./buggy, but I prefix it now with debug50.
所以完全一样，./buggy，但我现在在它前面加上了debug50。
When I hit Enter, a whole bunch of--
当我按下回车键时，一堆--
another error is going to pop up on the screen, which
另一个错误将出现在屏幕上，这
is a good reminder because this will happen to you, too, invariably.
是一个很好的提醒，因为这也会发生在你身上，不可避免地。
It's reminding me that I have to set what's called a breakpoint.
它提醒我，我必须设置一个称为断点的设置。
And as that word suggests, it is the point
正如这个词所暗示的那样，它就是那个点
at which you want your code to break.
您希望代码中断的地方。
Not break in make the situation worse sense, but rather,
不是让情况变得更糟，而是
where do you want to pause?
您希望暂停在哪里？
Execution, break, execution-- like hitting the brakes on a car
执行、中断、执行-- 就像踩汽车的刹车一样
so the program doesn't run all at once.
这样程序就不会一次运行完。
And you can put this any number of places,
你可以把它放在任何地方，
and you might have done this accidentally
你可能无意中做过这件事
if you've ever hovered over the gutter of VS Code,
如果你曾经将鼠标悬停在VS Code的代码行边距上，
the left-hand side next to your line numbers.
行号旁边的左侧。
See the little red dot that appears?
看到那里出现的红色小点了吗？
If I click on any of these lines, that's going to set a breakpoint, so to speak.
如果我点击这些行中的任何一行，就会设置一个断点，可以这么说。
And I want to break execution at main.
我想在main处中断执行。
So I'm just going to click to the left of line 6 in this case.
所以我要点击第6行的左侧，在这种情况下。
That makes it a darker red circle, a stop sign
这样就变成一个更深的红色圆圈，一个停止标志
of sorts that tells the debugger to pause execution on that line,
它告诉调试器在那一行暂停执行，
though I could put it elsewhere if I so choose.
虽然我可以根据需要把它放在其他地方。
Let me go ahead and rerun debug50 ./buggy, Enter,
让我继续运行debug50 ./buggy，回车，
and now a bunch of things are going to happen on the screen.
现在屏幕上会发生很多事情。
It's going to look a little overwhelming perhaps at first glance,
乍一看，它可能看起来有点让人不知所措，
but there's some useful stuff that just happened.
但是有一些有用的东西刚刚发生了。
So one, my code is still here, but the line that I set the breakpoint on is--
所以，首先，我的代码仍然在这里，但是我设置断点的行是--
rather, the first line of actual executable
更确切地说，是我设置的断点之下第一行实际可执行的
code at or below the breakpoint I set is highlighted in this yellowish green
代码以这种淡黄绿色突出显示，这意味着这一行代码还没有执行。
here, which says, this line of code has not yet been executed.
我们在这点上中断了，但如果我点击一个按钮，这一行代码
We broke at this point, but if I click a button, this line of code
将会被执行。
will be executed.
因为到目前为止，你写的每一个C程序都运行得飞快。
Because up until now, every C program you write runs as fast as that.
我想踩刹车，在这里暂停一下。
I want to pump the brakes and pause here.
但是请注意这里窗口的几个其他方面。
But notice a few other aspects of the window here.
所以请注意这里上面的一些奇怪的东西。
So notice that up here some weirdness.
那里提到了变量，我们对这些很熟悉。
There's mentions of variables and we're familiar with these.
局部是一个我们本周会用到的术语。
Local is a term we'll use this week.
但是有这个变量h，奇怪的是，
But there's this variable h, which weirdly,
这个值21912是从哪里来的呢？
where did the value 21912 come from?
所以事实证明，在C语言中，在你用一个值初始化一个变量之前
So it turns out, in C, before you initialize a variable with a value
通过字面意义上的输入数字3，或者使用像get_int这样的函数，
by literally typing the number 3, or by using a function like get_int,
它通常包含一个叫做垃圾值的变量。
it often contains what's called a garbage value.
关于这些，我们将在几周后详细讲解。
More on those in a couple of weeks.
但你可以把垃圾值看作
But a garbage value is you can think of it
是计算机内存中运行程序之前残留的东西。
as like remnants of whatever was in the computer's memory
这是一个过度简化的说法，
before you ran your program.
但你不能指望一个变量在这种情况
And that's a bit of a oversimplification,
下会拥有一个特定的值，
but you cannot trust that a variable will have a certain value in this case
除非你自己设置了它。
if you did not put one there yourself.
所以现在，h 是没有意义的。
So for now, h is nonsensical.
它是一个垃圾值，没有任何意义。
It's a garbage value it means nothing.
但一旦我执行这一行，它应该包含用户输入的任何内容。
But once I execute this line, it should contain whatever the human types in.
好的。
All right.
在下面，有一个观察区域，这是一个更复杂的功能。
Down here, there's a watch section, which is a more sophisticated feature.
在下面是所谓的调用堆栈。
Down here is what's called the call stack.
我们将在未来详细讲解。
More on that in the future.
但现在这意味着我正在执行main函数，而不是
But what this means for now is that I'm executing the main function, not,
例如，print_column。
for instance, print_column.
所以请注意这里，这些是界面中最有用的控件。
So notice up here, these are the most useful controls within the interface.
如果我点击这个播放按钮，它就会
If I hit this Play button, it's just going
运行我的程序，直到结束，不再打扰我。
to actually run my program to the end of it without bothering me further.
然而，我可以实际执行这一行代码，
However, I can actually step over this line of code and execute it,
或者我可以进入这一行代码，并实际
or I can step into this line of code and actually
查看get_int的内容，如果它在系统上可用的话。
poke around the contents of get_int if it's available on the system.
所以从概念上来说，你可以执行这一行
So conceptually you can either execute this line
或者你可以在概念上深入下去，看看这个函数内部有什么。
or you can dive down conceptually deeper and see what's inside of that function.
最后，这将让你跳出，这将
Lastly, this will let you step out, this will
让你重新启动整个过程，这将停止调试器。
allow you to restart the whole process, and this will just stop the debugger.
所以这些按钮将是我们的好朋友。
So these buttons are going to be our friends.
我要点击的第一个按钮是我描述的第一个按钮，
And the one I'll click first is the first one I described,
也就是“单步跳过”。
which is step over.
所以“单步跳过”并不意味着跳过这一步，它只是意味着执行这一步，
So step over doesn't mean, skip this step, it just means execute it,
但不要因为深入到特定行中的细节而打扰我，
but don't bother me by going into the weeds of what is on the specific line,
namely get_int.
也就是 get_int 函数。
So when I click this button in a moment, you'll
所以，当我过会儿点击这个按钮的时候，你就会
see that my terminal, which is still at the bottom, prompts me for a height.
看到我的终端（还在底部）提示我输入高度。
I'm going to go ahead and type 3.
我要输入 3。
As soon as I hit Enter, what part of the screen
当我按下回车键后，屏幕的哪一部分
probably will change based on what I've said?
可能会根据我所说发生变化？
So h, the variable h should hopefully take on the number 3.
所以 h，变量 h 应该会取值为 3。
And I'll probably see a different line of code
而且我可能还会看到不同的代码行
highlighted, probably line 9 next once I'm done executing line 8.
被高亮显示，可能接下来就是第 9 行，一旦我执行完第 8 行。
So let me go ahead and hit Enter and watch the top-left of the screen.
所以我按一下回车键，然后观察屏幕的左上角。
And voila, h now has the value 3, and execution has now paused on line 9
瞧，h 现在值为 3，程序执行已经暂停在第 9 行
because the debugger is allowing me to step through my code line by line.
因为调试器允许我逐行调试代码。
Now let me go ahead and print out-- let me go ahead and just say, all right,
现在让我打印出来，让我先说一下，好吧，
I'm done with this.
我已经完成了。
Let's go ahead and run the rest of the program.
让我们继续执行程序的剩余部分。
It clearly got the value 3.
它明显获取到了 3 这个值。
But wait a minute--
等等，
oh, and at this point, it closed the window
哦，到了这一步，它关闭了窗口
in which I would have seen the output, I would have still seen four hashes.
我本来可以在里面看到输出，我本来还是会看到四个井号。
So let me actually do this again.
所以让我再来一遍。
Let me go back into debug50 by running the exact same command again.
让我再次运行同一个命令，回到 debug50。
It's going to think for a moment, it's going to reconfigure the screen.
它会想一会儿，它会重新配置屏幕。
I'm going to do the exact same thing.
我将执行完全相同的事情。
I'm going to step over this line, but I'd
我要跳过这行，但是我想
like to actually see what's going on inside of my print_column function.
实际看一下我的 print_column 函数内部发生了什么。
So this time, instead of just saying run to the end
所以这次，我不会直接运行到结尾
and close all the windows on me, let me go ahead
并关闭所有窗口，让我继续
and step into my print_column function.
进入我的 print_column 函数。
So don't step over, step into.
所以不要跳过，要进入。
Because if I step over--
因为如果我跳过，
and now this is what I meant to show earlier,
现在这就是我之前想展示的，
you can see that it's still printing out 4.
你可以看到它仍然打印出 4。
So in fact, let me undo this, let me just stop the whole thing.
所以实际上，让我撤销这个操作，让我直接停止整个程序。
Let me rerun the command a final time.
让我最后一次重新运行命令。
So it goes back to where we began before.
所以它又回到了我们之前开始的地方。
It's going to prompt me again once I step over line 8 for a number like 3.
当我跳过第 8 行时，它会再次提示我输入一个数字，比如 3。
But this time, instead of stepping over line 9, let's poke around.
但是这次，我们不是跳过第 9 行，而是探索一下。
I wrote print_column, so let's look at print_column step by step,
我写了 print_column，所以让我们一步一步地看一下 print_column，
step into it, and watch what happens to the yellow highlight.
进入它，然后观察黄色高亮发生了什么。
It now jumps logically to the inside of print_column,
现在它逻辑地跳转到 print_column 的内部，
thereby letting me walk through this code.
从而让我逐行查看这段代码。
And now I can just step over each of these lines one at a time.
现在我可以一次跳过每一行。
So stepping over.
所以跳过。
OK, so what did it do?
好的，它做了什么？
It did that whole narrative that I did verbally last week
它做了上周我用语言描述的整个流程
where it compared i against height.
它将 i 与 height 进行比较。
It then went inside of the loop.
然后它进入循环。
When I click Step Over, watch what happens in my terminal-- one hash
当我点击“跳过”时，观察我的终端发生了什么，一个井号
prints out.
被打印出来。
Now line 14 is highlighted again.
现在第 14 行再次被高亮显示。
It's comparing per the Boolean expression, i,
根据布尔表达式，它正在比较 i，
is it less than or equal to height?
它是否小于或等于 height？
If so, it's going to go ahead and print out the hash.
如果是，它将继续打印出井号。
It's going to do this again, print out the hash.
它将再次执行此操作，打印出井号。
But notice at the top-left of the screen, height
但请注意屏幕的左上角，height
is still the same, it's still 3, but what has been changing, apparently?
仍然保持不变，仍然是 3，但明显发生了变化的是什么？
i on each iteration.
每次迭代中的 i。
So the debugger is letting me see what's going on slowly inside of this loop
所以调试器让我慢慢地看到这个循环内部发生了什么
because i keeps getting incremented.
因为 i 不断地被递增。
So if I step over this line now, notice that I've now printed 3.
所以如果我现在跳过这行，请注意我已经打印了 3 个。
So ideally I want this loop to end, but if I click Step Over once more,
所以理想情况下我希望这个循环结束，但如果我再次点击“跳过”，
notice that the value of i at top-left is 3,
请注意屏幕左上角 i 的值为 3，
but 3 is less than or equal to height-- oh, now I get it, if I play along here.
但 3 小于或等于 height，哦，我现在明白了，如果我继续这样做。
Now I see why less than or equals to, mathematically, is clearly incorrect.
现在我明白为什么从数学角度来说，小于或等于明显是不正确的。
And as soon as that light bulb goes off, you can just sort of
一旦你恍然大悟，你就可以直接
bail out, click the red Stop button to turn the debugger off,
退出，点击红色的“停止”按钮关闭调试器，
go back in, fix your code, and voila, recompile, run it,
重新进入，修复你的代码，瞧，重新编译，运行它，
and you're back in business.
你又可以继续了。
So the takeaways here really are just what tools now exist?
所以这里真正的收获是，现在都有哪些工具？
Printf is your friend, but only for quick-and-dirty debugging techniques.
Printf 是你的好朋友，但它只适用于快速调试的技术。
Get into the habit now of using debug50, and in turn, VS Code's debugger.
现在养成使用 debug50 的习惯，进而使用 VS Code 的调试器。
You will invariably not take this advice, say,
你不可避免地不会采纳这个建议，比如说，
for problem set 2 as you first begin because it's
在开始做第二套问题集时，因为它
going to feel easier and quicker just to use printf, just to use printf,
感觉用 printf 更简单快捷，用 printf 就好了，
just to use printf.
用 printf 就好了。
And the problem with that logic is that you
这种逻辑的问题在于你
begin to build up like technical debt, so to speak,
开始积攒技术债务，可以这么说，
where you really should have learned it earlier,
你本应该早点学习的，
you really should have learned it earlier,
you really should have learned it earlier, at which point,
你本应该早点学习的，那样一来，
you end up spending more time wasted using printf
你最终会浪费更多时间使用 printf
and doing things manually than if you had just spent 10 minutes,
手动操作，而不是花 10 分钟，
30 minutes just learning the user interface
30 分钟学习一下正规调试器的用户界面
and the buttons of a proper debugger.
和按钮。
So please take that advice because it will save you
所以请记住这条建议，因为它会为你节省
significant amounts of time over time.
大量的宝贵时间。
Questions on printf or debugging in this way?
关于 printf 或这种调试方法，有什么问题吗？
Any questions on this?
关于这方面，有什么问题吗？
No?
没有？
OK.
好的。
So let me give you a third and final technique for debugging, which has been
让我来介绍第三种也是最后一种调试技巧，它一直
looming over us here for some time.
潜伏在我们身边。
So there is actually this technique known as rubber duck debugging.
实际上有一种叫做“橡皮鸭调试”的技术。
And in the absence of a roommate who is taking CS50 or who has taken CS50
如果没有一个正在学习 CS50 或已经学过 CS50 的室友
or knows how to program, in the absence of having a TF or TA or CA
或者知道如何编程，如果没有助教或助教组成员，
sitting next to you, in the absence of having a family member available to ask
坐在你旁边，因为没有家人可以问
questions of, if you have simply an inanimate object on your desk,
一些问题，如果你只是在你的桌子上放了一个无生命的物体，
goes the tradition, just talk to that inanimate object.
按照传统，就和那个无生命的物体说话。
Better yet, if it's an adorable rubber duck in this way.
更好的是，如果它是一个可爱的橡皮鸭。
And the idea of rubber duck debugging is that simply
而橡皮鸭调试的想法很简单
by verbalizing literally out loud to this inanimate object--
就是把你的想法大声说出来，对着这个无生命的物体说出来——
probably with the door closed and no one knowing
很可能是在关着门的情况下，没有人知道
that you're talking to this rubber duck, you invariably
你在和这个橡皮鸭说话，你一定会
end up hearing any illogic in your own thoughts, at which point
最终会听到你自己的想法中的任何逻辑错误，此时
the proverbial light bulb tends to go off and you're like, oh, I'm an idiot.
灯泡就会亮起来，你会想，哦，我真是个笨蛋。
It's supposed to be less than, not less than or equal to.
应该是小于，而不是小于等于。
So literally just explaining to a duck or any inanimate object what's
所以，实际上，只要向一只鸭子或任何无生命的物体解释清楚你
going on in your code will quite frequently just
代码中正在发生的事情，就经常会
help you see in your mind's eye what it is you've been doing wrong.
帮助你在脑海中看到你一直在做错的地方。
So rubber duck debugging is indeed a very effective technique
所以，橡皮鸭调试确实是一种非常有效的技巧
even if you don't happen to have a small or large rubber duck.
即使你没有一只大小适宜的橡皮鸭。
Of course, you're also welcome to use the CS50 Duck who
当然，你也可以使用 CS50 鸭子，它
lives at cs50.ai, and also within a pane in VS Code at cs50.dev.
住在 cs50.ai 上，也在 cs50.dev 上的 VS Code 面板中。
You can ask the CS50 Duck about concepts you don't understand,
你可以向 CS50 鸭子询问你不理解的概念，
or you can even copy paste certain lines of code
或者，你甚至可以复制粘贴一些你可能在其中遇到麻烦的代码行
with which you might be having trouble and ask the duck for its own advice.
并向鸭子寻求它自己的建议。
All right.
好的。
So, with those tools in our toolkit, let me propose now that we do--
有了这些工具，我现在提议我们
that we introduce now a few lower-level features of C
介绍一些 C 的底层功能
itself and better understand how we can start solving some of those problems
本身，并更好地理解如何开始解决其中的一些问题
like the readability of text or the encryption of data.
比如文本的可读性或数据的加密。
These were our so-called types last week when
这些就是我们上周所说的类型，当时
we introduced at least a subset of them or used them just to store data
我们至少介绍了其中的一部分，或者只是用它们来存储数据
in a certain format, so to speak.
用某种格式存储，可以这么说。
Like in week 0, we said that everything at the end of the day
就像在第 0 周，我们说过，归根结底
is just 0's and 1's, binary.
只是一些 0 和 1，二进制。
And I claimed conceptually that how a computer knows if a set of bits
我从概念上声称，一台计算机如何知道一组比特
is a number versus a letter versus a color or a sound or an image or a video
是一个数字还是一个字母，还是一种颜色或声音或图像或视频
is just context-dependent, like you're using Photoshop
仅仅取决于上下文，就像你在使用 Photoshop
or you're using Microsoft Word or something else.
或者你正在使用 Microsoft Word 或其他一些东西。
But last week, we saw a little more precisely that it's
但上周，我们更精确地看到了，它
not quite as broad strokes as that.
并不像那样笼统。
It's more about what the programmer has told the software is
更多的是关于程序员告诉软件存储的是什么
being stored in a given variable.
存储在给定的变量中。
Is it an integer?
是一个整数吗？
Is it a char, a character?
是一个字符吗？
Is it a whole string?
是一个字符串吗？
Is it a longer integer or the like?
是一个较长的整数或类似的东西吗？
So you now have this control.
所以你现在有了这种控制权。
The catch, though, recall, though, is that each of these types
不过，请记住，这些类型中的每一个
has only a finite amount of space allocated to it.
只分配了有限的空间。
So for instance, an integer is typically 4 bytes,
例如，一个整数通常是 4 字节，
and 4 bytes is 32 bits because it's 8 times 4.
4 字节是 32 位，因为它是 8 乘以 4。
32 bits, we claimed, is roughly 4 billion,
我们声称，32 位大约是 40 亿，
but if you want to represent negative and positive numbers,
但如果你想表示负数和正数，
the biggest integer you can store is like 2 billion.
你可以存储的最大整数大约是 20 亿。
Now that's really big for a lot of applications,
对于很多应用来说，这确实很大，
but years ago, Facebook, for instance, was
但几年前，例如，Facebook 使用的是
rumored to be using integers when they had fewer users.
整数，因为当时他们的用户还不多。
But now that they have billions of users--
但现在他们拥有数十亿用户——
3-plus billion users, an integer is no longer big enough for the Facebooks,
30 多亿用户，一个整数对于 Facebook、
the Googles, the Microsofts and so forth of the world.
Google、微软等世界巨头来说已经不够大了。
So we also have longs, which use twice as many bytes, but exponentially
所以我们还有 longs，它使用两倍的字节数，但可以表示指数级
bigger range of values.
更大范围的值。
Meanwhile, a bool, interestingly, is a byte, which
与此同时，一个 bool 很有趣，它是一个字节，这
is kind of bad design in what sense?
从某种意义上来说，是一种糟糕的设计？
Why might that be bad design?
为什么这可能是一种糟糕的设计？
It's only-- it should only be 2--
它应该只有 2——
1 bit, rather, because a 0 or 1 should suffice.
1 位，因为 0 或 1 就足够了。
Turns out, it's just easier to use a whole byte
事实证明，使用一个完整的字节更容易
even though we're wasting seven of those bits,
即使我们浪费了其中的七位，
but bools are represented nonetheless with 1 byte.
但 bools 仍然用 1 个字节表示。
Chars are going to be 1 byte.
Chars 将是 1 个字节。
Floats tend to be 4 bytes.
Floats 通常是 4 个字节。
Doubles tend to be 8 bytes.
Doubles 通常是 8 个字节。
Some of this is system-dependent, but nowadays on modern computers,
其中一些是系统相关的，但如今在现代计算机上，
this tends to be a useful rule of thumb.
这往往是一个有用的经验法则。
The only one I can't commit to here is a string
唯一一个我无法在这里确定的就是字符串
because a string, recall, is a sequence of text.
因为字符串，请记住，它是一系列文本。
And maybe it has no characters, one character, two, 10, 100.
它可能没有字符，一个字符，两个字符，十个字符，一百个字符。
So it's a variable number of bytes presumably
所以它可能是一个可变数量的字节，
where each byte represents a given character.
其中每个字节代表一个给定的字符。
So with that said, how do we get from an actual computer
所以，话虽如此，我们如何从实际的计算机
to information being represented therein?
得到其中表示的信息？
Well, let me remind us that this is what's inside of our Macs, PCs, phones.
好吧，让我提醒大家，这就是我们 Mac、PC 和手机内部的东西。
Even though this isn't a scale and it might not be the same shape,
即使这不是一个比例，它可能不是同一个形状，
this is memory, random access memory.
这就是内存，随机存取内存。
And on these black chips, on the circuit board
在这些黑色芯片上，在电路板上
here, are the bytes that we keep talking about.
这里，就是我们一直在谈论的字节。
In fact, let's go ahead and zoom in on one of these chips,
事实上，让我们放大其中一个芯片，
fill the screen here.
填充屏幕。
And just for an artist's depiction's sake,
为了艺术表现的需要，
let me propose that if you've got, I don't know,
我建议，如果你有，我不知道，
a megabyte, a gigabyte-- like a lot of bytes packed into this chip nowadays,
一个兆字节，一个吉字节——就像如今大量字节被压缩到这个芯片中一样，
it stands to reason that no matter how many of them you have,
这是有道理的，无论你有多少个，
we could just number them from top to bottom
我们可以从上到下编号
and we could say that this is byte 1, or you know what?
我们可以说，这是字节 1，或者你知道吗？
This is byte 0, 1, 2, 3, and this is maybe byte 1 billion or whatever it is.
这是字节 0、1、2、3，而这可能是字节 10 亿，或其他任何东西。
So you can think of memory as having addresses
你可以将内存想象成拥有地址
or just locations, numeric indices that identify each of those bytes
或者说是位置，数值索引用于识别每一个字节
individually.
单独地。
Why a byte?
为什么是一个字节？
Individual bits are not that useful, so 8, again, 1 byte
单个比特没有那么有用，所以，再一次，一个字节
tends to be the de facto standard.
往往成为事实上的标准。
Let me-- so, for instance, if you're storing just a single character,
让我…… 比如，如果你只是存储一个字符
a char, it might be stored literally in this top-left corner, so to speak,
一个 char，它可能被存储在，这么说吧，这个左上角
of the chip of memory.
的内存芯片上。
If you're storing maybe an integer, 4 bytes,
如果你存储的是一个整数，4 个字节
it might take up that many bytes.
它可能会占用那么多字节。
If you're storing a long, it might take up that many bytes instead.
如果你存储的是一个长整型，它可能会占用那么多字节。
Now we don't have to dwell on the particulars of the circuit board
现在我们不需要详细了解电路板
and these traces and all the connections, so let me just abstract
以及这些迹线和所有连接，所以我只是抽象一下
this away and claim that what your computer's memory really
它，并声称计算机内存实际上
is is just kind of this canvas, I mean kind of in the Photoshop sense.
是，就是这种画布，我的意思是，有点像 Photoshop 的意义。
If you've ever made pictures, it's just a grid
如果你曾经做过图片，它只是一个网格
of pixels, up, down, left, right, that's really all your memory is.
像素，上下左右，这就是你内存的全部。
It's this canvas that you can manipulate the bits on to store numbers anywhere
这就是这块画布，你可以操作上面的比特，在任何地方存储数字
you want in the computer's memory.
你想要在计算机内存中。
So in fact, let's zoom in here and let's consider
所以，事实上，让我们放大这里，并考虑
how your computer is actually storing information using just these bytes.
你的计算机实际上是如何使用这些字节来存储信息的。
At the end of the day, no matter how sophisticated
最终，无论你的 Mac，你的 PC，你的手机多么复杂
your Mac, your PC, your phone is, like this is all
你的 Mac，你的 PC，你的手机，它所拥有的一切
it has access to for storing information.
可以用来存储信息。
It's a canvas of bytes, and what you do with this
它是一个字节的画布，你用它做什么
now really invites design decisions.
现在确实需要一些设计决策。
So let's consider this.
所以，让我们考虑一下。
Here is an excerpt from a program wherein maybe I'm
这里是从一个程序中摘录的一部分，我可能
prompting the user for three scores.
提示用户输入三个分数。
Like three test, scores, exam scores, something like that.
就像三个考试分数，测验分数，诸如此类。
And the purpose in life of this program is maybe
这个程序的目的是，也许
to average those three scores together if you
将这三个分数加在一起取平均值，如果你
want to get a sense of where you stand in some class.
想了解你在某个班级的成绩如何。
So we can certainly whip up some code like this.
所以我们当然可以写出这样的代码。
And in just a moment, let me go ahead and flip over to VS Code here.
过一会儿，让我切换到 VS Code。
And I'll write up a new program called scores.c.
我会写一个名为 scores.c 的新程序。
And in this, let me go ahead and first include stdio.h,
在里面，我首先要包含 stdio.h，
int main void at the top.
int main void 在最上面。
And in here, let me go ahead and assume that, eh,
在里面，我假设，呃
it's not been the greatest semester.
这学期过得不太好。
So my first score, which I'll call score1, was a 72,
所以我的第一个分数，我叫它 score1，是 72，
my second score was a 73, but my third score, score3, was like a 33.
我的第二个分数是 73，但我的第三个分数，score3，是 33。
Now you might remember these numbers in another context,
你现在可能在另一个情境中记得这些数字
they might spell a message, but in this case, it's just integers.
它们可能拼出一个消息，但在这个例子中，它只是整数。
It's just numbers because I'm telling the computer to treat these as ints.
它只是数字，因为我告诉计算机将它们视为整数。
Now if I want to figure out what my average is, I can do a bit of math.
现在，如果我想知道我的平均成绩，我可以做一些数学运算。
So let me just print out that my average is--
所以，让我输出我的平均成绩是——
and I don't want to shortchange myself.
我不想低估自己。
I'm not going to use %i because I don't want to lose even anything after
我不会使用 %i，因为我不想丢失小数点后的任何东西
the decimal point.
小数点。
So we're going to use a float instead.
所以我们将使用浮点数。
And my average i claim will be score1 plus score2 plus score3
而我的平均成绩，我声称是 score1 加上 score2 加上 score3
divided by 3, semicolon.
除以 3，分号。
With parentheses, because just like grade school math,
用括号，因为就像小学数学一样
like order of operations, I parenthesize the numerator,
就像运算顺序一样，我把分子加了括号
so I can divide the whole thing by 3.
这样我才能把整个式子除以 3。
But I have screwed up already.
但我已经搞砸了。
I am going to shortchange myself and not give myself as high a grade
我要低估自己，不给自己一个那么高的分数
as I deserve, but this one's subtle.
如我应得，但这有点微妙。
What have I done wrong?
我做错了什么？
Yeah, I might want to cast these scores to floats
是的，我可能想把这些分数转换为浮点数
because if you do integral math, divide an integer or the sum of an integers--
因为如果你做整数运算，用一个整数或多个整数的和来除
some integers by an integer, it's going to be an integer as the result,
一些整数，结果会是一个整数
so it's going to throw away anything after the decimal point.
所以它会丢弃小数点后的任何东西。
Even if it's something-point-1, something-point-5, something-point-9,
即使是某个数点 1，某个数点 5，某个数点 9
that fraction is going to be thrown away.
那个分数会被丢弃。
There's a bunch of ways to fix this.
有很多方法可以解决这个问题。
I could just use floats or doubles for all of these.
我可以直接对所有这些使用浮点数或双精度浮点数。
I could cast score1, score2, or score3 as you propose.
我也可以像你建议的那样将 score1、score2 或 score3 转换为浮点数。
Frankly, the simplest way is just change the denominator
坦率地说，最简单的方法就是改变分母
because so long as I've got one float involved in the math,
因为只要我的数学运算中包含一个浮点数
this will promote the whole arithmetic expression to being floating point
这将使整个算术表达式变为浮点运算
math instead of integer math.
而不是整数运算。
So let me go ahead now and do make scores, Enter.
所以我现在要执行 make scores，回车。
So far, so good. ./scores, and my average seems to be not great,
目前为止，一切都好。./scores，我的平均成绩似乎不太好
but 59.33333--
但 59.33333——
so in the third.
所以排在第三名。
But I would have lost that third if I hadn't
但如果我没有
used a float in this particular way.
用这种特殊方式使用浮点数，我就可能丢掉第三名。
Well, let's consider now what's actually going on inside of the computer
现在让我们看看计算机内部实际发生了什么
when I store these three variables.
当我存储这三个变量的时候。
So, back to the grid here, just my canvas of memory.
所以，回到这个网格，我的内存画布。
It doesn't really matter where things end up.
实际上，最终的位置并不重要。
I might put it here, I might put it there,
我可能会把它放在这里，我可能会把它放在那里
the computer makes these decisions.
这些都是由计算机决定的。
But for the artist's sake, I'm going to put it at the top left-hand corner
但是，为了艺术家的考虑，我要把它放在左上角
here.
这里。
So, score1 is containing the integer 72.
所以，score1 包含整数 72。
Why is it taking up four squares, though?
但是，为什么它占用了四个方格呢？
Because?
因为？
It's an integer.
它是一个整数。
And on this system, an integer is 4 bytes.
在这个系统上，一个整数是 4 个字节。
So I've drawn it to scale, if you will. score2 is the number 73,
所以，如果可以的话，我已经按比例绘制了。score2 是数字 73
it also takes 4 bytes.
它也占用了 4 个字节。
By coincidence, but also by convention, it
will likely end up next to the first integer
in memory because I've only got three variables going on anyway,
so the computer quite likely will store them back to back to back.
And indeed, by that logic, score3, containing the number 33,
is going to fill in this space here.
We'll consider down the road what happens
if things get fragmented-- something's here,
something's here, something's here, but for now, we
can assume that this is probably contiguous, though not necessarily so.
All right, so that's pretty straightforward,
but what's really going on?
Well, these are just bytes of memory--
that is, bits of memory times 8.
And so what's really going on is this pattern
of 0's and 1's is being stored to represent 72.
This pattern of 0's and 1's is being stored
to represent 73, and similarly, 33.
But that's a very low level detail that we don't really care about,
so we'll generally just think about these as numbers like 72, 73, 33.
All right.
So if we go back to the actual code, though, here, I
wonder if this is the best idea.
These three lines of code are correct.
I got my 59 and 1/3 for my average, which I claim
is correct, but code-wise, this should maybe rub you the wrong way.
Even if you hadn't programmed before CS50,
why might this not be the best approach to storing things
like scores in a program?
How might this get us in trouble?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
It's not the best because you have to use a whole bunch
of different variables for each score.
They're almost identically named, though, but just imagine
in almost any question involving the design of your code, what happens is n,
the number of things involved, gets larger?
Am I really going to start writing code that has score4, score5, score6,
score10, score20?
I mean, your code is just going to look like this mess of mostly copy-paste
except that the number at the end of the variable is changing.
Like that should make you cringe a little bit because it's not
going to end well eventually.
And typographical errors are going to get in the way most likely
because we'll make mistakes.
So how can we do a little bit better than that?
Well, let me propose that we introduce what we're going to now call an array.
An array is a sequence of values back to back to back in memory.
So an array is just a chunk of memory storing values back to back to back.
So no gaps, no fragmentation.
From left to right, top to bottom, just as I already drew.
But these arrays in C, at least, are going
to give a slightly new syntax that addresses exactly your concern.
So here instead is I would propose how you define a one variable--
not three, one variable called scores, plural, each of whose values
is going to be an int, and you want three integers tucked away
in that variable.
So now I can pluralize the name of my variable
because by using square brackets and the number 3, I'm telling the compiler,
give me enough room for not one, not two, but three integers in total.
And the computer is going to do me a favor by storing them back
to back to back in the computer's memory.
Now assigning values to these variables is almost the same,
but the syntax looks like this.
To assign the first value, I do scores, bracket, 0 equals whatever, 72.
scores, bracket, 1 equals 73; scores, bracket, 2 equals 33.
And it's square brackets consistently.
And notice, this is a feature--
or a downside of C.
We very frequently use the same syntax for slightly different ideas.
This first line tells the computer, give me an array of size 3.
These next three lines mean, go into this array at location 0
and put this value there.
Location 1, put this value there; location 2, put this value there.
So same syntax, but different meaning depending on the context here.
But the equal sign indeed means that this is assignment from right
to left just like last week.
So what does this mean in the computer's memory?
Well, in this case here, we now have a slightly different way of doing this.
And actually, let me do it first in code.
Let me go back to VS Code here, and let me
propose that instead of having these three separate variables,
let me give myself an int, scores variable of size 3,
and then do scores, bracket, 0 equals 72; scores, bracket, 1 equals 73;
scores, bracket, 2 equals 33.
And now I have to change this syntax slightly, but same idea.
scores, bracket, 0; scores, bracket, 1; and lastly, scores, bracket, 2.
So a couple of key details.
I started counting at 0.
Why?
That's just the way it is with arrays.
You must start counting at 0 unless you want to waste one of those spaces.
And what you definitely don't want to do is
go into scores, bracket, 3 because I only
进入分数，方括号，3，因为我只
ask the computer for three integers.
要求计算机提供三个整数。
If I blindly do something like this, you're going too far.
如果我盲目地做这样的事情，那就太过分了。
You're going beyond the end of the chunk of memory
你超出了内存块的末尾
and bad things will often happen.
而且通常会出现不好的事情。
So we won't do that just yet.
所以我们现在还不这样做。
But for now, 0, 1, and 2 are the first, second, and third locations.
但目前，0、1和2是第一个、第二个和第三个位置。
So if I recompile this code-- so make scores seems OK. ./scores,
所以如果我重新编译这段代码 - 所以分数看起来没问题。./scores，
and I get the exact same answer there.
我得到了完全相同的答案。
But let me make it more dynamic because this
但我让它更动态，因为这
is a little stupid that I'm compiling a program with my scores hardcoded.
我用我的分数硬编码编译程序，这有点愚蠢。
What if I have a fourth exam tomorrow or something like that?
如果我明天有第四次考试之类的事情怎么办？
So let's make it more dynamic and I think
所以让我们让它更动态，我认为
the syntax will start to make a little more sense.
语法将开始变得更有意义。
Let's go ahead and use get_int and ask the user for a score.
让我们继续使用 get_int 并询问用户分数。
Let's go ahead and get_int and ask the user for another score.
让我们继续使用 get_int 并询问用户另一个分数。
Let's go ahead and get_int and ask the user for a third score,
让我们继续使用 get_int 并询问用户第三个分数，
now storing the return values in each of those variables.
现在将返回值存储在每个变量中。
If I now do make scores--
如果我现在执行 make scores -
oh, darn it.
哦，该死。
a mistake.
犯了一个错误。
Similar to one I've made before, but we didn't see the error message last time.
与我之前犯过的错误类似，但我们上次没有看到错误信息。
What'd I do wrong?
我做错了什么？
Yeah?
是吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: OK.
大卫·马兰：好的。
What did I do wrong-- how about over here?
我做错了什么 - 在这里呢？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
大卫·马兰：对。
So I'm missing the CS50 header file.
所以，我缺少 CS50 头文件。
So how do you know that?
你怎么知道？
Well, implicit declaration of function get_int.
嗯，隐式声明函数 get_int。
So it just doesn't know what get_int is.
所以它不知道 get_int 是什么。
Well, who does know what get_int is?
好吧，谁知道 get_int 是什么？
The CS50 Library, that should be your first instinct.
CS50 库，这应该是你的第一直觉。
All right.
好吧。
Let me go to the top here and let me go ahead and squeeze in the CS50 Library
让我到顶端，然后我继续将 CS50 库挤进去
like this.
像这样。
Now let me clear my terminal.
现在让我清空我的终端。
make scores again.
再次执行 make scores。
We're back in business.
我们回来了。
And notice, I don't need to do -l cs50.
注意，我不需要执行 -l cs50。
make is doing that for me for clang, but we don't even see clang being executed,
make 正在为我执行 clang，但我们甚至看不到 clang 被执行，
but it is being executed underneath the hood, so to speak.
但它是在幕后执行的，可以这么说。
All right, so ./scores, here we go.
好吧，所以 ./scores，我们开始了。
72, 73, 33.
72、73、33。
Math is still the same, but now the program is more interactive.
数学仍然是一样的，但现在程序更具交互性。
Now this, too, hopefully should rub you the wrong way.
现在，我希望这也会让你感到不舒服。
This is correct, I would claim, but bad design still.
我认为这是正确的，但设计仍然不好。
Reeks of week 0 inefficiencies.
散发出第 0 周的低效率。
Yeah?
是吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: OK.
大卫·马兰：好的。
So I could ask the human how many scores do you want to input?
所以我可以问人类，你想要输入多少分数？
Let's come back to that.
让我们回到这一点。
But I think even in this construct, what better could I do?
但即使在这种结构中，我还能做些什么呢？
Use a loop, right?
使用循环，对吧？
Because I'm literally doing the same thing again and again.
因为我实际上是重复做着同样的事情。
And notice, this number is just changing slightly.
注意，这个数字只是稍微改变了。
I would think that a little plus-plus could help there. get_int Score,
我认为一个小小的加加可以帮助解决这个问题。 get_int Score，
get_int Score, get_int Score-- that's the exact same thing.
get_int Score、get_int Score - 这完全一样。
So a loop is a perfect solution here.
所以循环是这里完美的解决方案。
So let me go over into this code here, and I can still for now
所以让我看看这段代码，目前我仍然可以
declare it to be of size 3, but I think I
声明它的大小为 3，但我认为我可以
could do something like this-- for int i get 0, i is less than 3,
可以做这样的事情 - for int i 等于 0，i 小于 3，
so I'm not going to make the same buggy mistake as I made earlier.
所以，我不会犯和我之前一样的错误。
I++.
i++。
Inside of the loop now, I can do scores, bracket, i, and now
现在在循环内部，我可以执行 scores，方括号，i，现在
arrays are getting really interesting because you
数组变得非常有趣，因为你
can use and reuse them, but dynamically go to a specific location.
可以使用和重用它们，但可以动态地跳转到特定的位置。
Equals get_int, quote-unquote, "Score."
等于 get_int，引号，"分数"。
Now I can type that phrase just once and this loop ultimately
现在我可以只输入一次这个短语，而这个循环最终
will do the same thing, but it's getting better.
会做同样的事情，但它正在变得更好。
The code is getting better designed because it's more compact
代码设计得更好，因为它更加紧凑
and I'm not repeating myself.
而且我不再重复自己。
72, 73, 33.
72、73、33。
Still works the same, but we're iteratively improving the code here.
仍然是同样的效果，但我们正在迭代地改进这里的代码。
Now how else-- there's one design flaw here that I still don't love
现在还有什么 - 这里有一个设计缺陷，我仍然不喜欢
it's a little more subtle.
它更加微妙。
Any observations?
有什么观察？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Ah, interesting.
大卫·马兰：啊，有趣。
So instead of dividing by 3.0, maybe I should divide it
所以，与其除以 3.0，也许我应该除以
by the array size, which at the moment is technically still 3,
数组大小，目前技术上仍然是 3，
but I do concur that that is worrisome because they could get out of sync.
但我同意，这令人担忧，因为它们可能不同步。
But there's something else that still isn't quite right.
但还有其他一些地方不太对劲。
Yeah?
是吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: I'm OK moving to this zero-indexed model.
大卫·马兰：我不介意转向这种从零开始的索引模型。
So this is a new term of art.
所以这是一个新的术语。
To index into an array means to go to a specific location.
索引到数组意味着跳转到特定的位置。
So here, I'm indexing into location i, but i is going
所以，在这里，我正在索引到位置 i，但 i 将要
to start at 0 and then 1 and then 2.
从 0 开始，然后是 1，然后是 2。
I'm actually OK with that.
我实际上对这一点没有意见。
Even though in common day life we would say score1, score2, score3,
即使在日常生活中我们会说分数 1，分数 2，分数 3，
as a programmer, I just have to get into the habit
作为一名程序员，我必须养成
of saying score0, score1, score2 now.
现在说分数 0，分数 1，分数 2 的习惯。
But something else.
但还有其他事情。
Yeah?
是吗？
AUDIENCE: I could compute the average.
观众：我可以计算平均值。
DAVID MALAN: I could also compute the average in a loop
大卫·马兰： 我也可以在循环中计算平均值
because indeed, this is only going-- so solving the problem halfway.
因为实际上，这仅仅是解决问题的一半。
I'm gathering the information in the loop,
我在循环中收集信息，
but then I'm manually writing it all out.
但是之后我又手动把所有信息都写出来。
So it does feel like there should be a better solution here.
所以感觉这里应该有更好的解决方案。
But let me also identify one other issue I really don't like,
但让我指出另一个我不喜欢的点，
and this is, indeed, subtle.
这确实很微妙。
I've got 3 here, I've got 3 here, and I essentially have 3 here,
这里有 3，这里也有 3，这里本质上也有 3，
albeit a floating point version.
尽管是浮点数版本。
This is just ripe for me making a mistake eventually and changing one
这样很容易让我最终犯错，改变其中一个
of those values, but not the other two?
值，而不是另外两个？
So how might I fix this?
那么我该如何解决呢？
I might at least do something like this.
我至少可以做这样的事。
I could say integer maybe n for scores, I'll set that equal to 3.
我可以说整数，比如 scores 的 n，我将其设置为 3。
I could then use n here, I could use n here.
然后我可以在此处使用 n，也可以在此处使用 n。
I could use n here, but that's a step backwards
我可以在此处使用 n，但这是一种倒退
because I don't want an int because I'm going to run into the same math issue
因为我不想要一个 int，因为我将遇到与之前相同数学问题
as before, but I could convert it-- that is, cast it to a float,
就像之前一样，但我可以将其转换，即将其转换为浮点数，
and we did that briefly last week.
我们上周简单地做了这件事。
But there's one other thing I could do here that we did introduce last week.
但还有另一件事，我们上周介绍过。
This is better because I don't have a magic number floating around
这样做更好，因为我没有一个魔法数字到处乱飘
in multiple places.
在多个地方。
Yeah, if I really want to be proper, I should probably
是的，如果我真想严格一点，我应该
say this should be a constant integer.
说这应该是一个常量整数。
Why?
为什么？
Because I don't want to accidentally change it myself.
因为我不想意外地自己改变它。
I don't want to be collaborating with a colleague
我不想与同事合作
and they foolishly change it on me.
然后他们愚蠢地改变它。
This just sends a stronger signal to the compiler, do not let the humans change
这样向编译器发送更强烈的信号，不要让人类改变
this value.
这个值。
And now just to point out one other feature of C,
现在，只是指出 C 语言的另一个特性，
if you have a number like this, like the number 3,
如果你有一个像这样的数字，比如数字 3，
I've deliberately capitalized this variable name really
我特意将这个变量名首字母大写，
for the first time.
这是第一次。
Any time you have a constant, it tends to be a convention
任何时候你有一个常量，它往往是一个约定
to capitalize it just to draw your attention to it.
将其首字母大写只是为了引起你的注意。
It doesn't mean anything technically.
从技术上讲，这没有任何意义。
Capitalizing a variable does nothing to it,
将变量首字母大写对其没有任何影响，
but it draws attention visually to it to the human.
但它在视觉上提醒了人类。
So if you declare something as a constant,
因此，如果你将某个东西声明为常量，
it's commonplace to capitalize it just because.
通常的做法就是将其首字母大写。
Moreover, if you have a constant that you might want to occasionally modify--
此外，如果你有一个你可能偶尔想要修改的常量 -
maybe next semester when there's four exams or five exams instead of three,
也许下学期会有四次或五次考试，而不是三次，
it actually is OK sometimes to define what
实际上，有时可以定义
might be called a global variable, a variable that is not
可以称之为全局变量，一个不在
inside of curly braces, it's literally at the top of the file outside of main,
花括号内，它实际上位于文件顶部，main 函数之外，
and despite what I said about scope last week,
尽管上周我说了关于作用域的事情，
a global variable like this on line 4 will be in scope
像第 4 行这样的全局变量将在这个作用域内
to every function in this file.
对这个文件中的每个函数都有效。
So it's actually a way of sharing a variable
所以这实际上是一种在
across multiple functions, which is generally fine if you're
多个函数之间共享变量的方法，如果你使用的是常量，通常没问题。
using a constant.
使用常量。
If you intend to change it, there's probably a better way
如果你打算改变它，可能还有更好的方法
than actually using a global variable, but this is just
而不是真的使用全局变量，但这仅仅是
in contrast to what I previously did, which I would
与我之前所做的形成对比，我会将其称之为
call, by contrast, a local variable.
对比而言，一个局部变量。
But again, I'm just trying to reduce the probability of making mistakes
但再一次，我只是想降低犯错的概率
somewhere in the code.
在代码中的某个地方。
And I do agree.
我同意。
I don't like that I'm still adding all of these scores
我不喜欢我仍然手动添加所有这些分数
manually even though clearly I had a loop a moment ago.
手动添加，尽管我刚才明显使用了循环。
But for now, let's at least consider what's
但现在，让我们至少考虑一下
been going on inside of the computer's memory.
计算机内存中发生了什么。
So with this array, I now have not three variables, score1, score2, score3.
因此，使用这个数组，我现在不是三个变量，score1，score2，score3。
I have one variable, an array variable, called scores, plural.
我有一个变量，一个数组变量，称为 scores，复数形式。
And if I want to access the first element, its scores, bracket, 0.
如果我想访问第一个元素，就是 scores，中括号，0。
If I want to access the second element, its scores, bracket, 1.
如果我想访问第二个元素，就是 scores，中括号，1。
If I want to access the third element, it's scores, bracket, 2.
如果我想访问第三个元素，就是 scores，中括号，2。
If I were to make a mistake and do scores, bracket, 3,
如果我犯错，写成 scores，中括号，3，
which is the fourth element, I'd end up in no man's land here,
这是第四个元素，我将陷入无人区，
and worst case, your program could crash or something weird will happen,
最糟糕的情况是，你的程序可能会崩溃，或者发生一些奇怪的事情，
spinning beach balls, those kinds of things.
出现旋转的沙漏，类似的事情。
Just don't make those mistakes.
不要犯这种错误。
And C makes it easy to make those mistakes,
C 语言很容易让你犯这些错误，
so the onus is really on you programmatically.
所以责任实际上在你，你需要通过编程来解决。
Questions on this use of arrays?
关于数组的这种使用，有什么问题吗？
Question on this use of arrays?
Yeah, in back.
是的，后面那位。
AUDIENCE: Is there any way [INAUDIBLE]?
观众： 有没有办法 [听不清]？
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
大卫·马兰： 非常好的问题。
Is there any way to create an array just by using syntax alone
有没有办法只使用语法，
without prompting the human for it?
而不提示用户？
Short answer, yes.
简短的回答是，可以。
If you want to have an array of integers called, for instance, array,
如果你想要一个叫做 array 的整数数组，
you could actually do like 13, 42, 50, something like this,
你实际上可以写成 13, 42, 50，类似这样的形式，
would give you an array if you use this syntax.
如果你使用这种语法，它将给你一个数组。
This would give you an array of size 3 where the three values by default
这样会给你一个大小为 3 的数组，其中三个值默认情况下
are 13, 42 and 50.
分别为 13, 42 和 50。
It's not syntax we'll use for now, but there is syntax like that.
我们现在不会使用这种语法，但确实存在这样的语法。
It's not quite as user-friendly, though, as other languages
不过，它不像其他语言那样用户友好
if you've indeed programmed before.
如果你以前确实进行过编程。
Other questions on this use of arrays?
关于数组的这种使用，还有其他问题吗？
Yeah, in front.
是的，前面那位。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Is there a way to copy what?
大卫·马兰： 有没有办法复制什么？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Oh, is there a way to calculate the length of an array?
大卫·马兰：哦，有没有办法计算数组的长度？
Short answer, no, and I'm about to show you one demonstration of this.
简短的回答，没有，我将展示一个演示。
Those of you who have programmed before in Java, in JavaScript,
你们中之前用 Java 或 JavaScript 编程过的人，
in certain other languages, it's very easy to get the length of an array.
在其他某些语言中，获取数组的长度非常容易。
You essentially just ask the array, what's its length?
你只需要问问数组，它的长度是多少？
C does not give you that capability.
C 语言没有提供这种功能。
The onus is entirely on you and me to remember, s as with another variable,
记住数组的长度，就像其他变量一样，
like n, how long the array is.
就像变量 n 一样，记住数组的长度。
And so in fact, let me go ahead and do this.
实际上，让我继续做这件事。
I'm going to go ahead and open up a baking style, a program
我将打开一个烘焙风格的程序，
that I wrote in advance here which kind of escalates quickly,
我提前写好的，它会很快升级，
but there's not really too many new ideas here except for the array
除了数组之外，这里没有太多新想法，
specifics.
细节。
So this is scores.c premade this time.
所以这次是预先制作的 scores.c。
And notice what I have.
注意我有什么。
One, I've included cs50.h and stdio.h at the top, so that's the same.
首先，我在顶部包含了 cs50.h 和 stdio.h，所以这和之前一样。
I have declared a constant called n, set it equal to 3.
我声明了一个名为 n 的常量，并将其设置为 3。
That is now the same as of my most recent change.
这与我最近的修改相同。
I did introduce an average function, which was one of the remaining concerns
我引入了一个 average 函数，这是我剩下的一个问题，
that I could compute the average with some kind of loop, too.
我可以使用某种循环计算平均值。
That average function is going to return a float, which is what.
average 函数将返回一个浮点数，也就是。
I want my average to be a float with the fraction.
我希望我的平均值是一个带小数的浮点数。
But notice this.
但请注意这一点。
In answer to your question, if I want a function called
为了回答你的问题，如果我想要一个名为
average to do something iterate over an array step by step by step,
average 的函数来做一些事情，一步步地遍历数组，
add up all the numbers, and divide by the total number of numbers,
将所有数字加起来，然后除以数字总数，
I need to give it the array of numbers, and I need to tell it how many of those
我需要将数字数组传递给它，并且需要告诉它有多少个
numbers are.
数字。
So I literally have to pass in two values.
因此我必须传递两个值。
Meanwhile, this code is the same as before inside of main.
同时，这段代码在 main 函数内部与之前相同。
I'm declaring a variable called scores of size n.
我声明了一个名为 scores 的变量，大小为 n。
I'm iterating from i to n.
我从 i 迭代到 n。
And actually-- yep.
实际上 - 是的。
And then in this loop, I'm assigning each of the scores a return
然后在这个循环中，我为每个分数分配一个返回值
value of get_int.
get_int 的值。
The last line of main is this-- print out the average with f,
main 函数的最后一行是 - 使用 f 打印平均值，
but don't just do it manually by adding and dividing with parentheses.
但不要使用括号手动进行加法和除法。
Call the average function, pass in the length of the array and the array
调用 average 函数，传入数组的长度和数组
itself, and hope that it returns a float that then gets plugged into percent f
本身，并希望它返回一个浮点数，然后被插入到百分号 f 中
So I would claim that pretty much all of this, even though it's a lot,
所以我会说，尽管代码量很大，但这几乎所有东西
should be familiar.
都应该很熟悉。
There's no real new ideas except for this use of the global variable now
除了现在使用全局变量以及
and this average function.
average 函数之外，没有真正的新想法。
So let me scroll down to the average function
所以让我向下滚动到 average 函数，
because this is the takeaway from this final example.
因为这是从这个最后的例子中得到的启示。
In this example here--
在这个例子中 -
let me scroll up to the average function,
让我向上滚动到 average 函数，
copy-pasted the prototype for the very first line.
复制粘贴了第一行的原型。
And here's how I'm computing the average.
这是我计算平均值的方法。
There's different ways of doing this, but here's an accumulator way.
有多种方法可以做到这一点，但这里是一种累加器方法。
On line 28, I'm declaring a variable inside of the average function called
在第 28 行，我在 average 函数内部声明了一个名为
sum, and I'm just initializing it to 0.
sum 的变量，并且将其初始化为 0。
Why?
为什么？
Mentally I want to add up all of the person scores
在脑海中，我想将所有人的分数加起来
and then I want to divide by the total and that's my mathematical average.
然后除以总数，这就是我的数学平均值。
So here's my loop where I'm iterating from 0 up to, but not
所以这是我的循环，我从 0 迭代到，但不包括
through the length-- so that should be three times.
长度 - 因此应该是三次。
I am adding to the sum variable whatever is at the i-th location, so to speak,
我将 i 位置的值添加到 sum 变量中，可以这么说，
of the array.
数组中的值。
So this is array, bracket 0; array, bracket, 1; array, bracket,
所以这是数组，方括号 0；数组，方括号，1；数组，方括号，
2 on each iteration.
在每次迭代中都是 2。
And then the last thing I'm doing is a nice one-liner.
最后我要做的是一个简洁的一行代码。
I'm dividing the sum, which is an int, which is the sum of 72, 73, 33,
我将 sum 除以 length，sum 是一个整数，是 72、73、33 的总和，
divided by the length, which is 3, but 3 is not a float, so I cast it to a float
除以 length，length 是 3，但 3 不是浮点数，所以将其强制转换为浮点数
so that the end value, hopefully, is going to be 59.33333 and so forth.
这样，最终的值，希望是 59.33333 等等。
So the only thing that's weird syntactically is this, though.
所以唯一语法上奇怪的是这个。
When you define a function in C that takes an argument that isn't just
在 C 语言中定义一个函数，它接受一个参数，该参数不仅仅是
a simple char, isn't just a simple integer, it's actually an array,
一个简单的字符，也不仅仅是一个简单的整数，它实际上是一个数组，
you don't have to know the array's length in advance.
你不必提前知道数组的长度。
You can just put square brackets after the name you give it.
你只需要在给它起的名字后面加上方括号。
And I don't have to call it array.
我无需称它为 array。
I could call it x or y or z or anything else.
我可以称它为 x 或 y 或 z 或其他任何东西。
I called it array just to make clear that it's an array,
我称之为 array 只是为了明确它是一个数组，
but you do need to know the length somehow.
但你必须以某种方式知道长度。
OK.
好的。
Questions on combining those ideas in that there way?
关于将这些想法以这种方式组合在一起，有什么问题吗？
Any questions?
还有其他问题吗？
No?
没有？
All right.
好的。
Well, we've only dealt with numbers thus far.
好吧，到目前为止，我们只处理了数字。
It would be nice to actually deal with letters and words and paragraphs
能够处理字母、单词和段落，
and the like, much like our readability example,
等等，就像我们的可读性示例一样，
but I think first, some snacks and some fruit are served in the transept.
但我认为首先，一些小吃和水果将在横廊提供。
So we'll see you in 10.
所以我们 10 分钟后再见。
See you in 10.
10 分钟后再见。
All right.
好的。
So we're back.
所以我们回来了。
And up until now, we've been representing
直到现在，我们一直在表示
just numbers underneath the hood, but we've
只是幕后数字，但我们已经
introduced arrays, which gave us this ability, recall,
引入了数组，它赋予了我们这种能力，记得吗？
to store numbers back to back to back.
存储连续的数字。
So it turns out, you actually had this capability for the past
事实证明，你实际上在上周就拥有了这种能力，
week even though you might not have realized it.
即使你可能没有意识到。
And let me propose that we first consider very simple example of three
让我们先考虑一个非常简单的例子，有三个
chars instead of three integers.
字符，而不是三个整数。
And for simplistically, I'm going to call them c1, c2,
为了简单起见，我将它们称为 c1、c2，
and c3 just for the sake of discussion.
以及 c3，仅供讨论。
But I'm going to put our familiar characters, "HI!"
但是，我将使用单引号将我们熟悉的字符“HI！”
in those variables using single quotes because again.
放入这些变量中，因为再次。
That's what you do when using individual chars
这就是使用单个字符时要做的
to make the point that I can store three chars in three separate variables.
是为了说明我可以在三个单独的变量中存储三个字符。
So let me go ahead and go over to VS Code
所以让我继续去 VS Code
here and let me create something called hi.c.
这里，让我创建一个名为 hi.c 的文件。
And in this program, I'll first include stdio.h, int main void as before.
在这个程序中，我将首先包含 stdio.h，int main void，如前所述。
And then inside of main, let's just do exactly that.
然后在 main 内部，我们只需要做这些。
Char c1 equals, quote-unquote, capital H. Char C2 equals,
Char c1 等于，引号，大写 H。Char C2 等于，
quote-unquote, capital I. Char C3 equals,
引号，大写 I。Char C3 等于，
quote-unquote, exclamation point.
引号，感叹号。
So clearly not the best approach, but just for demonstration's sake.
显然，这不是最好的方法，但只是为了演示。
And here now that you understand hopefully
现在你应该明白
from week 1 that really number-- and really, from week 0,
从第一周开始，数字实际上是-- 实际上，从第零周开始，
that numbers are just letters, which can be something more, too.
数字只是字母，也可以是更多的东西。
We can really just use our basic understanding of C
我们实际上只需要使用我们对 C 的基本理解
to tinker with these ideas now and see them such
来研究这些想法，看看它们
that there is indeed going to be no magic happening for us ultimately.
最终不会有任何魔法发生。
So let me go ahead and print out three characters-- %c, %c, %c, backslash n.
所以，让我继续打印出三个字符-- %c、%c、%c、反斜杠 n。
And then print out c1, c2, c3.
然后打印出 c1、c2、c3。
So I've got three separate placeholders.
所以我有三个单独的占位符。
And we haven't really had occasion to use %c, but it means put char here,
我们还没有真正使用 %c 的机会，但它的意思是把 char 放到这里，
unlike %s, which is put a whole string here, or %i, put an integer.
与 %s 不同，它把整个字符串放在这里，或者 %i，把整数放在这里。
Let me go ahead and make hi, no syntax errors, ./hi,
让我继续创建 hi，没有语法错误，./hi，
and it should print out "HI!"
它应该打印出“HI！”
in exclamation points because I'm printing out
用感叹号，因为我打印的是
just three simple characters.
三个简单的字符。
But per our discussion as far back as week 0,
但正如我们在第零周的讨论中提到的，
letters are just numbers and numbers are just letters,
字母只是数字，数字只是字母，
it just depends on the context in which we use them.
这取决于我们使用它们的上下文。
So let me change this %c to an i.
所以让我把这个 %c 改成 i。
And I'm going to add a space just so that you can obviously
我将添加一个空格，这样你就可以很明显地
separate one number from another.
将一个数字与另一个数字分开。
Change this to i, change this to i, but still print out c1, c2, c3.
将这个改成 i，将这个改成 i，但仍然打印出 c1、c2、c3。
So no integers, per se.
所以，严格来说，没有整数。
Let me just print out those chars.
让我只打印出这些字符。
Let me do make hi, no errors, ./hi, and now I see 72, 73, 33.
让我执行 make hi，没有错误，./hi，现在我看到 72、73、33。
So in the case of chars and ints, you can actually treat one as the other
所以，对于字符和整数来说，你实际上可以将其中一个视为另一个
so long as you have enough bits to fit one in the other.
只要你有足够的位来容纳其中一个。
You don't have to cast even or do anything explicitly.
你甚至不需要进行强制类型转换或显式地做任何事情。
You do have to cast one of--
你确实需要将其中一个--
converting an integer to a float to make clear to the compiler
将一个整数转换为浮点数，以便让编译器清楚地知道
that you really intend to do this because that
你确实想这样做，因为
could be destructive if it can't quite represent the number as you intend.
如果它无法按照你的意愿表示这个数字，可能会破坏性。
But in this case here, I think we're OK just poking around and seeing
但在这种情况下，我认为我们没问题，只要四处看看，看看
what's going on underneath the hood.
引擎盖下发生了什么。
Well, what is going on underneath the hood memory-wise?
那么，从内存的角度来看，引擎盖下发生了什么？
Well, something very similar.
嗯，非常相似。
Here's that canvas of memory.
这是内存的画布。
And maybe we got lucky and it's in the top left-hand corner
也许我们很幸运，它在左上角
like this-- c1, c2, c3.
像这样-- c1、c2、c3。
But these are just three individual characters,
但这些只是三个单独的字符，
but we're getting awfully close to what we last week called
但我们越来越接近上周所说的
a string, which are just characters, a sequence of characters
字符串，它只是字符，从左到右的字符序列
from left to right.
从左到右。
And in fact, I think if we combine this revelation that these are just
事实上，我认为如果我们将这些只是
numbers underneath the hood back to back to back combined
引擎盖下的数字，背靠背地组合起来
with the idea of an array from earlier, we can
与之前数组的概念结合起来，我们可以
start to see what's really going on.
开始看到真正发生了什么。
Because indeed, underneath the hood, this is just a number, 72, 73, 33.
因为实际上，在引擎盖下，这只是一个数字，72、73、33。
And really, if we go lower level than that,
实际上，如果我们比这更低一层，
it's these three patterns of 0's and 1's.
它就是这三个 0 和 1 的模式。
That's all that's going on inside of the computer,
这就是计算机内部发生的事情，
but it's our use of int that shows it to us as an integer.
但我们使用 int 使它显示为整数。
It's our use of char that makes it clear that it's a char, or equivalently,
我们使用 char 使它清楚地显示它是字符，或者等效地，
%i and %c respectively.
分别为 %i 和 %c。
But what exactly is a string?
但字符串到底是什么？
Well, it's really just a sequence of characters,
嗯，它实际上只是一系列字符，
and so why don't we go there?
所以我们为什么不去那里呢？
Let me propose that we actually give ourselves an actual string,
我建议我们给自己一个真正的字符串，
call it s-- we'll use double quotes this time.
称之为 s-- 这次我们将使用双引号。
So if I go back to VS Code here, let me shorten this program
所以，如果我回到 VS Code，让我缩短这个程序
and just give myself a single string s, set it equal to "HI!"
只给自己一个字符串 s，将其设置为“HI！”
in double quotes.
用双引号。
And then below that, let's go ahead and print out %s, backslash n,
然后在它下面，让我们继续打印出 %s、反斜杠 n，
and then s itself.
然后是 s 本身。
And then, turns out, for reasons we'll soon
然后，事实证明，由于我们很快就会看到的
see, I do need to include the CS50 Library so as
原因，我需要包含 CS50 库，以便
to use the actual keyword string here even though I'm not using get_string,
在这里使用实际的关键字字符串，即使我没有使用 get_string，
but more on that another time.
但我们会在另一个时间讨论这个问题。
But if I now do make hi, it does compile ./hi and it still prints out the exact
但如果我现在执行 make hi，它确实编译了 ./hi，并且仍然打印出完全相同的
same thing.
东西。
But what's going on inside of the computer's memory
但是，当我使用一个名为 s 的字符串而不是三个字符时，计算机内存中发生了什么？
when I use a string called s instead of three chars, well,
嗯，你可以把字符串看作至少占用了三个字节，H、
you can think of the string as taking up at least three bytes, H,
I、感叹号。
I, exclamation point.
但它不是三个单独的变量，它是一个变量。
But it's not three separate variables, it's one variable.
但现在这到底是什么样子，尤其是
But what does this really look like now, especially
如果我添加回黄色线条？
if I add back the yellow lines?
s is really just an array of characters.
字符串实际上就是一个字符数组。
So we called it a string last week, and I claim today
上周我们把它称为字符串，而今天我声称
that this is an abstraction in the CS50 library that's giving us this string,
这是 CS50 库中提供的抽象，它给了我们这个字符串，
but it's really just an array of size at least 3
但实际上它只是一个至少包含 3 个元素的数组
here where s, bracket, 0 presumably gives me the H, s, bracket,
在这里，s 方括号 0 应该会给我 H，s 方括号
1 is the I, s, bracket, 2 is the exclamation point.
1 是 I，s 方括号 2 是感叹号。
But just by saying string, all of that happens automatically.
但只要说字符串，所有这些都会自动发生。
I don't even need to tell the computer how many chars are
我甚至不需要告诉计算机有多少个字符
going to be in this string all at once.
会同时出现在这个字符串中。
So in fact, let me go over to maybe a variant of this program
事实上，让我去看看这个程序的变体
and we can see this syntactically.
我们可以从语法上看到这一点。
So instead of printing out the whole string with %s,
所以，与其用 %s 打印出整个字符串，
let me actually be a little curious and print out %c, %c, %c,
让我有点好奇，打印出 %c, %c, %c，
and then change s to s, bracket, 0, s, bracket, 1, s, bracket, 2.
然后将 s 更改为 s 方括号 0，s 方括号 1，s 方括号 2。
Which is not better in any sense.
这在任何意义上都不更好。
This is way more tedious now, but it does
现在这太繁琐了，但它确实
demonstrate that I can treat here in week 2
证明了我可以在第二周将它
as though it's an array, which means even in week 1 it was an array,
当做数组，这意味着即使在第一周它也是数组，
we just didn't know it.
我们只是不知道。
We didn't have the syntax with which to express that.
我们没有语法来表达这一点。
So if I now do make hi, still compiles ./hi.
所以如果我现在执行 make hi，它仍然可以编译 ./hi。
Same exact output, but I'm now just kind of manipulating
输出完全相同，但我现在只是在操纵
the string in these different ways because I
字符串以不同的方式，因为我
a string is just an array of characters, so I can
字符串只是一个字符数组，所以我可以
treat with the square bracket notation.
用方括号表示法处理。
But how do I know-- how does the computer know where hi ends?
但是我如何知道，计算机如何知道 hi 在哪里结束？
And this is where strings get a little dangerous.
这就是字符串变得有点危险的地方。
Like a char is 1 byte no matter what.
就像一个 char 无论如何都是 1 个字节。
1 char, 1 character, that's it.
1 个 char，1 个字符，就是这样。
But a string, recall my question mark from earlier,
但一个字符串，还记得我之前问的？
could be null bytes if it's--
如果它是空字节，那么它
you would think could be 0 bytes if you have nothing in it inside the quotes.
你可能认为它可以是 0 字节，如果你在引号里什么都没有。
It could be one character, two, 10, 100 like I claimed,
它可以是一个字符，两个，十个，一百个，就像我之前所说的，
but how does the computer know where strings end?
但计算机如何知道字符串在哪里结束？
Like how does the computer not know that the string is not
就像计算机如何不知道字符串不是
the whole row of memory here?
这里一整行的内存？
How does it know that it ends here?
它怎么知道它在这里结束？
Well, it turns out, all this time, when we've been using, quote-unquote,
事实证明，一直以来，当我们使用所谓的
string and using get_string from the CS50 library,
字符串和使用 CS50 库中的 get_string 时，
there's actually a special sentinel value
实际上有一个特殊的哨兵值
at the end of every string in a computer's memory
在计算机内存中每个字符串的末尾
that tells the computer string, stops here.
告诉计算机字符串在这里停止。
And the sentinel value-- and by sentinel, I
哨兵值，而哨兵的意思是
just mean special value that the world decided on decades ago, is all 0 bits.
几十年前全世界决定好的特殊值，都是 0 位。
If you have a byte with all 0 bits in it, that means string ends here.
如果你有一个字节，其中所有位都是 0，这意味着字符串在这里结束。
So the implication is that the computer now, using a loop or something,
因此，这意味着计算机现在，使用循环或其他东西，
can print out char, char, char-- oh, done,
可以打印出 char，char，char，哦，完成了，
because it sees this special value.
因为它看到了这个特殊值。
If it didn't have that, it might blindly go char, char, char, char char--
如果没有它，它可能会盲目地继续 char，char，char，char char，
printing out values of memory that don't belong to that given string.
打印出不属于给定字符串的内存值。
So I was correcting myself verbally a moment ago
所以，我之前在口头上纠正了自己
because I said that this string is of length 3, it's 3 bytes, but it's not.
因为我说这个字符串的长度是 3，它是 3 个字节，但它不是。
Every string in the world, both last week and now, this
世界上所有的字符串，无论是在上周还是现在，这个
is actually n plus 1 bytes where n is the actual human length
实际上是 n 加 1 个字节，其中 n 是实际的人类长度
that you care about, H-I, exclamation point, or 3,
你关心的，H-I，感叹号，或者 3，
but it's always going to use one extra byte for this so-called zero value
但它总是会为这个所谓的零值使用一个额外的字节
at the end.
在末尾。
And this 0 value is very tedious to write a 0--
而这个 0 值用 0 来写很繁琐，
as 8 0 bits.
用 8 个 0 位来写。
So we would actually typically just write it as a 0.
所以我们实际上通常只是把它写成 0。
But you don't want to confuse a 0 on the screen-- it's actually being
但你不想将屏幕上的 0 与它混淆，它实际上是
like the number 0 on the keyboard.
像键盘上的数字 0。
And so we would actually typically write this symbol with a backslash 0.
所以，我们实际上通常用反斜杠 0 来写这个符号。
So this is the char-based representation of 0.
所以，这是 0 的基于字符的表示。
So it means the exact same thing, this is just
所以，它的意思完全一样，这只是
C notation that indicates that this is 8 0 bits,
C 语言中的表示法，表明这是 8 个 0 位，
but just makes clear that it's not literally the number
但它只是表明它不是字面上的数字
0 that you want to see on the screen, it's a sentinel value
0，你想要在屏幕上看到，它是一个哨兵值
that is terminating this here string.
它终止了这里的字符串。
So now what can I do once I know this information?
那么，现在我知道了这些信息之后，我能做什么呢？
Well, I can actually even see this let me go back to this code
好吧，我实际上甚至可以看看它，让我回到这段代码
here in VS Code.
在 VS Code 中。
Let me change these %c's to %i's just like before.
让我像之前一样将这些 %c 更改为 %i。
And now, we'll see again those same numbers, make hi, ./hi,
现在，我们将再次看到相同的数字，make hi，./hi，
there are the three.
那里有三个。
I can technically poke around a little bit further, %i one more,
从技术上来说，我可以再深入一点，%i 再加一个，
and let's look at s, bracket, 3.
让我们看看 s 方括号 3。
I was not exaggerating earlier when I said,
我之前说的时候没有夸张，
in general, if you go past the end of an array, bad things can happen.
一般来说，如果你越过数组的末尾，可能会发生不好的事情。
But in this case, I know that there is one more thing at the end of this array
但在这种情况下，我知道这个数组的末尾还有一个东西
because this is how strings are built. This is not a CS50 thing,
因为字符串就是这样构建的。这不是 CS50 的东西，
this is a thing in C. Every string in the world in double quotes
这是 C 语言中的东西。世界上每个用双引号表示的字符串
ends with a backslash 0-- that is 8 0 bits.
都以反斜杠 0 结尾，即 8 个 0 位。
So if I really want, I can see this by printing out s, bracket, 3,
所以，如果我真的想，我可以通过打印 s 方括号 3 来看到这一点，
which is the fourth and final location.
它是第四个也是最后一个位置。
If I recompile my code now, make hi ./hi, I should see 72, 73, 33, and 0.
如果我现在重新编译我的代码，make hi ./hi，我应该看到 72、73、33 和 0。
That's always been there.
它一直都在那里。
So I'm always using 4 bytes, somewhat wastefully, but somewhat necessarily
所以，我总是使用 4 个字节，有点浪费，但也有必要
so that the computer actually knows where that string ends.
这样计算机才能知道字符串在哪里结束。
So if we go back to the memory representation of this here,
所以，如果我们回到这里的内存表示，
it's just as though you have an array of integers being stored contiguously back
它就像你有一个整数数组，连续地存储在后面
to back to back, the last one of which means this is the end of the array
从头到尾，最后一个意味着数组的结束
of characters, but because I'm using, quote-unquote, "string,"
字符的数组，但因为我使用了“字符串”，
because I'm using %s and %c, I'm not seeing these numbers by default,
因为我使用 %s 和 %c，所以我默认情况下看不到这些数字，
I'm seeing H-I, exclamation point unless I explicitly tell printf, no, no, no,
我看到的是H-I，感叹号，除非我明确地告诉printf，不，不，不，
no, show me with %i these actual integers.
不，用 %i 显示这些实际的整数。
This, then, is how you can think about the string.
那么，这就是你可以思考字符串的方式。
Like you don't really need to think about
就像你真的不需要思考
it as being individual characters.
它是一个个的字符。
This is just s, and it has some length here,
这只是 s，它在这里有一定的长度，
but it does not necessarily an array that you yourself have to create,
但它不一定是你自己必须创建的数组，
you get it automatically just by using a string.
你只要使用一个字符串就可以自动获得它。
Now there's just-- not to add on to the jargon.
现在，只是 - 不想加更多术语。
This backslash 0, these 8 0 bits, there's
这个反斜杠 0，这 8 个 0 位，有
actually a technical term for them.
实际上有一个技术术语来称呼它们。
You can call them NUL.
你可以称它们为 NUL。
It's typically written in all caps like this, confusingly.
它通常像这样写成全大写，让人困惑。
In a couple of weeks, we're going to see another word pronounced null,
几周后，我们将看到另一个发音为 null 的词，
but spelled N-U-L-L. Left hand wasn't talking to right hand years ago,
但拼写为 N-U-L-L。几年前，左手没有和右手交流，
but N-U-L means this is the 0 byte that terminates strings,
但 N-U-L 意味着这是终止字符串的 0 字节，
that indicate the end of a string.
指示字符串的结束。
And fun fact, you've actually seen this before even though we glossed over it.
有趣的事实是，你实际上之前已经见过它了，即使我们一带而过。
Here's that ASCII chart from last time.
这是上次的 ASCII 表。
If I focus on the leftmost column, guess what is the 0 ASCII character?
如果我关注最左边的列，猜猜 0 ASCII 字符是什么？
NUL.
NUL。
You never see null on the screen, it's just how you pronounce 8 0 bits.
你永远不会在屏幕上看到 null，它只是你如何发音 8 个 0 位。
Whew!
呼！
questions on this representation of strings?
关于这种字符串表示方式有什么问题吗？
Yeah?
有吗？
AUDIENCE: Are strings [INAUDIBLE]?
观众：字符串 [听不清]？
DAVID MALAN: Are string structured differently in other languages?
大卫·马兰：字符串在其他语言中结构不同吗？
Yes.
是的。
They are more powerful in other languages.
它们在其他语言中功能更强大。
In C, you have to build them yourself in this way.
在 C 语言中，你必须以这种方式自己构建它们。
More on that when we get to Python.
我们将在学习 Python 时进一步讨论。
Other questions.
其他问题。
Yeah?
有吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
大卫·马兰：一个非常好的问题。
Does that mean we don't have a function to get the length of a string?
这意味着我们没有获取字符串长度的函数吗？
Do we have to create it?
我们必须自己创建它吗？
Short answer, there is a function, but you have to-- someone
简短的回答，有一个函数，但你必须 - 有人
had to write code for it.
必须为它编写代码。
You can't just ask the string itself like you can in JavaScript or Java.
你不能像在 JavaScript 或 Java 中那样直接询问字符串本身。
What is the--
是什么 -
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, you can.
大卫·马兰：是的，你可以。
It's actually more similar to Python than it is to JavaScript or Java,
它实际上更类似于 Python，而不是 JavaScript 或 Java，
but we'll see that in just a few minutes, in fact.
但事实上，我们将在几分钟内看到这一点。
So let's introduce maybe a couple of strings.
所以让我们介绍几个字符串。
So here's two strings in the abstract called s and t,
所以这里有两个抽象的字符串，分别叫 s 和 t，
and I've initialized them arbitrarily to "HI!" and "BYE!"
我将它们任意初始化为“HI！”和“BYE！”
just so we can explore what's going to actually happen underneath the hood.
这样我们就可以探索幕后实际上会发生什么。
So let me go back to VS Code.
所以让我回到 VS Code。
Let me just completely change this program to be that instead.
让我完全改变这个程序，改为那样。
So string equals, quote-unquote, "HI!"
所以 string 等于，引号，"HI！"
String t equals, quote-unquote, "BYE!"
String t 等于，引号，"BYE！"
in all caps.
全部大写。
And then let's print them both out very simply. %s backslash n, s.
然后让我们简单地把它们都打印出来。%s 反斜杠 n，s。
Print out %s backslash n, t just so we can see what's going on.
打印出 %s 反斜杠 n，t，这样我们就可以看到发生了什么。
If I do make hi ./hi, I should, of course, see these two strings.
如果我执行 make hi ./hi，我当然应该看到这两个字符串。
But what's going on inside of the computer's memory?
但是计算机内存内部发生了什么？
Well, in this computer's memory, assuming
好吧，在这台计算机的内存中，假设
these are the only two variables involved and assuming the computer
这两个是唯一涉及的变量，并且假设计算机
is just doing things top to bottom, "HI!"
只是从上到下执行，“HI！”
is probably going to be stored somewhere like this on my canvas of memory,
可能会被存储在我的内存画布上的某个地方，
"BYE!"
"BYE！"
is probably going to be stored there.
可能会被存储在那里。
And it's wrapping around, but that's just an artist's representation.
它正在循环，但这只是艺术家的表示方式。
But notice that it is now really important
但请注意，现在非常重要
that there is this NUL byte at the end of each string
在每个字符串的末尾都有这个 NUL 字节
because that's how the computer is going to know where "HI!"
因为这是计算机如何知道 "HI！"
ends and where "BYE!"
结束，以及 "BYE！"
begins, otherwise you might see "HI!"
开始，否则你可能会看到 "HI！"
"BYE!"
"BYE！"
all on the screen at once if there weren't the sentinel value indicating
全部同时出现在屏幕上，如果没有这个哨兵值指示
to printf, stop at this character.
告诉 printf，在此字符处停止。
But that's all that's going on in your program
但这就是你的程序中发生的一切
when you have two variables in this way.
当你以这种方式拥有两个变量时。
And in fact, what's really going on and things get a little more interesting
事实上，真正发生的事情，事情变得更加有趣
here, if I were to want two of these things,
在这里，如果我想要两个这样的东西，
notice that I could refer to them two as arrays.
请注意，我可以将它们两个称为数组。
So s, bracket, 0, 1, 2, and even 3.
所以 s，方括号，0，1，2，甚至 3。
t, bracket, 0, 1, 2, and even 3 and 4.
t，方括号，0，1，2，甚至 3 和 4。
But if I want to actually really blend some ideas,
但是如果我想真正混合一些想法，
just playing around with these basic principles now,
现在只是玩玩这些基本原则，
notice what I can do in this version.
注意在这个版本中我可以做什么。
If I know I've got two arrays in VS Code,
如果我知道我在 VS Code 中有两个数组，
I don't strictly need to do string s and t and u
我不需要严格地使用 string s 和 t 和 u
and v. That's devolving back into the scores1, scores2, scores3 mantra where
和 v。这又回到了 scores1、scores2、scores3 的模式，在那里
I had multiple variables almost the same name
我有几个变量几乎相同的名字
even though I'm using different letters of the alphabet.
即使我使用不同的字母。
What if I want--
如果我想 -
what if I do this?
如果我这样做？
string words, and if I want to store two words in the computer's memory, fine.
string words，如果我想在计算机内存中存储两个单词，没问题。
Create an array of two strings.
创建一个包含两个字符串的数组。
But what is a string?
但什么是字符串？
A string is an array of characters, so it's getting a little bit trippy here,
字符串是字符数组，所以这里有点奇怪，
but the ideas are still going to be the same. words, bracket,
但想法仍然是一样的。words，方括号，
0 could certainly equal "HI!"
0 当然可以等于“HI！”
words, bracket, 1 can certainly equal "BYE!" just like the scores example.
words，括号，1 当然可以等于“BYE！”，就像分数示例一样。
And then if I want to print these things with %s, I can print out words,
然后，如果我想用 %s 打印这些东西，我可以打印出 words，
bracket, 0.
括号，0。
And then I can print out %s backslash n words bracket 1.
然后我可以打印出 %s 反斜杠 n words 括号 1。
And the example is not going to be any different in terms of its output,
并且这个例子在输出方面不会有任何不同，
but I've now avoided s and t, I now just have one variable called words
但是我现在避免了 s 和 t，我现在只有一个名为 words 的变量
containing both of these here things.
包含这两者。
And if I really want to poke around, here's
如果我真的想四处探查，这里就是
where things get even more visually overwhelming,
事情变得更加直观地让人不知所措的地方，
but just the logical extension of these same ideas.
但只是这些相同想法的逻辑扩展。
Right now is the previous version where I had two variables, s and t.
现在是之前我使用两个变量 s 和 t 的版本。
If I now use this new version where I have one variable called words,
如果我现在使用这个新的版本，我有一个名为 words 的变量，
just like this here, the picture should follow logically like this.
就像这样，图片应该逻辑上像这样。
words, bracket, 0 is this string; words, bracket, 1 is this string;
words，括号，0 是这个字符串；words，括号，1 是这个字符串；
but what is each string?
但是每个字符串是什么？
It's an array of characters.
它是一个字符数组。
And so you can also think of it like this, where this H is words, bracket,
所以你也可以这样想，这里这个 H 是 words，括号，
0, bracket, 0.
0，括号，0。
So the 0-th character of the 0-th word.
所以是第 0 个单词的第 0 个字符。
And this is words, bracket, 0, 1; words, bracket, 0, 2; words, bracket, 0, 3.
而这是 words，括号，0，1；words，括号，0，2；words，括号，0，3。
And then words, bracket, 1, 0.
然后是 words，括号，1，0。
So it's kind of like a two-dimensional array, almost.
所以它几乎就像一个二维数组。
And you can think about it that way if helpful.
如果你觉得有用，可以这样想。
But for now, it's just applying the same principles to the code.
但现在，它只是将相同的原则应用于代码。
So if I go to my code here and I've got my "HI!" and my "BYE!"--
所以如果我到我的代码这里，我有了我的“HI！”和我的“BYE！”--
this is going to look a little stupid, but let me change this %s to %c, %c,
这看起来有点愚蠢，但让我把这个 %s 变成 %c，%c，
%c, and print out words, bracket, 0.
%c，然后打印出 words，括号，0。
words, bracket, 0, bracket 1.
words，括号，0，括号 1。
words, bracket, 0, bracket, 2 to print out that three-letter word.
words，括号，0，括号，2，用来打印出那个三个字母的单词。
And now down here, let me print out %c, %c, %c,
现在这里，让我打印出 %c，%c，%c，
%c because it's four letters in BYE, exclamation point.
%c，因为 BYE 有四个字母，感叹号。
This is words, bracket, 1, but the first character; words, bracket, 1,
这是 words，括号，1，但第一个字符；words，括号，1，
the second character; words, bracket, 1, the third character;
第二个字符；words，括号，1，第三个字符；
and words, bracket, 1, the fourth character.
以及 words，括号，1，第四个字符。
It's hard to say when you're typing a different number,
当你输入一个不同的数字时很难说，
but that's what we get by using zero indexing, so to speak.
但这就是我们使用零索引的方式，可以这么说。
make hi.
make hi。
Whew!
哇！
No mistakes.
没有错误。
"HI!"
“HI！”
Says the same thing.
说的是同一件事。
So again, there's no magic.
所以，再一次，这里没有魔法。
Like you are fully in control over what's going
就像你完全控制着发生的事情
on inside of the computer's memory.
在计算机的内存里。
And now that we have this array syntax with square brackets,
现在我们有了这个带方括号的数组语法，
you can both create these things and then manipulate them or access them
你既可以创建这些东西，然后操纵它们或访问它们
however you so choose.
随你喜欢。
Whew!
哇！
Questions on arrays or strings in this way?
关于数组或字符串，有疑问吗？
Yeah, over here.
是啊，这边。
AUDIENCE: Can you have any array that has multiple data types in it?
观众：你可以有一个包含多种数据类型的数组吗？
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
大卫·马兰：好问题。
Can you have an array with multiple different data types?
你可以有一个包含多种数据类型的数组吗？
Short answer, no; longer answer, sort of,
简短的回答，不行；更长的回答，算是吧，
but not in nearly the same user-friendly way as with languages
但不像 Python 或 JavaScript 或其他语言那样友好。
like Python or JavaScript or others.
比如 Python 或 JavaScript 等等。
So assume for now arrays should be the same type in C. Other questions?
所以现在假设 C 中的数组应该都是同一类型。还有其他问题吗？
Yeah, over here.
是啊，这边。
AUDIENCE: When you talk about [INAUDIBLE]??
观众：当你谈论 [听不清] ??
DAVID MALAN: Oh, a really good question.
大卫·马兰：哦，一个非常好的问题。
It will-- so for those who couldn't hear,
它会——对于那些没听清的人，
if you were to look past the end of one array,
如果你要看一个数组的末尾之后，
would you start to see the beginning of the second?
你会开始看到第二个数组的开头吗？
In this case, maybe the word "BYE!"
在这种情况下，可能是“BYE！”这个词。
Could depend on the particulars of your code in the computer.
这可能取决于你计算机代码的具体情况。
Let's try this.
让我们试试这个。
So let's get a little greedy here and go one past H-I, exclamation point,
所以让我们贪心一点，从 H-I，感叹号，之后的一个位置开始，
null character by looking at words, bracket, 0, 3,
空字符，通过查看 words，括号，0，3，
which should actually be our null character, so that's going to be there.
这实际上应该是我们的空字符，所以它会出现在那里。
And actually, let's see.
实际上，让我们看看。
Let's go ahead and do this.
让我们来做这个。
Make hi ./hi.
Make hi ./hi。
Still works as expected, but let me change this to integer,
仍然按预期工作，但让我把它改为整数，
integer so we can actually see what's going on.
整数，这样我们就可以看到发生了什么。
Integer.
整数。
And now, if I recompile make hi, I should see the same thing,
现在，如果我重新编译 make hi，我应该看到相同的结果，
but numerically.
但以数字形式。
And now what I think you're proposing is let's get a little crazy
现在我认为你正在提议的是，让我们疯狂一点
and go even past that to what could be location 4,
并且超越它，到达可能是位置 4 的地方，
but we know semantically doesn't exist, but maybe is bumping up against "BYE!"
但我们知道从语义上来说它不存在，但它可能会碰到“BYE！”。
So make hi ./hi.
所以 make hi ./hi。
And guess what 66 is.
猜猜 66 是什么。
Well, just the B, but yes.
嗯，只是 B，但没错。
66, recall, is capital B because in week 0, capital A was 65.
记住，66 是大写 B，因为在第 0 周，大写 A 是 65。
So indeed, now we're really poking around.
所以，现在我们真的在四处探查了。
And you can get crazy.
你可以变得很疯狂。
Like, what's 400 characters away and see what's going on there.
比如，看看 400 个字符之外是什么，看看那里发生了什么。
Eventually your program will probably crash,
最终你的程序可能会崩溃，
and so don't poke around too much, but more on that in the coming days, too.
所以不要探查太多，但我们将在接下来的几天里详细讨论这个问题。
All right, well how about some other revelations and problem-solving?
好的，那么其他的一些启示和问题解决呢？
Now coming back to the question about strings length earlier,
现在回到之前关于字符串长度的问题，
and we'll see if we can then tie this all together to something
我们来看看是否可以把这些东西都联系起来，形成一个
like cryptography in the end and manipulating strings
最终像密码学一样，操纵字符串
for the purpose of sending them securely.
以安全地发送它们为目的。
So let me propose that we go into VS Code here again in a moment.
所以，我建议我们一会儿再次进入 VS Code。
And I'm going to create a program called length.
我将创建一个名为 length 的程序。
Let's actually figure out ourselves the length of a string initially.
让我们自己来算算字符串的长度。
So I'm going to go ahead and code length.c.
所以我要开始编写length.c代码。
I'm going to go ahead and include cs50.h.
我要包含cs50.h头文件。
I'm going to include stdio.h, int main void.
我要包含stdio.h头文件，定义主函数。
And then inside of main, I'm going to prompt the user for their name.
然后在主函数中，我将提示用户输入姓名。
get_string, quote-unquote, "Name."
使用get_string函数获取输入，并提示用户输入“姓名”。
And then I'm going to go ahead and I want
然后我要开始
to count the length of this string.
计算这个字符串的长度。
But I know what a string is now.
但现在我知道字符串是什么了。
It's char, char, char, char, and then eventually the null character.
它由一个一个字符组成，最终以一个空字符结尾。
So I can look for that.
所以我可以查找空字符。
And I can write this in a few different ways.
我可以使用多种方法来编写代码。
I know a bunch of different types of loops now,
我现在知道很多种循环类型，
but I'm going to go with a while loop by first declaring a variable n,
但我要使用while循环，首先定义一个名为n的变量，
for number of characters, set it equal to 0.
用于存储字符数量，并将其初始化为0。
It's like starting to count with your fingers all down,
就像从零开始用手指计数，
and I want to do the equivalent of this, counting each of the letters
我要做同样的事情，统计每个字母的数量
that I type in.
我输入的每个字符。
So I can do that as follows.
我可以按如下方式实现。
While the name variable at location n does not equal,
当name变量中第n个位置的值不等于
quote-unquote, backslash 0, which looks weird,
空字符（用反斜杠0表示），看起来很奇怪，
but it's just asking the question, is the character
但这只是在问，该位置的字符
at that location equal to the so-called null character?
是否等于空字符？
Which is written with single quotes and backslash 0 by convention.
根据惯例，空字符用单引号和反斜杠0表示。
And what I want to do, while that is true, is just add 1 to n.
当条件为真时，我要做的就是将n加1。
And then at the very bottom here, let's just go ahead and print out with %i
然后在最后，我们使用%i打印
the value of n because presumably if I type in HI, exclamation point,
n的值，因为假设我输入的是HI，感叹号，
I'm starting at 0 and I'm going to have H, I, exclamation point,
我从0开始，然后会有H，I，感叹号，
null character so I don't increment n a fourth time.
空字符，所以我不会第四次增加n。
So let's go ahead and run down here.
让我们运行这段代码。
make length ./length, Enter.
输入make length ./length，然后回车。
Well, I guess I'm asking for name, so I'll do my name for real.
嗯，它要求我输入姓名，所以我就输入我的真实姓名。
David, five characters, and I indeed get 5.
David，有五个字符，我确实得到了5。
If I used a for loop, I could do something similar,
如果我使用for循环，我可以做类似的事情，
but I think this while loop approach, much like our counter from the past,
但我认为这种while循环方法，就像我们之前使用的计数器一样，
is fairly straightforward.
非常直观。
But what if I want to do this?
但如果我想这样做呢？
What if I want to make another function for this?
如果我想为此创建一个新函数？
Well, I could do that.
当然可以。
Let me--
让我
All right, let's do this.
好的，我们来试试。
Let's write a quick function called string_length.
让我们编写一个名为string_length的简短函数。
It's going to take a string called s or whatever as input.
它将接收一个名为s的字符串作为输入。
And then you know what?
然后你知道吗？
Let's just do this in that function.
让我们直接在这个函数中实现它。
I'm going to borrow my code from a moment ago.
我要从刚才的代码中借用一些代码。
I'm going to paste it into this function.
我要将代码粘贴到这个函数中。
But I'm not going to print out the length,
但我不会打印出长度，
I'm going to return the length n.
我会返回长度n。
So I have a helper function of sorts that's
所以，我创建了一个辅助函数，它
going to hand me back the length of the string,
将返回字符串的长度，
and that's why this returns an int, but takes a string as its argument.
因此它返回一个整数类型的值，但接收一个字符串作为参数。
How do I use this?
我该如何使用它呢？
Well, first, I do need to copy the prototype
首先，我需要复制函数原型
so I don't get into trouble as before.
以避免出现之前的问题。
Semicolon.
加上分号。
And then in my main function, what I think I can do now
然后在我的主函数中，我认为现在我可以
is something like this.
这样做。
I can do int length equals the string length of the name variable
我可以定义一个名为length的整数变量，并将其赋值为name变量的字符串长度
that was just typed in.
刚刚输入的姓名。
And now using printf %i, print out length, semicolon.
现在使用printf %i打印出length的值，加上分号。
So exact same logic.
所以逻辑完全相同。
The only thing I've done that's different this time is I've
这次我做的唯一不同的是，我
added a helper function just to demonstrate
添加了一个辅助函数，只是为了演示
how I can take some pretty basic functionality,
如何将一些非常基本的功能，
find the length of a string, and modularize it
找到字符串的长度，并将其模块化
into a function abstract it away so I never again have
封装成一个函数，将其抽象化，这样我就不再需要
to copy-paste that for loop.
复制粘贴那个for循环。
I now have a function called string_length
我现在有一个名为string_length的函数
that will solve this problem for me.
可以解决这个问题。
Whoops, wrong program. make length.
哎哟，程序错了，应该是make length。
Huh.
嗯？
Use of undeclared identifier 'name.'
使用未声明的标识符“name”。
What did I do wrong?
我做错了什么？
Apparently on line 16 of length.c, what did I do wrong here?
显然是在length.c的第16行，这里我做错了什么？
Yeah, in front.
是的，前面。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Good.
大卫·马兰：很好。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Good.
大卫·马兰：很好。
Perfect terminology.
完美的术语。
So name is local to main.
所以name只在main函数中可见。
The scope of name is main, though sounds similar, but different words.
name的作用域是main，虽然听起来相似，但却是不同的词语。
And so I'm actually should be calling this
所以，我实际上应该调用
s because s is the name of the local variable being passed in even though it
s，因为s是传入的局部变量的名称，即使它
happens to be 1 and the same as name because on line 9,
碰巧与name相同，因为在第9行，
I'm indeed passing in name as the argument.
我确实将name作为参数传入。
All right.
好的。
So this is where, again, copy-paste can sometimes get you into trouble.
所以，这里再次说明，复制粘贴有时会导致问题。
Let's try to make length again.
让我们再次尝试make length。
Now it works. ./length, D-A-V-I-D, and now we have a function that seems to be
现在它可以正常运行了。输入./length，然后输入D-A-V-I-D，现在我们有一个看起来正常的函数。
working.
工作。
But this is such like commodity functionality.
但这就像一种商品功能。
Like my God, like surely someone before us
我的天哪，肯定有人在我们之前
has written a function to get the length of a string before,
写过一个函数来获取字符串的长度，
and indeed, other people have.
确实如此，其他人也写过。
So it turns out that in C, just as you have the stdio library,
事实证明，在C语言中，就像你拥有stdio库一样，
you also have a string library whose header file is called, appropriately,
你也有一个字符串库，它的头文件被称为string.h，非常贴切。
string.h.
string.h。
In fact CS50 has documentation, therefore, in its own manual pages,
实际上，CS50 在其自己的手册页面中提供了文档，
so to speak, along with some sample usage thereof.
可以這麼說，還有一些示例用法。
But it turns out, in the string library, there
但事實證明，在字符串庫中，
is a very popular function analogous to the Python one
有一個非常流行的函數，類似於 Python 中的函數
that you asked about earlier called strlen
你之前問的叫做 strlen
where strlen, one word, no underscores, just
strlen，一個單詞，沒有下劃線，
figures out the length of a string.
計算字符串的長度。
And honestly, I've never looked at its source code,
老實說，我從未看過它的源代碼，
but it probably uses a while loop, maybe it uses a for loop,
但它可能使用了 while 循環，也許使用了 for 循環，
but it certainly uses the same idea of just iterating-- that is,
但它肯定使用了相同的迭代思想——也就是說，
walking from left to right over a variable
從左到右遍歷一個變量
in order to figure out what the length of a given string is.
以便找出給定字符串的長度。
So how do we use this?
那麼我們如何使用它呢？
Well if I go back to VS Code here, I can throw away
好吧，如果我回到 VS Code，我可以丟棄
the entirety of my string length function,
我的字符串長度函數的全部內容，
I can throw away the prototype, therefore,
因此，我可以丟棄原型，
and I can include a third header file, string.h, inside
我可以在裡面添加第三個頭文件 string.h
of which I claim now is this function called strlen
我現在聲稱這個函數叫做 strlen
that I can just now use out of the box for free
我現在就可以免費使用它
because someone else wrote this function for me.
因為其他人為我編寫了這個函數。
And string.h will teach the compiler that it exists.
而 string.h 將告訴編譯器它存在。
So if I now do make length and ./length, now I have a similarly working program
所以，如果我現在運行 make length 和 ./length，我現在有一個類似工作的程序
that doesn't bother having me write unnecessary code.
它不必讓我寫不必要的代碼。
So this is another example of a library.
所以這是另一個庫的例子。
The string library is just going to make our lives easier by not having to--
字符串庫只會讓我們的編程更輕鬆，而無需——
for us not having to reinvent some wheel.
讓我們不必重新發明輪子。
All right, well where else does this get interesting?
好吧，還有哪裡有趣呢？
How about something like this?
比如這樣？
Let me go back into VS Code here.
讓我回到 VS Code 中。
Let's create a program called string.c--
讓我們創建一個叫做 string.c 的程序——
we'll play around with our own strings-- that's going to start similarly.
我們將使用自己的字符串——開始方式類似。
So let's include cs50.h, let's include stdio.h,
所以讓我們包含 cs50.h，讓我們包含 stdio.h，
let's include string.h so we can use that same strlen function.
讓我們包含 string.h，以便我們可以使用相同的 strlen 函數。
int main void.
And inside of this, let's do this.
在這裡面，讓我們做這個。
Let's get a string s and prompt the user for any old string as input.
讓我們獲取一個字符串 s 並提示用戶輸入任意字符串。
All right.
好的。
And then let's go ahead and maybe print out, quote-unquote, "Output."
然後，讓我們繼續打印，引號中的 “輸出”。
And I'm just going to line up my spaces just right because these words are
我將把我的空格對齊，因為這些單詞
slightly different lengths, but we'll see why I'm doing this.
長度略有不同，但我們會看到我為什麼這樣做。
It's just for aesthetics' sake in a moment.
這只是為了美觀。
And let's go ahead now and do this.
現在讓我們繼續做這個。
If I want to print out every character in a string, how can I now do this?
如果我想打印出字符串中的每個字符，我現在如何做到呢？
Well, this is actually a pretty common task
好吧，這其實是一個很常見的任務
even though this version, thereof, will seem pointless. for int i gets 0,
即使這個版本看起來毫無意義。for int i 獲取 0，
i is less than the length of s.
i 小於 s 的長度。
i++ is just the conventional way to start a loop that iterates from left
i++ 只是開始從左到右迭代循環的傳統方式
to right over a string of that length.
到那個長度的字符串。
And then let's go ahead and print out each character, %c,
然後，讓我們繼續打印出每個字符，%c，
printing out the string at location i using our fancy new array syntax.
使用我們新奇的數組語法打印出位於 i 位置的字符串。
And at the very end of this program, let's just
在這個程序的最後，讓我們
print out a new line character just to move the cursor to the bottom
打印一個換行符，以將光標移動到底部
like we've done in the past.
就像我們過去所做的那樣。
So this is kind of a stupid program like I am reinventing the wheel that is
所以，這個程序有點愚蠢，就像我在重新發明輪子一樣
the %s format code.
%s 格式代碼。
I already know that printf can print out a whole string.
我已經知道 printf 可以打印出整個字符串。
Suppose it didn't.
假設它不能。
Suppose I forgot about %s and I only knew about %c,
假設我忘記了 %s，我只知道 %c，
these lines of code here collectively will print out the entirety of a string
這裡的這些代碼將共同打印出整個字符串
character by character based on its length.
基於它的長度，逐個字符地打印。
So if I compile this program, make string ./string and type in my name--
所以，如果我編譯這個程序，運行 make string ./string 並輸入我的名字——
for instance, David, the output is D-A-V-I-D,
比如，David，輸出是 D-A-V-I-D，
and here's why I hit the spacebar an extra time,
這是為什麼我多按了一下空格鍵，
because I wanted input and output to line up nicely so we could see that
因為我希望輸入和輸出整齊地對齊，以便我們可以看到
they're, in fact, the same length.
它們事實上是相同的長度。
So let me just stipulate.
所以讓我簡單說明一下。
This code is correct, but there is an inefficiency with this line of code.
這個代碼是正確的，但這行代碼存在一個低效的地方。
Let's talk about design instinctively.
讓我們本能地談談設計。
What is maybe bad about this line of code 9--
這行代碼 9 有什麼不好——
line 9 that I've highlighted?
我已經突出顯示的第 9 行？
This one is subtle.
這個很微妙。
Let's go over here.
讓我們過去那邊看看。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
觀眾： [聽不清]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
大衛·馬蘭：是的。
I'm calling strlen inside of the loop again and again and again.
我在循環裡面不斷地調用 strlen。
Why?
為什麼？
Well, recall how for loops worked.
好吧，回憶一下 for 循環是如何工作的。
When we walked through it last week, that middle part of for loop
上週我們講解時，for 循環中間部分
in between the semicolons keeps getting checked, keeps getting checked,
分號之間的部分會不斷被檢查，不斷被檢查，
keeps getting checked.
不斷被檢查。
And so if you put a function call there, which is totally fine syntactically,
所以，如果你在那裡放一個函數調用，從語法上來說是完全沒問題的，
you're asking the same damn question again and again and again.
你一遍又一遍地問著相同的問題。
And the length of David, D-A-V-I-D, is never changing.
而且 David 的長度，D-A-V-I-D，從未改變。
So strlen, implemented decades ago by some other human,
所以 strlen，在幾十年前由其他人實現，
has some kind of loop in it, and you're literally
它裡面有某種循環，而你實際上
making that code run again and again and again just
不斷地執行那段代碼，
to get the same answer 5 again and again.
一遍又一遍地得到相同的答案 5。
So I think your instinct is right.
所以我認為你的直覺是正確的。
I could come up with another variable outside of the loop.
我可以想出另一個在循環外部的變量。
I could do something like this.
我可以做類似的事情。
int length equals strlen of s, and then I could just plug that in.
int length 等於 s 的 strlen，然後我就可以直接將它代入。
But there's a slightly more elegant way.
但有一個更優雅的方法。
If you like doing things with slightly less code,
如果你喜歡用更少的代碼做事，
this is correct as I've now written it.
這是我現在寫的，是正確的。
It's less efficient-- it's more efficient because I'm only
它效率更低——它效率更高，因為我只
calling strlen once now on this new line 9,
在新的第 9 行調用了一次 strlen，
but a more common way to write this would typically
但更常见的写法通常
be to do something like this.
是像这样做的。
After initializing i, you can also initialize something else like length.
初始化 i 后，还可以初始化其他东西，比如 length。
And you can set length equal to strlen of s, then your semicolon,
然后你可以将 length 设置为 s 的 strlen，然后是分号，
and now you can say while i is less than that length.
现在你可以说，只要 i 小于该长度。
Or I can tighten this up further.
或者我可以进一步紧凑。
If it's just a number and it's a super short loop, might as well just call it
如果它只是一个数字，而且是一个超短的循环，不妨直接称它为
n.
n。
So this now would be a canonical way of implementing the exact same idea,
所以现在将是实现完全相同想法的规范方法，
but without the inefficiency because now you're
但没有效率低下，因为现在你正在
calling strlen in the initialization part of for loop,
在 for 循环的初始化部分调用 strlen，
not inside of the Boolean expression that gets checked and executed
而不是在被检查和执行的布尔表达式内部
again and again.
一次又一次。
Yeah?
对吧？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众： [听不清]
DAVID MALAN: Correct.
大卫·马兰： 正确。
Well, I'm declaring i as an int, but by way of the comma,
好吧，我将 i 声明为一个 int，但通过逗号，
I am also declaring n as an int.
我也将 n 声明为一个 int。
So they've got to be the same type for this trick to work.
所以它们必须是相同类型，才能使这个技巧生效。
Good observation.
好的观察。
Other questions on this one here?
还有其他关于这个的问题吗？
No?
没有？
All right.
好吧。
Well, let's play around further here.
好吧，让我们进一步玩玩。
Let me propose that there's other libraries and header files
我来提议一下，还有其他库和头文件
as well that you might find useful.
也可能对你有用。
There's also something called ctype, which relates to types
还有一个叫做 ctype 的东西，它与类型有关
and c's that's got a bunch of useful functions
和 c 的，它有一堆有用的函数
that we can actually see if we visit the documentation here.
我们实际上可以在这里访问文档来查看。
But before we get there, let me actually whip up
但在我们到达那里之前，让我实际编写一个
a program that maybe does something a little bit fun, albeit low level,
一个程序，它可能做一些有趣的事情，虽然是低级的，
like forcing some string to uppercase if the human types it in lowercase.
比如强制将一些字符串转换为大写，如果用户输入的是小写。
So let me go ahead and write a program called uppercase.c.
所以让我先写一个叫做 uppercase.c 的程序。
Let me go ahead and give myself the same header files.
让我先给自己相同的头文件。
Include cs50.h, include stdio.h.
包含 cs50.h，包含 stdio.h。
And for now, let's include string.h for the length.
现在，让我们包含 string.h 来获取长度。
And let's go ahead and have int main void as before.
然后让我们像以前一样使用 int main void。
And inside of main, let's give myself a string
在 main 内部，让我们给自己一个字符串
s equaling get_string "Before," just so I know what the string is initially.
s 等于 get_string "Before"，这样我就知道字符串最初是什么。
Now I'm going to print out proactively "After" with two spaces
现在我要主动打印 "After" 以及两个空格
just so that things line up aesthetically on the screen
这样东西在屏幕上看起来会比较美观
because "After" is one character shorter.
因为 "After" 短了一个字符。
And now I'm going to do the same technique as before.
现在我要做与之前相同的技巧。
for int i equals 0, n equals the string length of s, i is less than n, i++.
for int i 等于 0，n 等于 s 的字符串长度，i 小于 n，i++。
And then inside of this loop, what do I want to do logically?
然后在这个循环内部，我逻辑上想要做什么？
I want to force these characters to uppercase if they are, in fact,
我想将这些字符强制转换为大写，如果它们实际上是
lowercase.
小写。
And so how might I do this?
那么我该如何做到呢？
Well, there's a bunch of ways to express this,
好吧，有很多种方法可以表达这一点，
but I'm going to do it maybe the most straightforward way
但我可能要采用最直接的方式
even if you've not seen this before.
即使你以前没有见过。
If the current letter in the string at location i,
如果字符串中位置 i 处的当前字母，
because I'm in a loop starting from 0 all the way up to, but not
因为我处在一个从 0 开始一直到，但不是
through the string length, is greater than
字符串长度，大于
or equal to a lowercase a, in single quotes, and that letter is less than
或等于一个单引号中的小写字母 a，并且该字母小于
or equal to a lowercase z.
或等于一个小写字母 z。
What does this mean in English?
用英语来说，这意味着什么？
Well, this essentially means if lowercase--
好吧，这本质上意味着如果小写——
logically, if it's greater than or equal to little a and less than
逻辑上，如果它大于或等于小写字母 a，并且小于
or equal to little z, it's somewhere between and z in lowercase.
或等于小写字母 z，那么它在小写字母 a 和 z 之间。
What do I want to do?
我想做什么？
Well, I want to force it to uppercase.
好吧，我想把它强制转换为大写。
So I want to print out a character without a new line yet
所以我想打印出一个字符，但还没有换行
that prints out the current character, but force it to uppercase.
它打印出当前字符，但强制它转换为大写。
Well, how can I do this?
好吧，我该怎么做呢？
Well, this is where this gets into some low-level hacking,
好吧，这就是它开始进行一些低级黑客操作的地方，
but notice the same ASCII chart.
但请注意相同的 ASCII 表。
Here's our uppercase letters from last time.
这是我们上次的大写字母。
Here's our lowercase characters, and let me highlight those.
这是我们的所有小写字符，让我突出显示它们。
Does anyone notice a relationship between capital A and lowercase a
有人注意到大写字母 A 和小写字母 a 之间的关系吗
that happens to be the same for capital B and lowercase b?
对于大写字母 B 和小写字母 b 也是一样吗？
AUDIENCE: Capital A [INAUDIBLE].
观众： 大写字母 A [听不清]。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
大卫·马兰： 是的。
Like this pattern is true.
就像这个模式是正确的。
So 97 minus 65 is 32, and that's true for every lowercase and uppercase
所以 97 减去 65 等于 32，对于所有的小写字母和大写字母来说都是这样
letter respectively.
字母。
So I can leverage that.
所以我利用了这一点。
And this is not a CS50 thing.
这不是 CS50 的东西。
Like this is ASCII.
就像这是 ASCII。
This is, in turn, Unicode.
反过来，这就是 Unicode。
This is how modern computers work.
这就是现代计算机的工作原理。
So if I go back to VS Code here, you know what I could do.
所以如果我回到 VS Code 这里，你知道我可以做什么。
Let's just literally subtract 32.
让我们直接减去 32。
But because I'm displaying this as a char, not as an int,
但因为我将其显示为 char，而不是 int，
I'm going to see the lowercase letter seemingly become an uppercase instead.
我将看到小写字母似乎变成了大写。
Else, if it's not lowercase-- maybe it's already uppercase,
否则，如果它不是小写——也许它已经是大写了，
maybe it is punctuation, let's just go ahead and print out with %c
也许它是标点符号，让我们直接使用 %c 打印出来
the original character unaltered.
原来的字符不作修改。
And then at the very end of this program,
然后在这个程序的最后，
let's print a new line just to move the cursor to the next line.
让我们打印一个换行符，以便将光标移动到下一行。
All right, so let's do make uppercase.
好了，让我们做 make uppercase。
And let me type ./uppercase.
然后让我输入 ./uppercase。
And I'll type in D-A-V-I-D, all lowercase, and now,
然后我会输入 D-A-V-I-D，全部小写，现在，
you'll see it's in all caps.
你会看到它全部是大写的。
If, though, I type in maybe my last name but capitalized M, that's OK,
但是，如果我输入我的姓氏，但 M 大写，那没关系，
the rest of it will still be capitalized for me.
其余部分仍然会为我大写。
Now I don't love this technique.
我现在不喜欢这种方法。
It's a little bit fragile because I had to do some math.
它有点脆弱，因为我不得不做一些数学运算。
I had to check my reference sheet and then incorporate it into my program.
我不得不查看我的参考表，然后将其整合到我的程序中。
Even though it will be correct, I could be a little more clever.
即使它将是正确的，我也可以更聪明一些。
I could actually do something like this.
我实际上可以做这样的事情。
Well, whatever the value of lowercase is--
好吧，无论小写字母的值是什么 -
lowercase a is minus whatever the value of capital A is,
小写 a 减去大写 A 的值，
and I could actually do it arithmetically even though that, too,
我实际上可以用算术的方式做到，即使这样，
is somewhat inefficient in that it's asking the same question again
效率有点低，因为它一直在问同样的问题
and again, but the compiler is probably smart enough to optimize that.
又问了一次，但编译器可能足够聪明，可以优化它。
And frankly, for those more comfortable, a good compiler
坦率地说，对于那些更熟悉的人来说，一个好的编译器
will also notice, no, no, no, no, you don't
也会注意到，不，不，不，不，你不想
want to call strlen again and again.
一次又一次地调用 strlen。
The compiler can do some of these optimizations for you,
编译器可以为你做一些这些优化，
but it's still good practice to get into yourself.
但养成良好的习惯仍然很重要。
But there's probably a better way.
但可能有一种更好的方法。
Instead of rolling this solution ourselves
与其自己编写这个解决方案
and subtracting 32 or doing any arithmetic,
并减去 32 或做任何算术运算，
let's use that ctype library.
让我们使用那个 ctype 库。
Let me go back up to my header files.
让我回到我的头文件。
Let's additionally include ctype.h.
让我们另外包含 ctype.h。
Let's pretend like I read the documentation in advance, which I did,
让我们假装我已经提前阅读了文档，实际上我已经阅读过了，
in fact.
事实上。
And let's instead of doing any math here,
我们不用在这里进行任何数学运算，
let's use a function that exists in that library called toupper
让我们使用该库中存在的一个名为 toupper 的函数
and pass to it whatever the current character is in s at location i.
并将当前 s 中第 i 个位置的字符传递给它。
Otherwise, I still print out the unchanged character.
否则，我仍然打印出未更改的字符。
And let me go ahead and do make uppercase ./uppercase.
让我继续执行 make uppercase ./uppercase。
And now without any math, no subtracting 32, that, too, also works.
现在不需要任何数学运算，也不需要减去 32，它也同样有效。
But it gets better.
但它变得更好了。
If you read the documentation for toupper,
如果你阅读了 toupper 的文档，
it turns out its documentation tells you, if C is already uppercase,
事实证明，它的文档告诉你，如果 C 已经是大写字母，
it just passes it through for you.
它会直接传递给你。
So you don't even need to ask this conditional question.
所以你甚至不需要问这个条件问题。
I can actually cut this to my clipboard, get rid of all of this,
我实际上可以将其剪切到我的剪贴板，摆脱所有这些，
and just replace that one line only and just
只替换那一行，然后
let toupper handle the situation for me because again, its documentation
让 toupper 为我处理这种情况，因为它的文档
has assured me that if it's already uppercase,
向我保证，如果它已经是大写字母，
it's just going to return the original value.
它只会返回原始值。
So if I make uppercase, this time, ./uppercase,
所以如果我这次执行 make uppercase ./uppercase，
now it works and now things are getting kind of fun.
现在它可以工作了，现在事情变得有点有趣了。
I mean, these are mundane tasks, admittedly,
我的意思是，这些都是平凡的任务，不可否认，
but at least I'm standing on the shoulders of smart people
但至少我站在聪明人的肩膀上
who came before me who implemented the string library, the ctype library--
在我之前实施了字符串库、ctype 库的人 -
heck, even the CS50 Library so I don't need to reinvent any of those wheels.
哎呀，甚至包括 CS50 库，所以我也不需要重新发明轮子。
Questions on any of these library techniques?
关于这些库技巧的任何问题？
It's all still arrays, it's all still strings and chars,
它们仍然是数组，仍然是字符串和字符，
but now we're leveraging libraries to solve some of our problems for us.
但现在我们正在利用库来解决我们的一些问题。
All right.
好的。
So let's come full circle to where we began,
所以让我们回到最初的地方，
where and I mentioned that some programs include
在那里，我提到了一些程序包含
support for command line arguments.
对命令行参数的支持。
Like Clang takes command line arguments words after the word clang.
就像 Clang 会接受在 clang 之后出现的命令行参数。
CD, which you've used in Linux, takes command line arguments.
CD（你在 Linux 中使用过）接受命令行参数。
If you type cd, space, pset1 or cd, space,
如果你输入 cd、空格、pset1 或 cd、空格，
mario in order to change directories into another folder.
mario 来切换目录到另一个文件夹。
If you do rm like I did earlier, you can remove a file
如果你像我之前一样使用 rm，你可以删除一个文件
by using a command line argument, a second word that
通过使用命令行参数，即第二个词，它
tells the computer what to remove.
告诉计算机要删除什么。
Well, it turns out that you, too, can write
事实证明，你也可以编写
code that takes words at the command prompt and uses them as input.
接受命令提示符下的单词并将其用作输入的代码。
Up until now, you and I have only gotten user input via get_string, get_int,
到目前为止，你和我都只通过 get_string、get_int 获取用户输入，
get_float, and functions like that.
get_float 和类似的函数。
You, too, can write code that take command line arguments which,
你也可以编写接受命令行参数的代码，它
frankly, just save the human time.
坦率地说，只是节省了用户的时间。
They can type their entire thought at the command line, hit Enter, and boom,
他们可以在命令行中输入完整的想法，按下回车键，然后，
the program can complete without prompting them and re-prompting them
程序可以完成，而无需提示他们并重新提示他们
again.
再次。
So here's where we can now start to take off some more training wheels.
所以现在我们可以开始去掉更多辅助轮。
Up until now, we've just put void inside of the parentheses here any time
到目前为止，我们只是在括号中放入 void，无论何时
we implement main.
我们实现 main。
It turns out that you can put something else in parentheses
事实证明，你可以在括号中放入其他内容
when using C. It's a mouthful, but you can replace void
在使用 C 时。这是一个很长的词，但你可以用它来替换 void
with this bigger expression.
这个更大的表达式。
But it's two things.
但它有两部分。
int, called argc by convention, and a string,
int，按照惯例称为 argc，以及一个字符串，
but not a string, actually an array of strings called argv.
但实际上不是字符串，而是称为 argv 的字符串数组。
And these terms are a little arcane, but argc means
这些术语有点深奥，但 argc 代表
argument count-- how many words did the human type at the prompt?
参数计数 - 用户在提示符中输入了多少个单词？
Argv stands for argument vector, which is generally
Argv 代表参数向量，通常
another term for an array--
是数组的另一个术语 -
you've heard it perhaps from mathematics.
你可能在数学中听说过它。
It's like a list of values, or in this case, a list of command line arguments.
它就像一个值列表，或者在这种情况下，一个命令行参数列表。
So C is special.
所以 C 是特殊的。
If you declare main as not taking void inside of parentheses, but rather,
如果你将 main 声明为不接受括号内的 void，而是接受
an int and an array of strings, C will figure out
一个 int 和一个字符串数组，C 会弄清楚
whatever the human typed at the prompt and hand it to you
用户在提示符中输入的内容，并将它传递给你
as an array and the length thereof.
作为一个数组及其长度。
So if I want to leverage this, I can start
所以如果我想利用这一点，我可以开始
to implement some programs of my own that actually incorporate command line
实现我自己的程序，这些程序实际上包含命令行
arguments.
参数。
For instance, let me go back in a moment here to VS Code.
例如，让我回到 VS Code 中。
Let me create a program, for instance, called greet.c
让我创建一个程序，例如，名为 greet.c
that's just going to greet the user in a few different ways.
它只是用几种不同的方式来问候用户。
So let me first do it the old way. cs50.h.
所以让我先用老方法。cs50.h。
Let me include stdio.h.
让我包含stdio.h。
Let me do int main void still.
让我仍然使用int main void。
So the old way.
所以是老方法。
And if I want to greet myself or Carter or Yulie or anyone else,
如果我想问候我自己、卡特、尤里或其他人，
I could do, old fashioned now, get the answer from the user, get_string.
我可以使用老方法，从用户那里获取答案，get_string。
Let's prompt for "What's your name?" question mark,
让我们提示“你叫什么名字？”问号，
just like we did in Scratch.
就像我们在Scratch中做的那样。
And then do printf, "Hello," comma, %s backslash n, answer.
然后执行printf，“你好，”逗号，%s 反斜杠n，答案。
So we've done this many times now this week and last.
所以我们这周和上周已经做了很多次了。
This is the old school way now of getting command line--
现在，这是从命令行获取用户输入的传统方式——
of getting user input by prompting them for it.
通过提示用户获取用户输入。
So if I do make greet /greet, there's no command line arguments at the prompt,
所以如果我执行make greet /greet，提示符中没有命令行参数，
I'm literally just running the program's name.
我只是在运行程序的名称。
If I hit Enter, though, now get_string kicks in, asks me for my name,
但是，如果我按Enter，get_string现在开始工作，会询问我的姓名，
and the program then greets me.
然后程序会向我问候。
But I can do--
但我可以——
otherwise, I could do something like this instead.
否则，我可以尝试这样操作。
First, answer's a little generic, so let's first change
首先，answer有点泛泛，所以让我们先更改
this back to name and back to name, but that's a minor improvement there
将其改回name，但那只是一个小的改进
just stylistically.
只是从风格上来说。
Let's, though, introduce now a command line argument
但是，让我们现在引入一个命令行参数
so that I can just greet myself by running the program, hitting Enter,
这样我就可以通过运行程序、按Enter键来问候自己，
and being done, no more get_string.
然后就完成了，不再需要get_string。
So I'm going to go ahead and change void to int argc, string
所以我将把void改为int argc，string
argv with square brackets.
带方括号的argv。
string means-- the square brackets means it's an array;
string代表——方括号意味着它是一个数组；
string means it's an array of strings; and argc, again,
string意味着它是一个字符串数组；而argc，再次强调，
is just an integer of the number of words typed.
只是一个表示输入单词数量的整数。
Now I'm going to somewhat dangerously going to do this.
现在我要冒险尝试一下。
I'm going to get rid of my use of get_string altogether,
我要完全放弃使用get_string，
and I'm going to change this line to be not name, which no longer exists,
我要更改这一行，不再使用name，因为name不存在了，
but I'm going to go into this array called argv
而是要进入这个名为argv的数组
and I'm going to go into location 1.
并进入第1个位置。
So I'm doing this on faith.
所以我凭着信念去做。
I haven't explained what I'm doing yet, but I'm going to do make greet ./greet,
我还没有解释我在做什么，但我将执行make greet ./greet，
and now I'm going to type my name at the command line just like with rm,
现在我要在命令行中输入我的姓名，就像使用rm一样，
with clang, with cd.
使用clang、使用cd。
With any of the commands you've written with multiple words,
对于你使用多个单词编写的任何命令，
I'm going to greet literally David.
我将直接向David问候。
So I hit Enter, and voila, I've somehow gotten access
所以，我按Enter键，瞧，我不知何故获得了访问权限
to what I typed at the prompt by accessing this special parameter called
通过访问这个名为argv的特殊参数，可以访问我在提示符中输入的内容
argv.
argv。
Technically you could call it anything you want, but the convention is
从技术上讲，你可以随意命名它，但惯例是
argv and argc from right to left here.
这里从右到左使用argv和argc。
Just a guess, then.
只是猜测而已。
What if I change this to print out bracket 0 and recompile the code?
如果我将此更改为打印方括号0，并重新编译代码？
And I run ./greet David?
然后我运行./greet David？
What might it say instinctively?
它会直觉地说些什么呢？
Any hunches?
有什么预感吗？
Yeah.
是的。
So it's going to say hello, ./greet.
所以它会说你好，./greet。
So it turns out, you get one for free.
所以事实证明，你得到一个免费的。
Whatever the name of your program is always
无论你的程序名称是什么，始终
accessible in argv at location 0.
可在argv的第0个位置访问。
That's just because.
这是因为。
It's a handy feature.
这是一个方便的功能。
In case there's an error or you need to tell the user how to use the program,
如果出现错误，或者你需要告诉用户如何使用程序，
you know what the command is that they ran, but at location 1,
你就会知道他们运行的命令是什么，但是在第1个位置，
maybe 2, maybe 3 are the additional words
可能是2、3或更多，是用户在命令行中输入的额外单词
that the human might have typed in.
用户可能输入的。
Well, let's do something a little smarter than this.
好吧，让我们尝试一些比这更聪明的做法。
Let me go back to version 1.
让我回到版本1。
Let me recompile it, make greet.
让我重新编译它，make greet。
Let me rerun ./greet David, and this seems to work fine.
让我重新运行./greet David，看起来工作正常。
What if I get a little curious and print out location 2?
如果我有点好奇，打印出第2个位置？
Let me recompile the code, make greet ./greet David, Enter, OK, there's null.
让我重新编译代码，make greet ./greet David，Enter，OK，那里是null。
And I mentioned we'd see N-U-L-L, and here's one incarnation thereof,
我提到过我们会看到N-U-L-L，这里就是其中一个体现，
but this is clearly wrong.
但这明显是错误的。
So I probably don't want to even let the user do this because I
所以，我可能不想让用户这样做，因为我
don't want them to see bogus output.
不想让他们看到错误的输出。
Like this is arguably the a bug in the code
就像这可能是一个代码中的错误
that it even bothered to show this by default. So what could I do instead?
它默认情况下甚至还显示了这一点。那我可以怎么做呢？
Well, what if I do this?
那么，如果我这样做呢？
If argc equals equals 2, then go ahead and comfortably
如果argc等于2，那么就可以轻松地
say printf "hello," argv, bracket, 1.
说printf “你好，”argv，方括号，1。
Else, if the human did not give exactly two arguments at the prompt,
否则，如果用户在提示符中没有给出恰好两个参数，
let's just print out some default value like "hello, world"
我们就打印出一些默认值，例如“你好，世界”
like from last week.
就像上周一样。
In other words now I'm doing this error checking with a conditional,
换句话说，我现在正在使用条件语句进行错误检查，
making sure with this Boolean expression only
确保只有这个布尔表达式
if argc equals equals 2, and therefore has two words in argv
如果argc等于2，因此argv中包含两个单词
do you want to proceed.
是否要继续。
And so now if I do make greet again, ./greet David, this now works.
所以，现在如果我再次执行make greet，./greet David，这就可以正常工作了。
But if I don't cooperate and I just run greet, what should it say?
但是，如果我不配合，只是运行greet，它应该说些什么呢？
Just hello, world.
就说你好，世界。
If I run David Malan as two words, what should it say?
如果我运行David Malan作为两个单词，它应该说些什么呢？
hello, world, because that's not exactly equal to 2.
你好，世界，因为那并不完全等于2。
Again, the first word in argv is always the program's name.
再次强调，argv中的第一个单词始终是程序的名称。
The second word is whatever the human, then, has typed.
第二个单词就是用户输入的。
Now if we don't even know in advance how many words they're going to be,
现在，如果我们事先不知道用户会输入多少个单词，
we can combine today's ideas.
我们可以将今天的想法结合起来。
This is going to look a little weird, but it's the same thing as before.
这看起来有点奇怪，但和以前一样。
for int i gets 0, i is less than--
for int i 获取0，i小于——
how about argc i++?
argc i++怎么样？
And then inside of this loop, I can print out %s, maybe backslash n, comma,
然后在这个循环内部，我可以打印出%s，也许还有反斜杠n，逗号，
and then print out argv, bracket, i.
然后打印 argv，括号和 i。
So I can have a loop that iterates argc number of times,
所以我可以有一个循环，迭代 argc 次，
once for every word at the prompt.
每次迭代都对应于命令提示符中的一个单词。
I can print out argv, bracket, i, which is the i-th word in that array
我可以打印 argv，括号和 i，它是数组中的第 i 个单词
from left to right.
从左到右。
And so if I now run make greet and I do ./greet alone,
所以，如果我现在运行 make greet 并执行 ./greet，
I just see the program's name.
我只会看到程序的名称。
If I do ./greet David, I see, those two, one after the other.
如果我执行 ./greet David，我会看到这两个单词，一个接一个。
If I do David Malan, I get those three words.
如果我执行 David Malan，我会得到这三个单词。
If I keep going, I'll get more and more words.
如果我继续输入，我会得到越来越多的单词。
So using just the length of the array and the name of the array,
所以，只使用数组的长度和数组的名称，
I can actually do quite a bit there.
我实际上可以做很多事情。
Now there's actually some fun things you can do with this,
现在，实际上有一些有趣的事情你可以用它来做，
and this is sort of beside the point, but there's
这有点偏离主题了，但是，
this thing in the world called ASCII art, which
世界上有一种叫做 ASCII 艺术的东西，它
is making pictures and beautiful things just using ASCII or maybe
就是使用 ASCII 或者可能是
nowadays Unicode characters, but without using emoji.
现在是 Unicode 字符，但没有使用表情符号。
Like emoji kind of make this a little too easy.
就像表情符号让这变得太容易了。
But if all you have are traditional largely English letters
但是如果你只有传统的，大部分是英文的字母
and punctuation, you can actually do some interesting things.
和标点符号，你实际上可以做一些有趣的事情。
On Linux systems-- for instance, if I go back to VS Code here,
在 Linux 系统上——例如，如果我回到这里的 VS Code，
let me increase the size of my terminal window here.
让我在这里增加终端窗口的大小。
And it turns out that we've pre-installed-- really,
事实证明，我们已经预先安装了——实际上，
for no compelling reason, but just for fun, a program called cowsay,
没有充分的理由，只是为了好玩，一个叫做 cowsay 的程序，
which has a cow say something.
它可以让一头奶牛说一些话。
So if I want to have a cow say "moo" in ASCII art, I can do this,
所以，如果我想让一头奶牛用 ASCII 艺术说“哞”，我可以这样做，
and you get an adorable cow saying something like "moo" on the screen.
你将会在屏幕上看到一只可爱的奶牛说“哞”。
But moo is a command line argument that is clearly
但是 moo 是一个命令行参数，它显然
modifying the output of this program because I could also
修改了这个程序的输出，因为我也可以
change it to say hello, comma, world, and now the cow
把它改为说 hello，逗号，world，现在奶牛
is going to say that instead.
将会说这句话。
So it takes multiple command line arguments, if you will.
所以它接受多个命令行参数，如果你愿意。
But it also takes what are called flags or switches whereby any command line
但是它也接受被称为标志或开关的东西，任何以破折号开头的命令行
argument that starts with a dash is usually like a special configuration
参数通常就像一个特殊的配置
option that you would only know exists by reading the documentation
选项，你只有通过阅读文档才会知道它的存在
or seeing a demonstration.
或者看到演示。
And if I have my syntax right, if I do cowsay -f, and maybe I'll do--
如果我的语法正确，如果我执行 cowsay -f，也许我会——
let's see.
让我们看看。
Instead of this cow say, how about I'll do -f for file,
与其让这头奶牛说，不如让我执行 -f 来表示文件，
and I'm going to change it into duck mode.
我将把它改为鸭子模式。
And I'm going to have this version of the ASCII art say quack.
我将让这个版本的 ASCII 艺术说 quack。
So it's a tiny little duck there, but it's saying quack.
所以，那是一只小鸭子，但是它说 quack。
And you can kind of waste a lot of time doing this.
你可以用这种方式浪费很多时间。
I can do cowsay -f dragon and say something like, RAWR,
我可以执行 cowsay -f dragon 并说类似 RAWR 的东西，
and this is just amazing.
这简直太棒了。
Again, not really academically compelling,
再说一次，从学术的角度来看，这并不令人信服，
but it does demonstrate, again, command line arguments, which are everywhere,
但是它确实再次演示了命令行参数，它们无处不在，
and you've indeed been using them already.
你实际上已经在使用它们了。
But there's one other feature we wanted to introduce you
但是，我们想向你介绍另一个功能
to today, which will be a useful building block, which will also
今天，它将是一个有用的构建模块，它也将
reveal one other thing about the code that we've been writing.
揭示我们一直在编写的代码中的另一个东西。
It turns out that all of the programs we've been writing thus far, eventually
事实证明，我们到目前为止编写的程序，最终
obviously exit because you see your prompt again
显然会退出，因为你又看到了你的命令提示符
unless you have an infinite loop such that it never ends.
除非你有一个无限循环，这样它就永远不会结束。
But eventually they exit.
但最终它们会退出。
And secretly, every program we've written thus far actually
而且，秘密地，我们到目前为止编写的每个程序实际上
has what's called an exit status.
都有一个叫做退出状态的东西。
It's like a special return value from the program
这就像程序本身的一个特殊返回值
itself that by default is always 0.
它默认情况下总是 0。
0 as a number in the world generally means everything's OK.
在世界上，0 通常意味着一切正常。
The flip side of that is because the world tends to use integers
另一方面，由于世界倾向于使用整数
and you've got four billion possibilities,
你有四十亿种可能性，
like every other number in the world when it comes to our program's exit
就像世界上其他任何数字一样，当谈到我们程序的退出
status is bad.
状态时，意味着是错误的。
If it's 1, it's probably bad.
如果是 1，它可能是错误的。
If it's negative 1, it's bad.
如果是负 1，它也是错误的。
And in fact, you've probably seen this in the real world.
事实上，你可能在现实世界中见过这种情况。
If you've ever had like a random error message on the screen--
如果你曾经在屏幕上看到过随机的错误消息——
here's a screenshot of Zoom, for instance.
例如，这是 Zoom 的一个截图。
And that screenshot, somewhat confusingly or unknowingly,
这个截图，有点令人困惑，或者说并不知情，
has an error code like 1132, that probably
有一个像 1132 这样的错误代码，这可能
means that the Zoom software that some other humans wrote incorrectly somehow
意味着 Zoom 软件，由其他人编写，不知何故写错了，
had an error and it did not exit with status 0, it exited with status 1132.
出现了错误，它没有以状态 0 退出，而是以状态 1132 退出。
And somewhere at Zoom, there's probably a file
在 Zoom 的某个地方，可能有一个文件
or a book that tells the programmers what this error code actually means.
或者一本书，告诉程序员这个错误代码的真正含义。
This is not useful for you and me.
这对我们来说没有用。
There's some programmer at Zoom who would probably be like,
Zoom 的某些程序员可能会说，
oh, I know what I did or my colleague did wrong in this case.
哦，我知道我或者我的同事在这个案例中做错了什么。
You've seen this elsewhere even though this is not quite the same thing,
你之前在其他地方见过这种情况，尽管它并不完全相同，
but we'll talk about this in a few weeks.
但我们将在几周后讨论它。
If you've ever seen 404, like numbers are everywhere, and on the web,
如果你曾经见过 404，就像数字无处不在，在网络上也是，
404 means like file not found.
404 表示文件未找到。
It means you made a typo, the web server deleted a file, or something like that,
这意味着你打错了字，Web 服务器删除了一个文件，或者类似的事情，
but this is just to say numbers are so often used to signify or represent
但是，这只是说数字经常用来表示或代表
errors.
错误。
Even though that's not an exit status, per se,
尽管它本身不是退出状态，
that's an HTTP status code, which we'll soon see.
那是 HTTP 状态码，我们很快就会看到。
But you have access to exit statuses as it relates
但是，你可以访问与
to command line software already.
命令行软件相关的退出状态。
Up until now, this is how we've been writing main, now
到目前为止，我们一直是这样编写 main 函数的，现在
with command line arguments, but we've also
有了命令行参数，但我们还有
been writing main with an int return value.
我一直在写主函数，它有一个整型返回值。
And you've never used this-- we didn't talk about this last week.
而且你从来没有用过它——我们上周没有讨论过这个。
I just ask that you trust me and just keep copying and pasting this.
我只要求你相信我，并继续复制粘贴这段代码。
But that int means that even your programs
但是，这个int意味着，即使是你的程序
can return values which can be useful even if you don't use command line
可以返回值，即使你不使用命令行，这些返回值也可能很有用
arguments and we just go back to the original version like void.
参数，我们只是回到像void这样的原始版本。
So for instance, if I go ahead and open up, for instance, VS Code again,
例如，如果我继续打开，例如，VS Code 再次，
I'll get rid of the dragon.
我会去掉那个龙。
And let's do one other program here called status just
让我们在这里做一个名为status的程序，只是
to play around with the idea of these so-called exit statuses.
为了玩玩这些所谓的退出状态的想法。
Let me just demonstrate the idea with an include cs50.h, include
让我用一个 include cs50.h, include 来演示这个想法
stdio.h, int main, and here I'll do int argc, string argv.
stdio.h, int main, 这里我将使用 int argc, string argv。
And then inside of main, let's do a similar program
然后在main内部，让我们做一个类似的程序
to before like the hello, world.
类似于之前的hello, world。
So printf "hello," comma, %s backslash n.
所以 printf "hello," 逗号, %s 反斜杠 n。
Then let's print out argv 1.
然后让我们打印argv 1。
But I only want to execute that line if the human gave me a command line
但是我只想在用户给我一个命令行参数的情况下执行那行代码
argument.
参数。
Otherwise I don't want to even say some default like hello, world.
否则我甚至不想说一些默认的，比如 hello, world。
I just want to abort early and just exit the program, no output whatsoever.
我只是想提前中止并退出程序，没有任何输出。
So I could do this.
所以我可以这样做。
If argc does not equal 2--
如果argc不等于2——
and it's a single equals, but it's a bang, an exclamation point,
这是一个单等号，但它是一个感叹号，
means not equal.
表示不等于。
So this is the opposite of equals equals.
所以这是等于等于的反义词。
Then previously I would have just printed hello, world,
然后之前我只会打印hello, world，
but now I want to print out an error message
但现在我想打印一个错误信息
like, "Missing command-line argument" just to explain to the user
比如，“缺少命令行参数”，只是为了向用户解释
why the program is about to terminate, and then I can return 1.
为什么程序即将终止，然后我可以返回1。
It's kind of arbitrary.
这有点随意。
I could also return 1132, but why start there?
我也可以返回1132，但为什么要从那里开始呢？
This is the only possible error that could go wrong in my program.
这是我的程序中唯一可能出错的地方。
So I'm going to start at 1.
所以我将从1开始。
Zoom clearly has 1,000-plus possible things that can go wrong
Zoom显然有1000多个可能出错的地方
in their source code, which is why the number got as big as 1132,
在他们的源代码中，这就是为什么这个数字达到了1132，
but I'm just going to arbitrarily, but conventionally return 1.
但我只是随意地，但按照惯例返回1。
But if everything is OK and I do-- it is not the case that argc does not equal 2
但是如果一切正常，我做到了——argc 不等于 2 并不是事实
and I actually get to line 11, I'm going to return 0 because 0, again, I claim,
而我实际上到达了第11行，我将返回0，因为0，我再次声明，
signifies success.
表示成功。
And all of this time, every program we've written-- you've written
一直以来，我们写的每一个程序——你写的
has secretly exited with 0 by default. But now
默认情况下，已经秘密地以0退出。但是现在
that our programs are getting more sophisticated,
我们的程序变得越来越复杂，
when something goes wrong, it turns out it's
当出现错误时，事实证明，它
useful to have the power to just return some other value even
能够返回其他值非常有用，即使
though the user is not going to see it.
用户不会看到它。
Even though the Zoom user shouldn't see it, it's still there.
尽管Zoom用户不应该看到它，但它仍然存在。
It's diagnostically useful to you, or in the case of a class,
这对你有诊断意义，或者在一个班级的情况下，
to your TF or TA or CA.
对你自己的TF、TA或CA。
So if I do make status now to compile this program and run ./status and type
所以如果我现在用 make status 来编译这个程序，然后运行 ./status 并输入
my first name I think this is a success.
我的名字，我认为这是成功的。
It should say hello, David and secretly exit with 0.
它应该说 hello, David 并且秘密地以 0 退出。
If you really want to see the 0, there's this arcane command you can type.
如果你真的想看到 0，有一个晦涩的命令你可以输入。
You can literally type at your prompt echo $?.
你可以在你的提示符下输入 echo $?。
It's weird symbology, but it's what the humans chose decades ago.
这是一个奇怪的符号，但这是人类几十年前选择的方式。
This will just show you what did the most recently-run program secretly exit
这将向你展示最近运行的程序秘密地退出了什么
with.
状态。
So if I do this in VS Code, I can do exit $?, Enter,
所以如果我在 VS Code 中这样做，我可以输入 exit $?，回车，
and there's that secret 0.
那里就有那个秘密的 0。
I could have been doing this week and last week, it's
我本来可以在本周和上周做的，它
just not that interesting.
只是不那么有趣。
But it is interesting, or at least marginally so, if I rerun status
但如果我重新运行 status，它很有趣，或者至少有点意思
and maybe I don't provide a command line argument or I provide too many.
也许我没有提供命令行参数，或者我提供了太多。
So argc does not equal 2.
所以 argc 不等于 2。
And I hit Enter, I get yelled at with the error message,
我按下回车键，我收到一个错误信息，
but I can see the secret status code, which is, indeed, 1.
但我可以看到秘密的状态代码，它确实是 1。
And so now if you're ever in the habit in either a class like this
所以现在，如果你习惯于在一个像这样的课堂上
or in the real world where you're automatically testing your code,
或者在现实世界中，你自动测试你的代码，
be it with check50 or in the real world, things called
无论是使用 check50 还是在现实世界中，被称为
unit tests and other third-party software,
单元测试和其他第三方软件，
those tests can actually detect these status code-- exit statuses
这些测试实际上可以检测到这些状态代码——退出状态
and know that your code succeed or fail, 0 or 1.
并知道你的代码成功或失败，0 或 1。
And if there's different types of failures it can detect--
如果存在不同的失败类型，它可以检测到——
status 2, status 3, status 1132, it's just one other tool in your toolkit.
状态 2，状态 3，状态 1132，它只是你的工具箱中的另一个工具。
But all of that is terribly low level, and really,
但这一切都非常底层，实际上，
the goal of this week-- and really, today, and really, code more generally,
本周的目标——实际上，今天，实际上，更广泛地说，代码
is to solve problems.
是为了解决问题。
So let's consider an increasingly important one, which
所以让我们考虑一个越来越重要的，那就是
is the ability to send information securely,
安全发送信息的能力，
whether it is in file format, wirelessly, or any other.
无论是文件格式，无线传输，还是其他任何方式。
Cryptography is the art and the science of encrypting.
密码学是加密的艺术和科学。
Scrambling information.
对信息进行加密。
So that even if I write a secret message to you
这样，即使我写了一封秘密信息给你
and I send it through this open audience with so many nosey eyes
而我把它通过这个开放的观众发送出去，有那么多爱管闲事的人
who could look at the message, if I've encrypted this message, none of them
他们可以查看信息，如果我对信息进行了加密，他们中没有人
should be able to read it, only you, whoever you are,
应该能够读到它，只有你，无论你是谁，
to whom I intended that message.
我打算把信息发给谁。
In the world of cryptography, then encryption
在密码学的世界里，加密
means scrambling the information so that only you and the recipient
意味着对信息进行加密，以便只有你和接收者
can receive it.
可以收到它。
So if we consider our black box like in week 0 and 1,
所以如果我们考虑第0周和第1周的黑色盒子，
here is the problem to be solved.
这就是要解决的问题。
And let me propose a couple of pieces of vocabulary.
并且让我提出几个词汇。
Plaintext is any message written in English or any human language
明文是指任何用英语或任何人类语言写成的信息
that you want to send and write yourself.
你想要发送并自己写的。
Ciphertext is what you want to convert it
密文是你想要转换的东西
to before you just hand it off to a bunch of random strangers
在你把它交给一群随机的陌生人之前
in the audience or a bunch of servers on the internet,
在观众中或互联网上的一堆服务器中，
any one of whom could look at your message.
任何一个都可以看到你的信息。
So in the black box is what we're going to call
所以，在黑盒子里，我们将它称为
a cipher, an algorithm for encrypting or scrambling information
密码，一种用于加密或扰乱信息的算法
in a reversible way.
以可逆的方式。
It doesn't suffice to just scramble the information randomly,
仅仅随机地打乱信息是不够的，
otherwise the recipient can't do anything with it.
否则接收者将无法对其进行任何操作。
It's an algorithm, a cipher that encrypts it in such a way
这是一种算法，一种以某种方式加密它的密码
that someone else can decrypt it.
以便其他人可以解密它。
And here's a common way.
这是一个常见的方法。
Most ciphers take as input not only the plaintext message in English
大多数密码不仅将英语中的明文信息作为输入
or whatever else, but also a key.
或其他任何东西，而且还有一个密钥。
And it's metaphorically like a key to open a lock,
它就像打开锁的钥匙一样，
but it's technically generally a number, like a really big number made up
但从技术上讲，它通常是一个数字，就像一个很大的数字
of lots of bits.
由很多位组成。
And not even 32, not even 64, sometimes 1,024 bits, which is crazy
甚至不是 32 位，甚至不是 64 位，有时是 1024 位，这太疯狂了
unpronounceable large, but the probability
难以发音的巨大，但概率
that someone is going to guess your key is just so, so small
有人会猜出你的密钥的概率非常非常小
that for all intents and purposes, you are, in fact, secure.
以至于从所有意图和目的来看，你实际上是安全的。
So what's an example of this, for instance?
例如，这是什么例子呢？
Suppose the secret message I want to send is innocuously just "HI!"
假设我想要发送的秘密信息仅仅是无害的“HI！”
Well, it'd be pretty stupid to write "HI!" on a piece of paper,
好吧，在纸上写“HI！”会很愚蠢，
hand it to someone in the audience, and expect
把它递给观众中的某个人，并期望
it to get all the way to the back without someone like glancing at it
它能一路传到后面，而不会有人看到它
and obviously seeing and reading the plaintext.
而且显然看到并阅读了明文。
So what if I, though, agree with someone in back, for instance,
所以，如果我，比如说，同意坐在后面的人，
that our secret is going to be 1?
我们的秘密将是 1？
And we have to agree upon that secret in advance,
我们必须事先就这个秘密达成一致，
but 1 just means that is my key.
但 1 仅仅意味着那就是我的密钥。
And let me propose that according to one popular cipher,
让我提议，根据一种流行的密码，
if I want to send "HI!", change the H to an I and the I to a J-- that is,
如果我想发送“HI！”，将 H 变成 I，将 I 变成 J，也就是说，
increment effectively every letter of the alphabet by one,
将字母表中的每个字母有效地增加 1，
and if you get to a Z, wrap back around to A, for instance.
如果你到了 Z，就回到 A，例如。
So shift the alphabet by one place in this case
所以，在这种情况下，将字母表向后移一位
and send this message now instead.
现在改发这条消息。
So is that secure?
那么，这安全吗？
Well, if one of you kind of nosily looks at this sheet of paper,
好吧，如果你们中的某个人偷偷地看这张纸，
you won't see "HI!"
你不会看到“HI！”
You will see some information leak in this algorithm.
你会看到一些信息泄露在这个算法中。
You'll see an exclamation point, so I'm enthusiastically saying something,
你会看到一个感叹号，所以我很热情地说着什么，
but you won't know what the message is unless you decrypt it.
但你不会知道信息是什么，除非你解密它。
Now that said, is this very secure, really, in practice?
话虽如此，但这在实践中真的非常安全吗？
I mean, not really.
我的意思是，不完全是。
Like, if you know I'm just using a key and I'm using the English alphabet,
比如，如果你知道我只是用了一个密钥，而且我用的是英语字母表，
you could probably brute force your way to a solution
你可能可以通过蛮力破解找到解决方案
by just trying 1, trying 2, trying 3, trying 25,
通过不断尝试 1，尝试 2，尝试 3，尝试 25，
go through all the possibilities tediously,
费力地尝试所有可能性，
but eventually it's probably going to pop out.
但最终它可能会跳出来。
This is actually known, though, as the Caesar cipher.
这实际上被称为凯撒密码。
And back in the day, before anyone else knew about or had invented encryption,
在过去，在其他人知道或发明加密之前，
Caesar, Julius Caesar, was known to use a cipher like this
凯撒，尤利乌斯·凯撒，以使用这样的密码而闻名
using a key of three, literally.
使用了一个 3 的密钥，真是的。
And I guess it works OK if you're literally the first human in the world
我想，如果你确实是世界上第一个想到这个主意的人
by lore to have thought of this idea, but of course, anyone who intercepts it
据说，但当然，任何截获它的人
could attack it nonetheless and figure things out a bit mathematically.
仍然可以攻击它，并用数学方法弄清楚一些事情。
13 is more common.
13 比较常见。
This is called ROT13 on the internet for rotate the letters of the alphabet 13.
这在互联网上被称为 ROT13，表示将字母表中的字母旋转 13 位。
That changes "HI!" to "UV!"
这将“HI！”变成“UV！”
You might think what's better than 13?
你可能会想，什么比 13 更好呢？
Well, let's double the security.
好吧，让我们将安全性提高一倍。
ROT26.
ROT26。
Why is this stupid?
为什么这很愚蠢？
I mean, there's like 26 letters in the alphabet, so like A becomes A. So
我的意思是，字母表中有 26 个字母，所以 A 就变成了 A。所以
that doesn't really help-- oh, wait.
这并没有真正帮助——哦，等等。
Oh, I'm pointing at something that's not on the screen, dammit.
哦，我在指向屏幕上没有的东西，该死。
Suppose the message is more lovingly, "I LOVE YOU," instead of just "HI!"
假设信息更深情一些，是“I LOVE YOU”，而不是仅仅是“HI！”
Same exact approach, whether or not there's punctuation, "I LOVE YOU,"
相同的方法，无论是否有标点符号，“I LOVE YOU”，
with an input of 13 might now become this.
输入 13 现在可能会变成这样。
And now it's getting a little less obvious what the ciphertext actually
现在，密文实际上代表什么变得不那么明显了
represents.
代表。
And now, what's twice as secure is 13?
现在，什么比 13 安全两倍呢？
Well, 26 is surely better, but of course, if you rotate 26 places,
好吧，26 当然更好，但当然，如果你旋转 26 位，
that, of course, just gives you the same thing.
当然，这只会给你相同的东西。
So there's a limit to this, but again, that just
所以，这有它的局限性，但同样，这仅仅
speaks to the cipher being used, which is very simple.
说明了所使用的密码非常简单。
There is much, much better, more sophisticated mathematical ciphers
有更多更好的，更复杂的数学密码
that are used.
被使用。
We're just starting with something simple here.
我们只是从这里开始一个简单的例子。
As for decryption, if I'm using a key of 1, how do I reverse the process?
关于解密，如果我使用的是 1 的密钥，我该如何逆转这个过程呢？
Yeah, so I just minus 1.
是的，所以我只需要减 1。
So B becomes A, C becomes B, A becomes Z. And if it's 13,
所以 B 变成 A，C 变成 B，A 变成 Z。如果它是 13，
I subtract 13 instead or whatever the key is, so long as sender
我就会减去 13 或者任何密钥，只要发送者
and receiver actually know it.
和接收者都知道它。
So in this case here, this is actually the message with which we began class.
所以，在这种情况下，这实际上就是我们开始上课时使用的那条信息。
If we have this message here and I used a key of 1 to encrypt it,
如果我们有这条信息，我用 1 的密钥加密了它，
well, decrypting, it might involve doing something like this.
好吧，解密，它可能涉及做一些类似的事情。
Here's those same letters on the screen, and I think in a moment
这是屏幕上相同的字母，我想过一会儿
before we adjourn, I'll mention too that we
在我们休会之前，我还想提一下，我们
might have encrypted a message in eight characters
可能在八个字符中加密了一条信息
this whole day, so if any of you took the time
这一整天，所以如果你有时间
and procrastinated and figured out what the light bulb spelled
然后拖延时间并弄清楚灯泡拼出了什么
and they didn't seem to spell anything in English,
而且它们似乎没有拼出任何英语单词
well, here now is the solution for cracking it.
那么，现在这里就是破解它的解决方案。
This, if I subtract 1, becomes what?
如果我减去 1，它会变成什么？
U becomes T. And this is obviously-- see where we're going with this?
U 变成 T。很明显—— 你明白我要表达的意思吗？
And if we keep going, subtracting 1-- so indeed, we're at the end of class
如果我们继续下去，减去 1—— 所以的确，我们已经到了课堂的最后
now because this was CS50.
现在是因为这是 CS50。
And the last thing we have to say is we have hundreds of ducks waiting for you
最后我们要说的是，我们有数百只鸭子在等着你
outside.
在外面。
So on the way out, grab your own rubber duck.
所以出门的时候，拿上你自己的橡皮鸭。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]